<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands triumph a more exact history of His Majesties escape after the battle of Worcester : with a chronologicall discourse of his straits and dangerous adventures into France, his removes from place to place till his return into England with the most remarkable memorials since : to this present September, 1660.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 254 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23871</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07916316</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07916316</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40427</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38443)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40427)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1205:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands triumph a more exact history of His Majesties escape after the battle of Worcester : with a chronologicall discourse of his straits and dangerous adventures into France, his removes from place to place till his return into England with the most remarkable memorials since : to this present September, 1660.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. for Nathaniel Brook,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: England's triumph, a more exact history of K. Charls the II.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40427:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40427:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Englands Triumph.</p>
            <p>A MORE EXACT HISTORY OF HIS Majeſties Eſcape After the Battle of <hi>WORCESTER, WITH</hi> A Chronologicall Diſcourſe of His Straits and dangerous Adventures into <hi>France,</hi> and His Removes from place to place till His return into <hi>England,</hi> with the moſt Remarkable Memorials ſince, to this preſent <hi>SEPTEMBER,</hi> 1660.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J.G.</hi> for NATHANIEL BROOK, and are to be ſold at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:40427:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40427:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE BY WAY OF ARGUMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ever did any age (in this Nation moſt eſpecially of all the reſt of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world,) afford more matter for a full and copious Hiſtory then theſe <hi>12.</hi> last years have done, wherein after a Mysterious war waged for and againſt the King, (if we look at what was pretended and what was acted,) the after game was playd by a party not the ſame with thoſe who at firſt undertook the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for the ſervants taking it out of the hands of thoſe that hir'd them and ſet them on work, and drawing it on to a far higher pitch of violence then was at firſt intended; brought their King (a moſt Noble and Pious Prince) to an untimely death, and
<pb facs="tcp:40427:3"/>utterly rejecting and proſcribing all the Royall race, ſubverted the ancient government of the Nation, and chang'd it into a kind of a Free-State, as they call'd it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or Common-wealth, during which the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable affair that happened was a war with the Dutch, and that carried on with no bad ſucceſs; but not many years did this form of government hold; for <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> Generall of this new States army, having ſubdued the Scotch Nation, and by too unequall ſtrength of arms forced the then heir apparent to the Crown, His Now gracious Majesty, (who came with arms, after all fair means uſed in vain, to aſſert his just claim,) to quit the Kingdome, violently uſurped the ſupream authority into his own hands, which having kept with much adoe by a high hand for his own life time, he alſo us'd ſuch means at his death, that he procured to have the chief Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy of the three Nations transferr'd to his Eldeſt Son <hi>Richard,</hi> which he held for a little while, till the Souldiery wanting other action to divert them, or an <hi>Oliver</hi> to keep them under, took an occaſion to mutinie, and making uſe of Protector <hi>Richards</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to diſſolve the Parliament he had called, lay'd him aſide and invited in again the remnant of the long Parliament, which <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> had ſome years ſince diſſolved to make way for his own advancement to the Supreame Authority. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth intereſt thus reſtor'd, there ſeem'd now no other hopes, but a Free-State muſt ſeize us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:40427:3"/>any redreſſe; yet neither had this convention ſate many months ere <hi>Lambert,</hi> ſpirited with his ſucceſs againſt Sir <hi>George Booth,</hi> (who roſe in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> for a Free-Parliament,) and thinking to have tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Olivers</hi> ſteps, he took the ſame courſe with the Members at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> as he had done before, that is, he turn'd them out of doors; and while he March'd into the North againſt Generall <hi>Monck,</hi> who had declar'd againſt theſe proceedings, he left affaires to be manag'd by the Council of Officers at <hi>Wallingford-houſe,</hi> theſe ſitting upon a Modell of Government, at length there was fram'd a thing called a Committee of Safety, which taking upon it the government of the Nation, brought in a great diſorder and confuſion upon the face of affairs, till by a ſtrange turn of fortune, all the Army on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain deſerting <hi>Lambert</hi> and his party, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigled thereunto by the policy of ſome of the late diſſolved Members, way is made hereby to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all men, for the re-entry of our little Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, which growing ſtill more and more odious to the people, came at length to be generally ſtiled in deriſion <hi>The Rump.</hi> Immediately after which Generall <hi>Monck</hi> hastens out of <hi>Scotland</hi> with his Army toward <hi>London,</hi> to make room for whoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance the old Army is order'd to march out, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd into ſeverall quarters, the City manifeſting diſcontent, and diſowning the preſent authority, <hi>Monck</hi> is commanded to pull down the City gates,
<pb facs="tcp:40427:4"/>which he unwillingly performs; but at the ſame time his commiſsion being out, and commiſsioners appointed for the government of the Army, and <hi>Monck</hi> nominated the laſt, he cloſeth with the City, and after a while cauſeth the old Members who had been ſecluded by the Army in <hi>1648.</hi> to be re-admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their ſeats in Parliament, yet limits them to ſit onely for a ſhort time, and to make preparations for the calling of a Free-Parliament; no ſooner is this Parliament aſſembled, but they receive a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration from His preſent Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, which unanimouſly they own, publickly Proclaime Him King, and invite Him to a ſpeedy return and exerciſe of His Royal truſt. The King immediately comes over, is receiv'd with incredible joy, and brought in great glory and triumph to His Palace at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and long may He there raign with peace and tranquility to the Nation: and thus you have a brief analyſis of all the grand and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable revolutions of this Nation in this ſtrange and capricious age, which are more at large though with brevity enough deliver'd in this preſent Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and although there are already made publick ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall relations of the ſame nature, yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we could not reaſonably be diſcouraged from committing this Hiſtory to the Preſs, in regard we have a juſt confidence to promiſe a more exact and punctuall account in all the moſt remarkable paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages then is to be found in any of the reſt, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:40427:4"/>for the manner of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> eſcape from <hi>Worceſter,</hi> his tranſactions during his abode in ſeverall parts beyond the ſeas, his joyfull reception into <hi>England,</hi> and his magnificent entry into his famous City of <hi>London,</hi> with all the materiall paſſages that have happened ſince <hi>His Majeſties</hi> reſtoration to his government. And furthermore our chiefeſt aime in this Hiſtory is to lay a foundation for the continuing from time to time the relation of all materiall paſſages that ſhall happen in this Kingdome for the future; which of how generall a concernment it is, cannot but be apparent to thoſe who diligently inquire into the advancement of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40427:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40427:5"/>
            <head>ENGLAND'S TRIUMPH: A MORE EXACT HISTORY OF KING <hi>CHARLES</hi> the II.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S to the writing the affaires of theſe late times, an Hiſtorian never met with more varietie of ſubjects, ſo for the right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and delivery of thoſe events, he will find it a matter of much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty; ſuch ſtrange changes and muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities of State, of which no other Country can ſhew a parallel, nor <hi>England</hi> it ſelf produce a preſident; A well ordered Monarchy turned into a confuſed Anarchy, Religion hewed down by the axe of Schiſme, moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid villanies acted under Religious pretences; Having not onely Prieſts (as in the time of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi>) but Princes alſo of the loweſt of the people. <hi>Wat Tylers, Jack a Leydons,</hi> and <hi>Knipper dollings;</hi> as may appear by their uſurping governments, which I ſhall endeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver unto you in the tranſactions of <hi>England</hi> from the death of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, to the re-eſtabliſhment of His Son King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, wherein the Reader may ſee in the fall of the Houſe of <hi>Cromwells,</hi> that <hi>Greatneſſe built upon perjury is of ſhort continuance,</hi> and that what ever aſpiring <hi>Phaetons</hi> pretend, <hi>None but Apollo is able to guide the Chariot of the Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40427:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt of Glorious Memory, being by a part of the Parliament (who had uſurped to themſelves the power of the whole or more:) ſentenced to death by the mouth of that audacious Traytor <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> was the 30. of <hi>January</hi> 1648. in purſuance of their deſignes moſt execrably murthered before His Pallace at <hi>White-Hall</hi> by ſevering His head from His body. A Prince, whoſe vertues far exceeded any Eulogy we can beſtow upon Him, His own pencill beſt pourtraies Him, the greatneſs of His worth being beſt expreſſed in the many miſeries ſuſtained by His loſſe.</p>
            <p>But the end of their malice reſted not here, it reached alſo to His poſterity, whom by Proclamation they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive of all Right in the Government of theſe three Kingdomes, and vote the Kingly Office quite down, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary both to the Word of God, and the Fundamental Laws of the Nation: Yet though they caſt a fair gloſſe on the matter, every ones Comment did not agree with their Text; and firſt <hi>Ireland</hi> (ſaving onely <hi>Dublin</hi> and <hi>London Derry</hi>) ſhew their diſlike by revolt, for the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> and the Lord <hi>Inchiquine</hi> having made a peace with the <hi>Quondam</hi> Rebels, with a joynt conſent Proclaime His Eldeſt Son King, by the name of <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond; ſolemnly inviting Him to come over to them being then in <hi>France</hi> with His Mother. But the King, though againſt the advice of His Mother, as plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly as he might, waves this invitation; becauſe he was unwilling to diſtaſte His better friends in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> by ſeeming to countenance thoſe with His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, whom they ſuppos'd he had already too much countenanced with His commiſſion. And indeed it fell out much for the beſt, conſidering the ſudden ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of His friends there. For their numerous Army (amounting to no leſſe then twenty two thouſand men,) with which they were then beleaguering <hi>Dublin,</hi> either
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40427:6"/>by the careleſneſs of the Commanders, or ſecurity of the Souldiers, was beat from before it by the beſieged, and utterly routed by the third part of their number. Soon after <hi>Cromwell</hi> alſo arrived there with an Army, ſent out of <hi>England</hi> to perfect their work of deformation, who ſoon made the Conqueſt compleat, putting many of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to death, eſpecially at <hi>Tredagh,</hi> where he continued Killing in cold blood for four days together, pretending they were Rebels, quite forgetting what him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his maſters were.</p>
            <p>In the year 1649. a part of the Army falſly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſervedly by <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Faction called Levellers, make a defection from the reſt; for they obſerving the exorbitant Counſels of <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his <hi>Council of State,</hi> were reſolved not to be inſtruments of b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inging the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome into further ſlavery, but rather to aſſert their own and the Nations liberty, and it is thought to joyn with the King whom they had fought againſt, rather then loſe their enterpriſe. Whether ſuch were their intentions or no I ſhall not debate, but ſure it is that thoſe differences did not make ill for the Royall party, who ſeeing the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, were not idle; ſo that in a ſhort time their deſignes were render'd ſo probable, that <hi>His Majeſty</hi> was reſolved to tranſport himſelf into <hi>Jerſey,</hi> then in the ſafe hands of the Earl of <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> to attend the ſucceſs. Whence if occaſion ſerv'd he might with more eaſe waft himſelf into the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> which part it is ſaid, that upon notice of the Southern diſorders he was to have fallen. While <hi>His Majeſty</hi> ſtayd in <hi>Gerſey</hi> he ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons <hi>Guernſey,</hi> but in vain, and becauſe that ſeemed not to be misfortune enough, he received the news of the Levellers being utterly quell'd through the treachery of <hi>Aeres</hi> and <hi>Reynolds,</hi> (for which piece of ſervice <hi>Cromwell</hi> was not ungratefull,) the forces of <hi>Cromwell</hi> falling upon them, while they were in treatie, ſuſpecting nothing l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40427:7"/>then force of Armes. Upon this the King retired again into <hi>France,</hi> though he were the ſooner forc'd to doe it, becauſe he had certain intelligence that the Enemy was ſending a fleet of ſhips to take from him that ſmall rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of His large dominions that yet remain'd unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
            <p>But from <hi>Scotland</hi> far greater dangers threatned the Parliamentary Juncto, for though the <hi>Scots</hi> had ſold their King before, yet feigning an abhorrency of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> proceedings, and that the world might take notice they were innocent of His murther, they likewiſe Proclaime Prince <hi>Charles, King of Great Brittain, France, and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and thereupon ſend Mr. <hi>Windram</hi> Laird of <hi>Lib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berton,</hi> to treat with <hi>His Majeſty</hi> about ſundry articles before His reception to the Crown; who having received his diſpatches, haſts unto Him, being then in the <hi>Iſle of Jerſey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſumme of their deſires was to this effect.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That</hi> His Majeſty <hi>would graciouſly be pleaſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſigne the ſolemne League and Covenant, and that he would paſſe an Act in Part that every perſon in that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome might take it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That He would paſſe divers Acts of the Parliament of</hi> Scotland, <hi>which was concluded on the two laſt Seſſions,</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>For approving of their diſclaiming Duke</hi> Hamiltons <hi>laſt return for receiving ſeverall Acts made by the</hi> Engliſh <hi>for the Militia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That the Kings of</hi> Scotland <hi>may have no Negative voice.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3: <hi>That</hi> His Majeſty <hi>would recall the late Commiſſions given to</hi> Montroſſe.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>That He would put away all Papists from about Him.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>That He would appoint ſome place about</hi> Holland <hi>to treate with their Commiſſioners. An Honorable company of the moſt noble Lords in</hi> Scotland, <hi>being to be appointed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40427:7"/>to attend</hi> His Majeſty, <hi>to whom likewiſe they ſend a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent proviſion to maintain Him, a traine ſuitable to His birth and deſerved greatneſſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>That He would be graciouſly pleaſed to give a speedy anſwer to their deſires.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>By theſe pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſitions the Reader may perceive, that notwithſtanding their pretenſions, they intended Him a King onely conditionally: and indeed thoſe bitter pills they afterwards made him ſwallow, may give the world juſt cauſe to think that their ſelf ends bore greater ſway with them then Love and Loyalty to <hi>His Majeſty;</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever (nowithſtanding the Lord <hi>Cleaveland</hi> and others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged their Treachery unto His Father, that they were Scots ſtill, and might doe the ſame unto Him: That the Marqueſſe of <hi>Montroſſe</hi> (who had lately received Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to aſſault the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi>) was raiſing forces in <hi>Holland,</hi> of whoſe valour and fidelity he need not to doubt of,) the Majority of voices carrying it for a Treaty, it was reſolved on, and this anſwer returned to their Propoſitions. <hi>That as to what was acted in the two laſt Seſſions of Parliament, He was content a generall Act of Oblivion ſhould be paſſed, but could not approve it. That neither thoſe of</hi> Montroſſes, <hi>nor Duke</hi> Hamiltons <hi>party in his laſt engagement ſhould bear Office in State without conſent of Parliament. That He had appointed</hi> Breda <hi>in</hi> Holland <hi>for the place of a ſolemne Treaty, for the make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a full accomodation and agreement between Him and His Loving Subjects of</hi> Scotland.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding theſe large condeſcentions, which to reaſonable men might have given ſatisfaction even to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation, the arrogant Kirk-men would not have had Him admitted into <hi>Scotland,</hi> but upon conditions, which ſhould make Him wholly ſubſervient to thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Commands, and much ſcuffle was betwixt the State and them about it: At length a mediation is concluded on betwixt them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40427:8"/>and the Earl of <hi>Castles,</hi> the Lord <hi>Lothian, Burley,</hi> and <hi>Libberton,</hi> Sir <hi>John Smith,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jeofferys,</hi> for the Eſtates; and Mr. <hi>Broady, Lawſon,</hi> and <hi>Wood,</hi> are appointed Commiſſioners for the Kirk.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>March</hi> the 19. 1649. at <hi>Breda</hi> aforeſaid they came before <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> where after obeiſance, the Lord <hi>Caſtles</hi> in behalf of the Eſtates, and Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi> for the Kirk made each of them a ſpeech, candied over with many expreſſions of Loyalty, and unfeigned obedience, but their reall intentions may be better preceived by theſe Propoſitions, which then they delivered to <hi>His Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That all thoſe who had been excommunicated by the Church, and ſtill continued ſo, ſhould be forbid acceſſe to Court.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That all Acts of the Parliament of</hi> Scotland, <hi>ſhould be by him ratified and approved of. That the Solemne Leauge and Covenant, the Presbyterian Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Directory, Confeſſion and Catechiſme ſhould be enjoyned in</hi> Scotland; <hi>and the ſame uſed and practiſed in His family, and an oath to be taken by Him that He would never oppoſe it, or endeavour to alter it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That He would by ſolemne oath, and under His hand and ſeal declare and acknowledge His allowanne of the ſolemne Leauge and Covenant, and the National Covenant of</hi> Scotland.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>That He would conſent and agree that all civil mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters might be determined by ſubſequent Parliaments in</hi> Scotland, <hi>and all Eccleſiaſtical matters by the Generall Kirk Aſſembly, as was formerly granted by His Royall Father.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>withſtanding the unreaſonableneſs of theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, yet working on His Neceſſities, the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling they found Him to condeſcend, the more impudent were they ſtill to propoſe; for not long after they ſent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40427:8"/>the Earl of <hi>Carnwarth,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Murrey,</hi> with new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſitions to this effect, viz.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That</hi> His Majeſty <hi>ſhould confirme all Acts done in ſome late Seſſions of Parliament, without any exception.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2, <hi>That neither</hi> Montroſle <hi>nor any of his adherents be admitted to come into the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe Propoſitions were very ſtiffely debated amongſt the Kings Councellors, ſome of them perſwade <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to an utter rejectment of them, alleadging, <hi>That the Covenanters horrid perfidiouſneſs to His Father, might be a ſufficient motive and inducement for Him not to truſt them. That ſhould He accept of their conditions, they would ſo tie up His hands that He would be then but a King onely in Title, which He was without them. That there was no reaſon why He ſhould be forc'd to relinquiſh the Religion of His Fathers, and whilſt He permitted to His Subjects Liberty of Conſcience, to be denied the ſame Himſelf: That the Covenant tendred, and ſo earneſtly preſt upon Him by them, was an obligatory Covenant to binde the Subjects to Him, and not for Him to ſwear to; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was judged ſufficiently ſatisfactory if He paſſed an Act for the pleoples taking it.</hi> On the other ſide, thoſe who ſtood for an accommodation, urged <hi>the neceſſity of</hi> His Majeſties <hi>affairs, which both in</hi> Ireland <hi>under</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſſe, <hi>and in the Navy under Prince</hi> Rupert, <hi>were in ſo weake and tottering a condition, that no help could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from them; That all the Princes in</hi> Chriſtendome, <hi>were ſo embroyled in wars of their own, that it was in vain to crave any forraigne aid; and that therefore there was no way left for</hi> His Majeſty <hi>to re-gaine His loſt Rights and Kingdomes, but by complying with His Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ects of</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>and though it were upon ſuch conditions as would at firſt ſeem harſh, thoſe Curbs might in time (poſſeſſion once got) be thrown off by degrees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt matters were thus debating, ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s was brought
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40427:9"/>the King of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Montroſſes</hi> ignominious death, who having gotten together about ſix or ſeven hundred men, with thoſe ſmall forces makes an attempt upon <hi>Scotland,</hi> but was by them unfortunately defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, himſelf treach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rouſly betraid into their hands by the Lord <hi>Aſton;</hi> and at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> hang'd drawn and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, with all the ſcorn and ignominy an inſulting enemy could invent. This act of theirs, conſidering the juncture of time, might ſeem to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one as in affront to the treaty, and could not but highly incenſe <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> not onely for the loſſe of ſo brave a perſon, whoſe valour and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naminity all <hi>Europe</hi> admired; but in their carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him His Leiutenant, He might read Lectures of diſloyalty againſt Himſelf. Many judged the death of this Marqueſſe would have put a period unto the Treaty, for thoſe who were averſe to it before, now oppoſed it with might and maine, telling the King, <hi>That they had by thus murthering His Leiutenant, demonſtrated to the world what they would doe to Him if they had Him in their power; That it was an act of Raſhneſs and deſperation to truſt them, or to have any more to doe with ſuch a perfidious genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That they onely cunningly and ſubtilly endeavoured to entrap Him that they might deſtroy Him.</hi> But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their high words, the Kings affairs were in ſo low a condition, that it forced Him to embrace thoſe conditions which He utterly deteſted, and to put a concluſion to the Treaty by condeſcending to moſt of their deſires.</p>
            <p>But though the King ſtooped thus low even to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, yet ſo impudent were they, that after the Treaty was concluded with Him, in the Parliament at <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> it was debated by ſome of them, <hi>Whether they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ould make any further addreſſes to Him;</hi> but the Major part carrying it in the affirmative, a meſſage was ſent to Him, inviting Him to make all poſſible ſpeed to His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40427:9"/>of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with a great many verball expreſſions of obedience, but to let Him know what rule they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended He ſhould walk by, they debarre Him from having thoſe whom He chiefly favour'd to waite upon Him, and nominate ſuch perſons as they thought fit out of their own gang to be Officers of His Houſhold there.</p>
            <p>But the King was reſolved to overcome all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and having provided things in a readineſs, about the beginning of <hi>June</hi> 1650. ſet ſail from <hi>Holland,</hi> and after a dangerous ſtorme, and narrow ſcape of ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> veſſels which lay in waite for Him, arrived at <hi>Spey</hi> in the North of <hi>Scotland:</hi> the Parliament hearing of His arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall ſent down ſome Lords to receive and accompany Him to <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enburgh;</hi> but before He could be admitted to come unto them, they ſend Him new Propoſitions to <hi>Dundee</hi> to ſigne, which with much regret (ſeeing He could doe no otherwiſe,) He at laſt condeſcended unto.</p>
            <p>But this was not all, for being in His way preſented with ſeveral ſummes of money, the Committee of Eſtates and Kirk fearing ſuch diet would make Him too un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weildy, fet forth injunctions, that what ever monies peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had to beſtow, they ſhould bring it in unto ſuch Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuries as ſhould be appointed by them; a very neat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice not onely to bring gaine unto themſelves, but to make Him the more conformable to their pleaſures.</p>
            <p>However, they pretend great matters for His ſervice, an army is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e raiſed of 16000. foot and 6000. horſe, of which the Earl of <hi>Leven</hi> is made Generall of the foot, and <hi>Holborne</hi> Major Generall; <hi>David Leſley</hi> Leiutenant Generall of the Horſe, and <hi>Montgomery</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Generall; <hi>His Majeſty</hi> (whom I name laſt, becauſe He had leaſt command,) had the Title of <hi>Generalliſſimo</hi> reſerved for Him, and indeed onely the Title, for He ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver went into the field with His army.</p>
            <p>Being come to <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> He is received by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40427:10"/>and Committy of Eſtates and Kirk with infinite expreſſions of fidelity and affection, the Common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple like Ecchoes anſwering their ſuperiours, the whole City ſounded nothing but VIVE LE ROY. In this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we will leave Him for a while, and caſt an eye upon the affairs of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſe Juncto (by the treachery of ſome that ſat in the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi>) had certain intelligence of all theſe proceedings; and now ſeeing things were grown to this height, they ſend for <hi>Cromwell</hi> out of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> making him Generall in the room of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> who (ſay ſome) refuſed to engage againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> others ſay his Commiſſion was taken from him to gratifie therewith their Creature <hi>Cromwell,</hi> though this their Idol afterwards prov'd their ſcourge; ſo juſt is God, that <hi>thoſe who would not endure a milde King, ſhould ſuffer under a mereileſs Tyrant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having received his Commiſſion he matches into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but upon his approach the <hi>Scots</hi> in two letters, one to himſelf, and another to the Parliament, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the invaſion. To which the Parliament in a declaration, and <hi>Cromwell</hi> in a letter, much to the ſame effect replie,</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Scots</hi> had once already invaded <hi>England</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Hamilton,</hi> and were now ready for a ſecond, ſo that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did now not ſo much invade as prevent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion.</p>
            <p>That they had made peace with the Common enemy, and had not onely reſtored Him to their own Kingdome, but promiſed to give Him all aſſiſtance as to His reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this.</p>
            <p>That they were not content to enjoy their own liberty in Religion, but would reſtrain them from theirs.</p>
            <p>Thus from words they fall to blows, and firſt <hi>Cromwell</hi> at a place called <hi>Muſcleborough</hi> encountereth with the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40427:10"/>
               <hi>Scots,</hi> under the command of <hi>Montgomery,</hi> whom he worſted, and afterwards gave them a totall overthrow at <hi>Dunbar, Sep.</hi> 3. 1650. a day very remarkable in the paſſages of his life, having on the ſame obtained two ſignall victories, was on the ſame choſen Protector, and on the ſame day died, the moſt fortunate of the foure, and deſerveth to be Rubrickt with red letters, for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from ſo bloudy a Tyrant.</p>
            <p>Soon after he had a dangerous fit of ſickneſs, from which if God had been pleaſed in mercy to have delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him by death, I believe he had not been guilty of ſo much perjury, bloud and apoſtacy, as afterwards he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted.</p>
            <p>Sad was the condition of the <hi>Scots</hi> at this time, being not onely perplexed with a forreigne enemy raging in her bowels, but were themſelves alſo miſerably divided into a Tripartite Schiſme; one party in the Weſt under <hi>Strangham</hi> and <hi>Ker</hi> declared for the Kirk againſt the King, another party in the North under the Command of <hi>Huntley, Atholl, Seaforth,</hi> &amp;c. for the King againſt the Kirk, a third being the Parliament, and Committy of Eſtates, and Kirk, for the King and Kirk; with theſe laſt was His Sacred Majeſty; but ſo imperious and inſolent were they over Him in extorting declarations from Him againſt His own party and proceedings, in uſurping the whole government of affaires to themſelves, and in placing guards of their own Creatures upon His per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp;c. That not able longer to ſuffer ſuch intollerable affronts, he went ſecretly away from them to the Lord <hi>Dedups</hi> houſe in the North Confines of <hi>Fife;</hi> The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Committy of Eſtates and Kirk, fearing He would have gone to <hi>Huntley,</hi> ſent Major General <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomery</hi> after Him to intreat His return again to S. <hi>John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton's;</hi> which at firſt He refuſed, but afterwards upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Propoſitions granted Him, He returned. And now,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40427:11"/>the Common enemy endangering all, they unite in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and a generall meeting is reſolved on to be held at S. <hi>Johnſton's,</hi> which ſhould conſiſt of King, Lords, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, Burgeſſes, and the Aſſembly of Miniſters; ſeverall Lords formerly in disfavour with the Kirk are received into command in the Army, and have Libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty to ſit in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſuch as <hi>Hamilton, Landerdale, Leith, Bucheim, Dedup,</hi> and <hi>Crawford,</hi> Major Generall <hi>Maſſey</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> was admitted to a Command in the Army. Thus did their ſoares begin to heal, their breaches again to be made up, and now it was well hoped theſe clouds of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſion being blown over, a ſerene sky would follow, and the Sun of proſperity ſhine upon their proceedings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>January</hi> the firſt following, with as great ſolemnity as the indigency of their affairs would permit, was the King Crowned at <hi>Scone,</hi> the ancient place for the Coronation of the Kings of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to omit the Ceremonies which were not many, as not fit to be uſed in ſo reformed a place: The King having the Crown ſet on His head, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to maintain the ſame againſt all oppoſers, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation whereunto. He reſolves upon the raiſing of an Army with all poſſible ſpeed, to which effect he ſets up His Standerd at <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> intending to be <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> thereof Himſelf, Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> is made Leiutnant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Army, and Sir <hi>Thomas Middleton</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Generall of the Horſe. The Town of <hi>Sterling</hi> is ordered to be fortified, to which <hi>His Majeſty</hi> went often in progreſſe to view the works, and encourage the Pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>And high time it was for Him to beſtirre Himſelf, <hi>Cromwell</hi> (that ſucceſſefull Rebel) having gained all on the other ſide <hi>Fife,</hi> takes the Earl of <hi>Eglington</hi> priſoner, every day drew nigher and nigher to them, whereupon <hi>His Majeſty</hi> removed His Court to <hi>Sterling,</hi> moſt of the <hi>Scotch</hi> army quartering about it, whither not long after
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40427:11"/>Sir <hi>Tho. Middleton</hi> brought 8000. men out of the North, and more were expected every day from <hi>Argile, Huntley,</hi> and <hi>Seaforth,</hi> who were gone to their ſeverall territories to compleat the Kings Levies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> deſirous to fight them before they were uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, uſed all his endeavours to bring them to a field bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, which <hi>His Majeſty</hi> for the reaſons aforeſaid declined, whereupon on a ſudden he draws off his army and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports 1600. foot, and foure Troops of Horſe over into <hi>Fife,</hi> and with an unparallel'd expedition faced again the Royall Army, with a r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſolution to fall upon their Rear if they ſhould attempt a motion thitherwards, yet could not this make them to ſtirre; In the mean time Sir <hi>John Brown</hi> Governour of <hi>Sterling</hi> with 4000. Horſe and Foot, marches againſt that party of <hi>Cromwells</hi> already landed in <hi>Fife; Lambert</hi> and <hi>Okey</hi> having intelligence thereof, with two Regiments o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Horſe and two of Foot, waft over to reinforce their party, with which additionall aid they routed Sir <hi>John Brown,</hi> took him priſoner, with near 1200. more, and killed 2000. upon the place. <hi>Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> fleſht with theſe beginnings, purſues his advantages, and tranſports his Army over <hi>Fife,</hi> marches to S. <hi>John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtons,</hi> and takes it almoſt upon the firſt ſummons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty</hi> not able to force them back, reſolves with all ſpeed to advance into <hi>England,</hi> well hoping the juſtneſſe of His cauſe would have incited the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to have joyned with Him, as experienc'd alſo of the <hi>Scots</hi> valour, expreſt better in other Countries then the own. <hi>Cromwell</hi> hereupon re-croſſes <hi>Frith,</hi> and ſends <hi>Lambert</hi> with a ſelect party of Horſe and Dragoones to fall upon their Rear, himſelf following quickly after. By the way of <hi>Carlile</hi> the Royal Army enters <hi>England,</hi> march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with that Civility and Obedience to military diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, that 'twas thought the Country was not endamaged ſix pence by them; but whether it was that their former
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40427:12"/>villanies had left ſuch a deep impreſſion in the hearts of the people, or that they were now dulled and beſotted with ſlavery, content with <hi>Iſſachers</hi> aſſe to couch under their burthens, or rather being over-awed by an armed power, few or none came in to their aſſiſtance, ſaving onely the Lord <hi>Howards</hi> Sonne of <hi>Eſtwick</hi> with a Troope of Horſe, notwithſtanding <hi>His Majeſties</hi> earneſt invitations.</p>
            <p>The Juncto at <hi>Weſtwinſter</hi> hearing of the Kings march, raiſed all the Counties againſt Him, and made it high Treaſon to aid Him with either men or monies; But the Loyall (though unfortunate) Earl of <hi>Darby</hi> not fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Bug-bear, brought Him a ſupply of 250. Foot, and 60. Horſe, out of the Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> and having raiſed a conſiderable force in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> ſet upon Col. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> (intending to have hindered him from joyning with a Regiment of <hi>Cromwells,</hi> which was ſent for that purpoſe towards <hi>Manchester,</hi>) but was by him unfortunately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, the Lord <hi>Witherington,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Tilſley,</hi> Sir <hi>William Throgmorton,</hi> Col. <hi>Boynton,</hi> and ſundry others taken priſoners.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Worceſter</hi> the Royall army made a ſtand, reſolving to abide all oppoſition, <hi>Cromwell</hi> having joyned himſelf with the Country forces was quickly at their heels, his army conſiſting of 50. or 60. Thouſand, the <hi>Scots</hi> not 10000. at moſt; yet adding courage to their ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, reſolved to fight it out to the uttermoſt; the King though of a Lambe-like diſpoſition, yet here acted the part of a Lyon, encouraging his Souldiers both by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and example; after ſeverall ſallies, and much cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage ſhown on both ſides, <hi>September</hi> 3. (an unfortunate day for the <hi>Scots</hi>) it came to a field fight, wherein though the Royaliſts valour exceeded even to admiration, yet multitude overmatching courage they were overthrown. The King (whoſe Horſe was twice that day ſhot under
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40427:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Him,) could not be induced to quit the field, untill He ſaw all the field almoſt cleared.</p>
            <p>The battle being thus abſolutely loſt, toward three of the Clock <hi>Thurſday</hi> Morning the 4. of <hi>September</hi> the King in Company with the ſaid Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi> Earl of <hi>Shrewſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cleaveland,</hi> Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> my Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> and others to the Number of fourſcore, came to the place called <hi>White-ladies</hi> in the pariſh of <hi>Tong</hi> in the Confines of <hi>Stafford</hi> and <hi>Shropſhire,</hi> being 25. Miles diſtant or thereabouts from <hi>Worceſter,</hi> which ſpace of ground he had Rid that Night.</p>
            <p>This <hi>White-ladies</hi> was a houſe belonging to one <hi>Fits<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbert,</hi> where <hi>George Penderil</hi> (the youngeſt brother of five, who were all ſeverally inſtrumentall in the Conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Preſerving <hi>His Majesty,</hi>) hearing ſome body Knocking at the Gate ſo early, opening the window and Eſpying there the aforeſaid <hi>Francis Yates</hi> who was his brother in law, together with Mr. <hi>Giffard,</hi> the firſt thing he asked of his brother <hi>Yates</hi> was, what News from <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> who anſwered that the King was defeared, and the Enemy in purſuit of Him, therefore bid him to make haſt and put on his cloaths; but ere he could doe that, the King with moſt of His Lords had entred the houſe, and were come into the hall, where after a very ſhort de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, the Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> called for <hi>William Penderil</hi> the Eldeſt brother, (for my Lord of <hi>Derby</hi> had taken this place for his Shelter, after the defeat given him by Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> near <hi>Wigan</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and was acquainted there, &amp; was by them conducted to <hi>Worceſter</hi> to the King, it had alſo been a Sanctuary for ſeveral other Gentlemen,) who being come, <hi>George</hi> was ſent to <hi>Tong</hi> within Five miles of <hi>Wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verhampton,</hi> to one <hi>Robert Beard</hi> a very honeſt perſon, to enquire of him whether there were any ſcattered Troops of the Kings thereabouts, or if any of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies appeared thereabouts; who returned and brought
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40427:13"/>word that there were no parties at all to be ſeen; return-in he met with his brother <hi>Richard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> being come in, Mr. <hi>Giffard</hi> called for him, and bad him bring his beſt cloathes, which were a jerkin and breeches of courſe green cloth, and a Doe-skin Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doublet, they borrowed an old Gray hat of <hi>Humphry Penderill</hi> the Miller, the courſe he open ſhirt was had of one <hi>Edward Martin,</hi> with <hi>George Penderils</hi> band, and ſhoes of one <hi>William Creſwell;</hi> which <hi>His Majeſty</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtripping Himſelf of His own cloaths, nimbly put on, His buff-coat, and linnen doublet, and gray Breeches, which were the cloath; that He put off, He gave into the brothers hands, who immediately buried them under ground, where they lay five weeks before they durſt take them up again, the Jewels of His Arme He gave to one of the Lords, who was then going away.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Richard</hi> brought a paire of ſhears, and founded the Kings hair, which my Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> had Notched be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with a Knife; and the King was pleaſed to take notice of <hi>Richards</hi> good workmanſhip, ſo as to preferre it before my Lord <hi>Wilmots,</hi> and now <hi>His Majeſty</hi> was eſteemed to be the compleat wood-man.</p>
            <p>Hereupon <hi>William Penderil</hi> was preſented to <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> by the Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi> and the care of His moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty committed to his charge, and the reſt of his brothers: After this all that were preſent took their leaves, and departed, every one ſhifting for himſelf, only my Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> was carried by <hi>John Penderil,</hi> to the houſe of one <hi>Thomas Whitgreaves;</hi> as they were going along, ſeeing ſome men coming behind them which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be friends, (though my Lord ſuſpected the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to riſe upon them,) they hid themſelves in a dry pit, where they ſtayed till Evening, and then arrived ſafely at Mr. <hi>Whitgreaves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Company being all gone, a wood-bill was brought
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40427:13"/>to the King, and ſo He and <hi>Richard</hi> went out into the wood; <hi>William</hi> went home, and <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>George</hi> went out to ſcout, and lay hovering in the wood to hear or ſee if any one approached that way; the King had not been above an hour in that wood, but a troop of the Enemies horſe came to <hi>Whitladies</hi> and enquired after the King, the towns-folks anſwered, that about three hours agoe there was a party of horſe came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they ſuppoſed the King with them, but that they made no ſtay: they were hereupon ſo eager in the purſuit when they heard which way they took, that they made no more ſearch there; the King had notice of this by the aforeſaid ſcouts, who were ever and anon ſtragling for intelligence into the town. All this day being <hi>Thurſday</hi> the King continued in the wood, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times lying on the ground, <hi>Richard Penderil</hi> conſtantly keeping Him company; but being a rainy-day, <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Yates</hi> his Wife came into the Wood and brought the King a blancket, which He threw over His Shoulders to keep Him dry, ſhe alſo brought Him His firſt meat He eat there, viz. a Meſſe of Milk mixed with Eggs and Sugar in a black Earthen diſh, the King gueſſed it to be milk and Apples, ſaying, He loved it very well, after He had drank and eat ſome of it with a pewter ſpoon, He gave <hi>George</hi> the reſt, and bid him eat, telling him it was very good; the King then exchanged His wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bill for <hi>Francis Yates</hi> broom-hook, being it was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing lighter.</p>
            <p>Toward five of the clock that Evening, the King, with <hi>Richard, Humphry, George</hi> and <hi>Francis Yates,</hi> left the wood and went to <hi>Richards</hi> houſe, under the Name of <hi>William Jones</hi> a wood-cutter newly come thither for work; againſt His coming the good wife for His entertainment at ſupper, was preparing a Fricaſſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40427:14"/>of Bacon and Eggs, and while that was doing the King held on His Knee their daughter <hi>Nan,</hi> after He had eat a little He asked <hi>Richard</hi> to eat, who replyed, yea Sir, I will, to which <hi>His Majeſty</hi> ſaid, you have a better ſtomack then I, for you have eaten five times to day already; ſupper ended, the King having reſolved to depart in the dusk of the Evening, before He went, <hi>Jane Penderill</hi> the Mother of the five brethren came to ſee the King, before whom ſhe bleſſed God that had ſo honoured her children in making them the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (as ſhe hoped) of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> ſafeguard and deliverance. Here <hi>Francis Yates</hi> offered the King thirty ſhillings in ſilver, the King took ten, bidding him put up the other; <hi>Humphry</hi> would have gone before to ſee and view about, but the King would not let him, it being now near night, they took their leave of the King upon their knees, beſeeching God to guide and bleſſe Him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> departed, intending to go to one Mr. <hi>Francis Wolf</hi> of <hi>Madeley,</hi> thence to take paſſe into <hi>Wales;</hi> on the way as they were to goe by a Mill at a place called <hi>Evelin,</hi> as they were going over the bridge, it being near nine a clock at night, the Miller ſteps forth and asked, <hi>who goes there?</hi> having ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that looked like a good Cudgell in his hand, to which <hi>Richard</hi> being foremoſt, thought it not ſafe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and therefore the water being ſhallow, he leaped from the bridge into it, the King did the like, following <hi>Richard</hi> by the Ratling of his Leather breeches; the Miller was glad he was ſo rid of them, for as it after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appeared, ſome of the Kings ſcattered ſouldiers were in his Mill, and he thought the other to be Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament party.</p>
            <p>Being come to <hi>Madely</hi> late that night, they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40427:14"/>the danger of paſſing into <hi>Wales,</hi> the Country being every where laid with Souldiers, and that he durſt not entertain them into his houſe, but ſhewed them a Hay-mow where they might lodge, where the King and <hi>Richard</hi> continued all that night, and the next day being <hi>Friday</hi> night with the conveyance of a Maid of this Mr. <hi>Wolfs,</hi> who brought the King two miles on His way, they retreated back again to <hi>Richards</hi> houſe; however, to ſhew his Loyalty, Mr. <hi>Wolfe</hi> lent the King ſome ſmall ſumme of money.</p>
            <p>This deſign being croſſed, <hi>Saturday</hi> morning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſtay, the King and he went to a houſe of Mris. <hi>Giffard</hi> called <hi>Boſcobel,</hi> where <hi>William Penderil</hi> and his wife dwelt as houſe-keepers, who received Him joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; but the Kings feet were ſo bliſtered with Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling in ſuch courſe and ſtiffe accountrements as He wore on His feet, and lying in them, that He was ſcarce able to ſtand or goe; which <hi>Williams</hi> wife per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, ſhe ſtript off His ſtockings, and cut the bli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and waſhed His feet, and gave the King ſome eaſe.</p>
            <p>The ſame time or near thereupon, that Noble Col. <hi>Careles,</hi> who as it is ſaid before made good the Kings paſſage at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and had fought his way through; after he had been two days at one <hi>David Jones</hi> living in the Heathin <hi>Tong-pariſh,</hi> and there by him ſecured, was brought by one <hi>Elizabeth Burgeſſe</hi> to this ſame houſe of <hi>Boſcobell,</hi> where he had layn obſcure three quarters of a year before, and there <hi>His Majeſty</hi> and he met; but the Colonel was ſo over-joyed with the fight of the King His Maſter in ſuch ſure and ſafe hands, that he could not refraine weeping, which kindneſſe of his forced the King to ſomething of the ſame paſſion.</p>
            <p>After a ſhort conference touching the Kings moſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40427:15"/>probable meanes of Eſcape, it was Reſolved by them to betake themſelves to the wood again, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly about nine of the clock that <hi>Saturday</hi> morning they went into the wood, and Colonel <hi>Carles</hi> brought the King to that famous Oake where before he had himſelf been lodged: this tree is not hollow, but of a found firm trunk, onely about the middle of the body of it, there is a hole in it about the bigneſſe of a mans head, from whence it is called hollow; by the help of <hi>William Penderils</hi> Ladder, they got up among the boughs of the tree, which were very thick and full of leaves, ſo that it was impoſſible for any one to diſcern any thing through them.</p>
            <p>Being both up, <hi>William</hi> gave each of them a pillow to lie upon, between the thickeſt of the branches; the King being over-wearied with his travell began to be very ſleepy, ſo that the Colonel to accomodate Him as well as he could, deſired <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to lay His head in his lap, and reſt His body upon the pillow, which the King agreed to, and after He had ſleept a good while, He awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked very hungry, wiſhing He had ſomething to eat; whereupon the Colonel pluckt out of his pocket a good Lunchion of bread and cheeſe which <hi>Jone Penderil</hi> had given him that day, and had wrapped it up in a clean linnen cloath, of which the King fed very heartily, and commending it highly for good Cheere, ſome other ſmall relief He had which was put up into the tree with a long hook-ſtick.</p>
            <p>At this time <hi>Richard Penderil</hi> was ſent to <hi>Wolver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton</hi> ſome three miles from thence, to buy wine and biſquet, and ſome other refreſhment for the King, and withall to ſpeak with one Mr. <hi>George Manwaring</hi> a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of known Integrity and Loyaly from Col. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> to know of him whether he knew of any ſuch pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40427:15"/>for two perſons of the Kings party fled from <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester:</hi> To which he ſent word back that he had not himſelf, but he would enquire if a friend of his, one Mr. <hi>Whitgreave</hi> of <hi>Moſeley</hi> could doe it; with this anſwer <hi>Richard</hi> returned with his wine, &amp;c. to the King, who toward the Evening came down from the tree, and was brought into the Garden of <hi>Boſcobel</hi> houſe, where in one of the bowers He ſat and drank part of the wine till toward Night.</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Humphry Penderil</hi> the Miller was ſent to get intelligence, and the eaſier to come by it, he was ſent to a Captain of the Rump, one <hi>Broadway,</hi> formerly a Heel-maker, under pretence of carrying him twenty ſhillings for the pay of a man in the new raiſed Militia of their County; for their Miſtris being there, in comes a Col. of the Enemies, asking for Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Broadways,</hi> that he might know what further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry had been made at <hi>Whiteladies,</hi> for the King; tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Broadways</hi> the ſtory of it; to which <hi>Broadways</hi> replyed, he knew nothing of it further then Rumor, but that there was one of that place in the houſe that could give an account of it; Hereupon <hi>Humphry</hi> was called, but he evaded all the queſtions put to him, only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that the King had been there as was ſuppoſed, but that there was no likely-hood He ſhould ſtay there, there being three families in the houſe, all at difference one with an other; then the Colonel told him there was a thouſand pound that would be given to any that ſhould take or diſcover Him, and that they queſtioned not but within a day or two to have Him delivered into their hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Humphry</hi> coming back related all the paſſages, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting not to tell <hi>His Majeſty</hi> of the price His Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had ſet on His head; at the relating whereof the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40427:16"/>King looked ſomewhat diſmayed, as having truſted his Life into the hands of ſuch poor men, whom ſuch a ſumme as that might pervert from their fidelity. This cauſed <hi>Humphry</hi> to be exceedingly troubled for His raſhneſſe, but Col. <hi>Carles</hi> aſſured the King if it were a hundred thouſand pounds it were to as little purpoſe, and that he would engage his ſoul for their honeſty, which <hi>Humphry</hi> alſo was not backward to ſecond with many ſolemn Affections.</p>
            <p>It was now late, and the King being very hungry, was deſirous of a Loin of Mutton, and being come into the houſe, asked <hi>William</hi> if he could not get it Him? <hi>William</hi> told Him that he had it not of his own, but he would make bold on ſuch an occaſion with one of his Maſters ſheep in the Coat; which preſently he did, and brought it into the Cellar, where the Col. impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of delay ſtab'd it with his dagger: the ſheep being fleyed, the King fell preſently to Chopping of the Loin to pieces, which the Col. clapt into the pan, while the King held it and fryed it.</p>
            <p>This paſſage was an occaſion to the King of much mirth: in a diſcourſe after His arrivall in <hi>France,</hi> where the queſtion was put, who was Cook, and who was ſcullion, the reſolution of the doubt, when it could not be decided by the Lords then preſent, was referred to the Judgment of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Maſter Cook, who affirmed that <hi>His Majesty</hi> was <hi>Hic &amp; Nunc,</hi> both of them.</p>
            <p>When this nimble collation was ended, the King was willing to betake Himſelf to His reſt, His cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain <hi>William</hi> brought Him to His Lodging, it was a place made between two walls on purpoſe for ſecrecy, contrived at the building of the houſe, thither they let the King down, where He ſlept very Incommodiouſly,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40427:16"/>the place not being long enough for Him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the next night they laid Him a ſorry bed upon the ſtaire-caſe, as they uſed to doe for ſtrange wood-cutters, that the meanneſſe of His Lodging might ſecure Him from ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> as is ſaid before, was all this while ſafe at Mr. <hi>Whitgreaves,</hi> only his care of the King made him full of Trouble, his hiding-place was ſo ſure an one, that at his firſt coming to it, he wiſhed ſo he gave twenty thouſand pounds that the King were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as ſecure or there with him: full of ſuch thoughts, he therefore diſpatch'd away <hi>John Penderil</hi> (who had attended him all along) to the <hi>Whiteladies,</hi> to enquire for the King, and to give Him no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice of the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency that was at Mr. <hi>Whitgreaves;</hi> but when he came thither, which was on Friday, the King was then gone to <hi>Madely</hi> to Mr. <hi>Woolfs;</hi> the next day he was ſent again, and by <hi>Richards</hi> Wife directed to <hi>Boſcobel,</hi> where he told the King his Meſſage, which the King agreed unto, and reſolved to remove thither.</p>
            <p>Munday Night <hi>Sept.</hi> 8. at eleven at Night was the time reſolved on for the Kings Journey to <hi>Moſely,</hi> but a Horſe was hard to be got, but remembring that <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phry</hi> the Miller had one, he was called and deſired to lend him for the Kings ſervice; it was a Horſe that uſed to carry nothing but ſacks, but now he put upon him a bridle and ſaddle, that had out-worne its tree and irons, and at the time brought him to the gate.</p>
            <p>The King Mounting, Colonel <hi>Carles</hi> and the ſix others Guarded Him, two before, and two behind, and one of each ſide armed with clubs and bills, <hi>Humphry</hi> leading his horſe by the bridle; and ſo they began their Journey, it was five Miles from <hi>Boſcobel</hi> to <hi>Moſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> Mr. <hi>Whitgreaves,</hi> and the way in ſome places
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40427:17"/>Miry; where the horſe blundering cauſed the King to ſuſpect falling, and bid <hi>Humphry</hi> have a care, to which he anſwered, <hi>that that now fortunate horſe had carried many a heavier weight in his time, ſix ſtrike of corn, but now had a better price on his back, the price of three Kingdomes, and therefore would not now ſhame his Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their travell was ſoon and ſafely ended, and the King brought the back way to a ſtile that led to the houſe; when the King was to alight, <hi>Humphry</hi> led the horſe into a ditch, and the King alighted off upon the ſtile, but forgetting that moſt of His Guard were to return home, He went five or ſix ſteps onward without taking leave of them, when ſuddenly recalling Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, He returned back, and took His leave of them in theſe words. <hi>I am troubled, that I forget to take my leave of my friends; but if ever I come into</hi> England <hi>by fair or foul means, I will remember you, and let Me ſee you when ever it ſhall ſo pleaſe God:</hi> ſo they all kiſſed His hand and departed, but the <hi>Colonel, john,</hi> and <hi>Francis Yates,</hi> who conducted <hi>His Majesty</hi> to the houſe.</p>
            <p>There Mr. <hi>Thomas Whitgreave</hi> received the King with an extraordinary duty and affection, and brought Him in to my Lord <hi>Wilmot,</hi> who with an unſpeakable gladneſſe Kneeled down and Embraced His Knees, after ſome ſmall conference <hi>His Majeſty</hi> was had to His Lodging, and the Cunning Intiques of it ſhown Him, where after the King had reſted Himſelf that night, they conſulted about His Eſcape, which had been contrived by the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> before.</p>
            <p>Thereupon the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> having thus by a ſtrange providence met with <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> ſends away <hi>John Penderil</hi> to Mrs. <hi>Lane,</hi> who had before promiſed to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40427:17"/>ſerve <hi>His Majeſty</hi> even to the hazard of her Life, who ſent him back again with a parcell of Leaves of Wall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut-tree boiled in ſpring-water, to colour <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> hands, and alter the whiteneſſe of His skin where it was moſt obvious, and withall gave notice by him to the King, what time ſhe ſhould be ready.</p>
            <p>Which when <hi>John</hi> had related to the King, He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and fitted Himſelf for His Journey, and one Mr. <hi>Huddleſtone</hi> and Mr. <hi>Whitgreave,</hi> accommodated Him with Boots, Cloak, Money, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>On Thurſday Night the eleventh of <hi>September</hi> Col. <hi>Lane</hi> came with his ſiſter to a field adjoyning, and there they put the King before her, <hi>John</hi> having the honour to hold the Kings ſtirup while He mounted, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they two ſet forward, having taken direction to know the Country, and my Lady <hi>Lane</hi> having ſeverall recommendations to the allyes, friends and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taince of her family that lay in her intended road, if any untoward occaſion ſhould put them to the triall.</p>
            <p>The firſt place where they attempted to get the King on ſhipboard was at a place called <hi>Crods and Peet</hi> hard by <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> in order to which deſign Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to the houſe of Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of hers, ſince Knighted by <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> which is called <hi>Leigh, His Majeſty</hi> Riding before her in the habit of her ſervingman.</p>
            <p>To relate each ſeverall accident which happened to them in their way, might ſeem too tedious to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as the Sermon was to thoſe that were conſtrained to hear it. I ſhall therefore only for Illuſtration of the ſtory touch at ſome paſſages which were moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. <hi>His Majeſty</hi> being ſomething indiſpoſed in body, complained to Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> that the cloak wearied Him,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40427:18"/>whereupon ſhe deſired Mr. <hi>Laſtell</hi> to carry it, but long had they not rid ſo when they met her Brother in Law upon the road, who amongſt other queſtions, asked her, if her Father muſt carry her mans cloak, ſhe to wipe off all ſuſpition made him this ready excuſe, (which if a ſin certainly a Veniall one) that it was ſo big, it often endangered the throwing her off the horſe, and therefore ſhe had deſired him to carry it.</p>
            <p>Scarce were they rid of this danger, but they met with a far greater, being to paſſe through a Town where a Troop of horſe was drawn up, as if in oppoſition to hinder their paſſage: the Lamb though innocent fears the Woolf, and a dangerleſſe fear is better then a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe danger, but the Captain was Civill, took them for honeſt travellers (as indeed they were,) and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Troop to open to the Right and Left, gave them quiet paſſage.</p>
            <p>Hitherto hath our Story been Tragicall, but ſeldome is a day ſo cloudy that the Sun makes no appearance: <hi>Diogenes</hi> though Cynicall would ſometimes ſmile, and <hi>His Majeſty</hi> ſurrounded as it were with misfortune, yet met with one paſſage which made Him to laugh; coming to <hi>Leigh</hi> as before is ſaid, He was left in the Kitchin under the notion of a Serving-man, with whom the Maid enters into diſcourſe, asking Him where He was Born, what Trade He was of, with many other queſtions ſuitable to a Kitchin-Maids Curioſity; the King anſwers, He was Born at <hi>Brumingham,</hi> and a Nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors Son; after ſome other diſcourſe the Jack being down, the Maid deſires Him to wind it up, which He undertakes, but being unskilfull therein, goes the wrong way about it, and ſomewhat prejudices it; the Maid herewith highly incenſed, (Cooks being moſt part of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40427:18"/>a chollerick diſpoſition,) vents her paſſion in ſcolding tearms, asking Him where He was bred, and telling him He was the verieſt Ignorant fellow ſhe ever ſaw in her life, that could not tell how to wind up a Jack, with other ſuch Language as came firſt to her tongues end; which being uttered with much vehemency made <hi>His Majeſty</hi> notwithſtanding His preſent condition to goe out of the room ſmiling.</p>
            <p>Being in the ſame place, becauſe the Gentleman Keeping a Noble houſe, <hi>His Majeſty</hi> feared the great reſort thither might occaſion a diſcovery of His Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he faigned Himſelf ſick of an ague, and ſo keeps His Chamber all day, coming down only at nights; now that diſeaſe naturally making men cold and thirſty, <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to poſſeſſe them that His diſtemper was reall, deſires of the Butler a glaſſe of wine, who cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly invites Him into the butlery, where the Butler forces Him to drink two or three Healths; one to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> and another to His Mother: But at length notwithſtanding His diſguiſe, ſuſpected Him to be the King, and thereupon falling on his Knees he begged <hi>His Majeſties</hi> pardon, and aſſured Him that he would be faithfull to Him in whatever He ſhould command Him, of which the King ſeemed to take no notice, but having drunk off His wine went out; but the Butlers ſuſpicion encreaſing further, to ſatisfie his Curioſity, went up to Mr. <hi>Laſtell,</hi> asking him how long he had had that ſervant; Mr. <hi>Laſtell</hi> though angry at the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers inquiſitiveneſſe, yet would needs know a reaſon of him for his demand, who whiſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing him in the ear, told him he did believe it was the King. Whereupon fearing a diſcovery, ſends immediately up for <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> acquainting Him with the Butlers ſuſpicion, the King though angry that He made Him not firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainteſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40427:19"/>with it, yet putting confidence in him denied it not, and afterwards found him very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in His conveyance through the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty</hi> willing to be freed from theſe dangers, was very deſirous to be gone; but though there lay a little Bark there, deemed very fit for the purpoſe, yet the Maſter would for no reward tranſport a ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; whereupon <hi>His Majeſty</hi> not willing to tempt providence too far, deſired to go further Weſtward, to a Noble Gentleman whom He knew to be a truſty friend, and being conducted thither by Mr. <hi>Laſtell</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> He there takes His leave of them with many thanks for their care and kindneſſe, till God ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Him to require them better.</p>
            <p>Having with due reſpect been carefully concealed in this houſe for a week, at laſt preparation being made of a paſſage for Him, but coming to the place where it was provided, He chanced to dine with a Parliament Col. then there; wherefore fearing His Embarking ſingly might breed ſuſpition in him, He rather choſe to loſe the benefit of His paſſage, then after ſo many ſtormes and tempeſts to be ſplit upon a rock within ſight of harbour.</p>
            <p>Wherefore returning back to the place from whence He came, He concealed Himſelf there three weeks longer, and then was conveyed through by-ways to a Gentlemans houſe in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> where having continued ſome few days, he heat of ſearch after Him being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily well over, He was at laſt furniſhed with that ſmall Veſſell, which is now to be ſeen riding at anchor over againſt <hi>White-hall;</hi> the Veſſell being brought, <hi>His Majeſty</hi> went to <hi>Shoreham</hi> a little Creek in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and there took ſhipping; when the skipper ſaw it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40427:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>was <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> for it ſeems he had ſeen Him oft be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he was a little daunted. But afterwards recollect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, he ſaid, he was reſolved to Venture hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>His Majeſty;</hi> to which <hi>His Majeſty</hi> replyed, that he need not put himſelf upon that Venture, for that he might go along with Him, where he ſhould not want as long as He was able to provide for him; thus ſetting Sale from <hi>Shoreham,</hi> they in a ſmall time came to Land near <hi>Havre de Grace</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to look a little back, great was the Liſt of priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners taken at <hi>Woreeſter,</hi> and many taken in the purſuit, inſomuch that the gleanings were almoſt anſwerable to the Harveſt; but more conſiderable to them who were publickly ſuffered to make a gain of, by felling them beyondſea to perpetuall ſlavery: this made the Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian party Cock a hoop, and to make it the greater, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like days of Thankſgiving are appointed, to make God the patronizer of their Villanies, Murders, Tyrannies, and Treaſons. And now ſay they, were not people blind, they might ſee God himſelf owning our cauſe, in thoſe wonderfull ſucceſſes he beſtowes upon us: an argument ſcarcely worth the anſwering, yet of great weight amongſt their filly Proſelites. Then might the Turk boaſt of the purity of his Religion from the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Territories, and his ſeverall victories over Chriſtian Princes. <hi>Ovid</hi> though a Heathen could have taught them better Divinity then ſo.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<hi>Careat ſucceſſibus opto,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quiſquis ab eventu facta notanda putat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>—<hi>May he never speed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who from th' event makes meaſure of the deed.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40427:20"/>
            <p>Not long after, the Juncto had knowledge how the king eſcaped, whereupon they vowed to make Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> exemplary, <hi>(Oh the grievous crime of Loyalty!)</hi> But ſhe having notice of their intentions, puts her ſelf into the habit of a Country-maid, and ſo croſſes the Country on foot to <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> where ſhe got ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, which conneyed her ſafe into <hi>France: His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> having notice of her arrivall, ſent ſome perſons of quality in Coaches to conduct her to <hi>Paris;</hi> Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the Queen His Mother, and the Dukes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> going ſome part of the way to meet her, entertaining her with this gratefull expreſſion, <hi>Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my Life.</hi> And ſo taking her into His own Coach, conducted her to <hi>Paris,</hi> where ſhe was entertained with the applauſe and wonder of the whole Court. The Juncto in the mean time had ſent Souldiers to ſearch after her, but miſſing their prey, they in revenge burnt down to the ground that poor Cottage where <hi>His Majeſty</hi> firſt took ſhelter after His eſcape from <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet one Note more may I conceive be thought not unworthy of our Story; Many there were who had got rich prizes in the plunder of the City of <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> by which they imagined themſelves enriched all the dayes of their lifes; but this wealth was to them <hi>Aurum Tholoſanum,</hi> being not only conſumed in a few days, but waſted with it the reſt of their Eſtates. And for the City it ſelf, ſhe quickly exalted her ſelf again, and is ſaid to be now in a better condition then ſhe was before.</p>
            <p>But let us at laſt proceed from the battle to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects which it produced. <hi>Cromwell</hi> heightned with theſe ſucceſſes, began to think of putting his ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes in practice; and firſt he turns the Juncto out of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40427:20"/>doors, a thing he knew would be very acceptable to the people, as being the originall of all our Calamities; but his ambition was to make himſelf great, not to give relief and take away the tyranny, therefore in ſtead of thoſe he puld down, he ſets up another of his own arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Election, who knew what they had to do before they met; for having ſat a while without doing of any thing conſiderable, they reſign up their power to him, and by the help of the Officers of the Army and <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> inſtrument, make him (the Lord protect us) <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> (The Common-wealth being in its Infancy) yet in this were we happy, that in his Reign one Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant only Lorded it over us, but in the Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment many.</p>
            <p>Now though <hi>Oliver</hi> had often ſworn againſt the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by a ſingle perſon, he could eaſily diſpence with ſuch triviall things as oaths, and thought them binding no further then conducible to his own intereſt: and becauſe he could not crave a bleſſing from God upon ſuch wicked practiſes, he ſeeks to eſtabliſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by humane policy; Being of no Religion, he gives a toleration to all; ſo that what was once ſaid of <hi>Amsterdam, (that if a man had loſt his Religion, there he might find it,)</hi> might now as fitly be applyed to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> here being <hi>Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, Quakers, Ranters, Adamites, Fift Monarchy men,</hi> and ſuch a Rabble more, that I want a Dictionary to find out their names. The two firſt indeed having not much fault beſides their Pride and Ambition, of which one writes of them, <hi>That</hi> Pope John <hi>in his Chair never thought himſelf ſo big as a Cynicall</hi> Presbyter <hi>amongſt his</hi> Lay-Elders, <hi>or as an</hi> Independent <hi>in a</hi> Committee of Tryers, &amp;c. <hi>Neither did</hi> Pope Joan <hi>in her State, over think ſo well of her ſelf as a ſanctified</hi> Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40427:21"/>
               <hi>wife, dreſt up in her beſt attire.</hi> The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> are a bloudy people, fatall both to Kingdomes and Common-wealths; and although <hi>England</hi> felt not much of their Cruelties, being timely prevented by the Divine Providence, yet wofull <hi>Germany</hi> was a long time a Stage for their Tragedies, being died red with many horrible murthers and maſſacres. The <hi>Quakers</hi> are of a ſowre Generation, who defie all Learning, of a crabbed diſpoſition, looking rather like Fantaſms or furies ſent from Hell to deceive the world, then Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. Yet grew they extreame potent, boaſting in their Schiſmaticall opinions, and ſeducing many poor and ignorant people to their own damnation. But ſhould I give you an account of every particular Sect, 'twould take up an age to deſcribe them: No day but produced its Schiſme or Hereſie, no Cobler but would preſume to make himſelf the head of a Sect or Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, glorying in thundring the holy word of God out of his prophane lips to his ſhe-Auditors, (for ſo for the moſt part they were;) who liſten to him as to an Oracle, and he preſuming his confidence to be knowledge, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries himſelf as proudly as if he were their Ghoſtly father.</p>
            <p>But to proceed. He knew that <hi>what was acqueſted by force muſt be maintained by violence;</hi> and therefore he had a care in raiſing ſuch indigent perſons to prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as might if not for love to him their Governour, yet for the preſervation of their own intereſts, ſpend their bloud in oppoſing any that might make reſiſtance. And as he raiſed vallies, ſo he leveld mountains; Great men being like metled Horſes, (if not well look'd to) may chance to caſt thoſe yong Riders, who are ſcarce ſetled in the ſadle. Thoſe who would not acknowledge him to be their Head, he made no more to do but cut
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40427:21"/>their heads off; to recite all thoſe who ſuffer'd under him, would make a fourth volume to <hi>Foxes</hi> Martyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy; not any who had the leaſt appearance of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe and worth, but ſuffered by death or ſequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whileſt his own Muſhrom'd Gentility, ſprung up in a Night of Rebellion, were the ſimple nothings then adored.</p>
            <p>His ſpies (of whom he had many) were very uſefull to him, the charges of whom amounted to no leſſe then two hundred Thouſand pounds <hi>per annum.</hi> Theſe were not onely diſtributed about all places of <hi>England,</hi> but very converſant in the Courts of moſt Chriſtian Princes; by this ſilver hook he gained intelligence from moſt places, and ſeldome are any ſecrets ſo cloſe lock't up that a golden key will not open. Then for Souldiers he took ſuch a courſe that he had always enough of them, having brought the Commons ſo low by want of Trade, that they muſt either take up Armes or ſtarve; nor would he want occaſion to keep up an Army on foot, for when he had no cauſe he could ſoon create one; witneſs the war he made with <hi>Spain,</hi> (<hi>Englands</hi> faſt friend in all the late troubles,) by which the Trade of <hi>England</hi> hath been more detrimented then by all the wars we have had ſince 1638.</p>
            <p>Having thus tyrannized over <hi>England</hi> the ſpace of five years, he at laſt made his <hi>exit</hi> in a moſt horrible tempeſt, we may well ſay that God was not in that winde, though we have cauſe to praiſe his bleſſed and holy name for that wind-fall. As he lived unbeloved, ſo he died unlamented, breathing out his ſoul with the ſin of perjury, for at his being choſen Protector, he called God to witneſs he was againſt <hi>Englands</hi> govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being made Hereditary; abuſing to that purpoſe the ſaying of <hi>Solomon, Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 2.19. <hi>Who knoweth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40427:22"/>whether his ſon ſhall be a wiſe man or a fool?</hi> Yet at his death he endeavoured all he could to ſettle it in his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, leaving his Son <hi>Richard</hi> Protector of <hi>England,</hi> and his Son <hi>Henry</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland.</hi> And though at his death the Common-wealth was indebted ſome millions of pounds, yet never was any King of <hi>England</hi> buried in that ſtate as was this grand Tyrant, the charges of his funerall amounting to no leſſe then ſixty thouſand pounds, beſides that he was preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly interred among <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Anceſtors at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> in that very place where <hi>His Majeſty</hi> had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for His own reſt, as if he had reſolved not only to detain Him from His right when He was alive, but when He was dead alſo.</p>
            <p>The Protector being interred among the Kings and Queens at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (at a vaſter charge then had been uſed before in the richeſt times) his Son <hi>Richard,</hi> an honeſt private gentleman well beloved in <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> aſcended the throne by the invitation and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of <hi>Fleotwood, Desborough, Sydenham,</hi> the two <hi>Jones's, Thurlow</hi> and others, the relations and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidents of his father, and by the contrivance of the Court received congratulations prepared at <hi>Whitehall</hi> from moſt of the Counties and Cities of <hi>England,</hi> and from the Armies of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with engagements to live and dye with him, with addreſſes from the Independent Churches brought by <hi>Goodwin</hi> and <hi>Nye</hi> their <hi>Metropolitans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This introduction being made to transferre the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment from the line of the <hi>Stuarts</hi> to the line of the <hi>Cromwells,</hi> it was conceived by ſome who had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thus far, that a Parliament choſen by influences from Court, would eaſily ſwallow what was ſo well prepared to their hands. Accordingly it was reſolved
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40427:22"/>by the Protectors Juncto, that a Parliament ſhould be called, who being met at the time and place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, they firſt declare <hi>Richard Cromwell</hi> Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and chief Magiſtrate of the Common-wealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then they vote, after 14. days oppoſition from the honeſt party in the houſe, to tranſact with the new Houſe of Lords. Other things they did not ſo pleaſing to the Protector and his party. For they order a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee to look after the accompts of the Nation in order to retrenching and leſſening the charge of the Common-wealth. They had alſo by a ſaving vote aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted their intereſt in the fleet, and had under conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration an act for taking away all Laws, Statutes and Ordinances, concerning Exciſe, and Tunnage and Poundage, after three years.</p>
            <p>Proceeding thus ſucceſsfully with much ſatisfaction to the Nation, the Protector and the Officers of the Army, who before were jealous of one another, grew now jealous of the Houſe of Commons, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they thought it ſeaſonable to contend for the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, before the People ſhould recover it from them both. In order hereunto the Officers of the Army keep their Councels at <hi>Wallingford-Houſe,</hi> and the Protector with his party countermin'd them at <hi>Whitehall.</hi> The reſult of the <hi>Officers</hi> debates was a Canting Repreſentation, written in ſuch an equivocating language, that the ſting was eaſily viſible through the Honey.</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Protector begins to think of ſecuring himſelf, and forbids their meetings, but in vain; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both ſides keep guards one againſt another day and night. In this divided poſture affairs continued till <hi>Friday</hi> the 22. of <hi>Aprill</hi> 59. on which morning early the Protectors brother <hi>Fleetwood, Diſborough,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:40427:23"/>his Unkle, carrying the greater part of the Army with them, and the Protectors party flinching, the conqueſt was obtain'd without one drop of blood, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector forc'd to conſent to the diſſolving of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, contrary to the beſt advice, his own intereſt and promiſes.</p>
            <p>Far different was the courage of this young Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor from that of our magnificent Hero <hi>Henry</hi> the 5. who having haſtily taken the Crown from the pillow of his not yet deceaſed father, and being by him with a ſad ſigh told that God knew how unjuſtly he had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it; replyed, <hi>That ſince his father had by his ſword attained it, and being now at his death by Gods Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence devolved on him, that therefore his ſword ſhould maintain it as his Right against all oppoſers.</hi> But our pittifull Protector wanted both his wit and valour, for having by fortune gotten a Crown without the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of either bloud or treaſure, yet was loth to do ſo much as to draw a ſword for its preſervation, thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Engliſh Proverb, <hi>Lightly come, lightly go,</hi> men ſeldome prizing that which they never ſweat for.</p>
            <p>The fathers ſervants being now grown the Sons Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, allow him ſome thouſands of pounds, and order him to retire into the Country; but the turning out <hi>Richard</hi> was not all they had to do, his Brother <hi>Henry</hi> was ſtill poſſeſſed of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who was looked upon as a man of a more couragious ſpirit, and doubtleſs they had found him ſo, would the Officers of the Army have ſtuck cloſe to him as at firſt they promiſed, but they (according to the courſe of the world) left him when he had moſt need of them, and ſo made him incapable either of aſſiſting himſelf, or reſtoring his Brother.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:40427:23"/>
            <p>The Protector being thus deveſted of all power and authority, <hi>Lambert</hi> comes again upon the ſtage, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſo large a ſpirit and undaunted courage, that <hi>Oliver</hi> fearfull of his great endownments, had depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him of all command in the Army, onely making him a member of his pageant houſe of Lords; during whoſe Protectorſhip he lived as 'twere retired, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in vain to ſtruggle againſt one who had got ſo ſetled a power; but he being dead, and an opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty given him to preſent himſelf again upon the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, his ambitious ſpirit would not let him lie ſtill, but attempts to make himſelf Commander of theſe three kingdomes, as <hi>Oliver</hi> (by his means) had done before; which deſign of his in the ſequell ruined him, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered thoſe grand cheates and abuſes which that party had put upon the Nation, endeavouring to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave them to their own Arbitrary power, whileſt they pretended to weare thoſe glorious yet ſtrangely wreſted names of Religion and Liberty.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, having pulled down one Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they are inforc'd to ſet up another, well knowing the people would not be contented to be ruled by the ſword, of all Governments the moſt unjuſt and arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and ſince they muſt have one, they reſolve to have one like themſelves, <hi>even thoſe men that murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the King, and had for ſome years enſlaved their Native Country.</hi> This Rump or fag end of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment do they pitch upon; So theſe Tyrants cement and knit together again like a Snakes tail, and for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour called themſelves <hi>the Revivers of the good old caſe,</hi> and were as buſy as if they had another King and three kingdomes to deſtroy. Thus by Gods permiſſion that old rotten Government which was the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t cauſe of <hi>Englands</hi> ruine, is new vampt and ſet up again, to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40427:24"/>bring the people into a far worſe then Egyptian bondage and ſlavery.</p>
            <p>Two things are to be wondered at in this tranſaction, Firſt, how the Rump durſt credit or give any truſt to the army, having formerly turned them out of doores, and likewiſe ſo lately deſerted their young Protector; And ſecondly, how the Army durſt truſt them whom they had ſo groſſely abuſed, with a full power over them to place and diſplace whom they pleaſed. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Rumpes intention was no leſſe, then to ſerve the Army as they had formerly ſerved them; but the Army were as cunning as they were crafty, and having knowledge of their deſign, inhibited their uſurped ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as you ſhall hear anon.</p>
            <p>Upon notice of the ſitting of the Rump, thoſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers who had been ſecluded by the Army in 1648. for refuſing to dip their hands in the bloud of their Prince; now demand an equall intereſt with the others to ſit and Vote; but as they had formerly been violently thruſt out, ſo are they now forcibly kept out by the Officers of the Army. This affront is highly reſented by them, Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> one of thoſe ſecluded members writing ſtrongly againſt them; proving them by ſeveral reaſons to be no Parliament, but onely a tyrannicall and illegall authority: <hi>they being first diſſolved by the death of the King who ſummoned them, he being</hi> Principium, cauſa &amp; finis Parliamenti. <hi>Secondly, they not being the fourth part of that number which ought to conſtitute a Parliament, the reſt of their fellow-members being at ſeverall times turned out of the houſe, according to the pleaſure of the factious army; ſo that moſt Shires and Corporations in</hi> England <hi>being unjuſtly deprived of their Burgeſſes, had no power nor intereſt in the government of the Nation. Thirdly, their power being again de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40427:24"/>into the people, who having by their Votes choſen another, did diſannul the autherity of this Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> But it was in vain to talk of Law to thoſe who would be ruled by none; However for the ſecurity of themſelves they proceed vigorouſly to change the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Army, cauſing them to take commiſſions from <hi>Lenthall</hi> whom they made Generall, making all the haſt they can to ſettle themſelves under the notion of the <hi>Good old cauſe.</hi> In the mean time the ſecluded party of the Houſe joyning with the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> party, who were now kept under by the predominant faction of <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> they combine toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſeek to gain by force what by fair means they could not attain; and this their deſign they make al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt generall over <hi>England,</hi> that as the ruine threatned the whole Nation, ſo was the whole Nation concerned in the redreſſe. <hi>Auguſt</hi> the firſt, (the day appointed by the Rump for the baniſhing the Cavaliers out of <hi>London</hi>) was the time ſet for them to riſe; But by the treachery of ſome of the Confederates, moſt places of their randevous were diſcovered, and ſo the deſign for the moſt part diſappointed. Yet Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> with divers other Gentlemen in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> and <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> raiſed a conſiderable force, and having ſecured <hi>Weſtcheſter</hi> and ſome other places, declared for a free Parliament, and to maintain the rights and priviledges of the people, the whole Nation (ſaving onely the Sectaries, and ſuch who had raiſed themſelves by the ruines both of Church and State) praying for their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, but few or none ſtirring to their aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>It is a thing to be taken notice of even to admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that thoſe very people who made their lawfull Soveraignes raiſing a little ſhip-money (which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs was expended for the benefit and ſecurity of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40427:25"/>the Nation) without authority of Parliament, one of the chief pleas for their raiſing wars againſt him, yet could now be contented with ſuch unparalleld impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and tyrannies, as no Hiſtory can acquaint us with the like; The <hi>Sicilian</hi> Tyrants being but meer ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows to theſe, whom we may juſtly call the very quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of all tyranny and oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>But to return to our purpoſe, the Rump had ſoon notice of this riſing, and immediately ſend out forces to oppoſe them, making <hi>Lambert</hi> head of the party, which gave him as fair an opportunity to put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his ambitious deſignes as poſſibly could be; He in ten dayes marches to them, faces, fights, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes them; re-takes thoſe holds which they had poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, and ſo returns again victorious. Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> ſoon after was taken in a womans apparell at <hi>Newport Pagnel,</hi> and committed priſoner to the Tower of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Rump in token of their gratitude to <hi>Lambert</hi> for his good ſervice, order him a Thouſand pound to buy him a Jewell, which he as frankly beſtows amongſt his Souldiers, intending they ſhould require him at a dead lift; this leſſon he had cond of his Maſter <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> to lay an Obligation upon the Souldiery, who now were grown altogether mercenary. This act of his diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leaſed the Rump, who now began to find out his deſign, but were not able to hinder it.</p>
            <p>Whileſt <hi>Lambert</hi> was thus acting in the North, the Rump were as buſy in conſulting all ways for their own ſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, as well from being ſupplanted by the Army, as to ſuppreſs the peoples inſurrection; to this purpoſe they ſetle the Trained Bands in <hi>London,</hi> with ſix Troops of Horſe, and began to raiſe the Militia in the Counties, appointing ſuch Commanders over them as were fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40427:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet aſſertors of their intereſt. Thoſe Governours of Garriſons who held for the Army they put out, placing others in their Rooms, whom they could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in; and raiſe three new Regiments, compoſed for the moſt part of Anabaptiſts, Quakers, and fift-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy-men, whom they call the Congregationall Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade, and now they hope in ſhort time to be ſtrong enough, not onely to keep the people under, but in due time to curb the pride of the inſolent Army.</p>
            <p>But all their endeavours were to little purpoſe, <hi>Lambert</hi> heightned with his ſucceſſe, ſcornes to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject himſelf to any ſuperiour power, and was reſolved to leave no ſtone unturned till he had ſet up himſelf; and indeed his hopes were great, having beſides an obliged Army, many of the Rumpers themſelves his friends; the chief of whom was Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> or rather <hi>Sir Humerous Vanity,</hi> a meer <hi>Proteus</hi> in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, the chief ring-leader of all the frantick Sectari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; of a turbulent ſpirit, and working Braine: a ſtrange compoſition of Choler and Melancholy, who having given himſelf wholly to whimzies in Religion, would find out crotchets in State too, and thoſe the ſtrangeſt in the world, as well his Modell teſtifies: Which we have thought fit to inſert, that men may ſee the danger which the nation hath ſcaped.</p>
            <p>The firſt poſition was,</p>
            <p>That all men being by nature free, are equally free from an over-ruling Magiſtraticall power.</p>
            <p>If there be any exceſs in the ſufferings of a ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed party, they are not to conſider what the prevalent party does, but what moves them to give them ſuch actions, ſeeing that inconſiſtency of principles juſtify a ſcrupulous ſeverity.</p>
            <p>Where there are two or more parties diſagreeing as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40427:26"/>to the Erection of a government, and but one agrees to this determinate forme, there the Magiſtrate hath onely a direct power onely from and over them; his power over others is indirect, and in order to the ſafety of thoſe that impowred him.</p>
            <p>That they are onely the people of a Country who upon the Erection of a Government have impowred the Legiſlators to act, being avowedly ready to ſtand by and uphold them, and not every one that either farmes or actually poſſeſſes lands therein.</p>
            <p>Thoſe diſtenting people ought to be onely as the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots</hi> to the <hi>Lacedemonians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be in the pay of the State, doth not render an army Mercenary, or deprive them of their ſhare in being the people.</p>
            <p>That thoſe are moſt truly the people of this Nation, who owned the Parliament in that day of Triall, when Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> was up in <hi>Cheſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neuters in any part and conſtitution of Government, are not to be conſidered as the people.</p>
            <p>That the Presbyterians are excluded from being the people.</p>
            <p>That the Sectaries are all included both by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious and ſubſequent ſervices to the Parliament.</p>
            <p>That there is no Religion, which can lead a man to renounce the performances of ſuch actions, as render him capable of civill or politicall ſociety.</p>
            <p>That the faithfulneſſe of the Sectaries, is that whereby the State hath been and muſt be ſecured, and is ſufficient to diſcharge ſatisfactorily, whom an equall Toleration can make them capable of.</p>
            <p>Silence is not to be taken for conſent, where a party is under force.</p>
            <p>Good orders doe not ſecure a Common-wealth,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40427:26"/>wherein the Major or more active part is out-ſpirited for ſuch a form.</p>
            <p>It is not the making a Common-wealth by force that deſtroys a Common-wealth, but their not making it naturall afterwards.</p>
            <p>To make a Government Naturall, the Circumſtances of affaires muſt be ſo diſpoſed of, that they may neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate to ſuch a poſture.</p>
            <p>That thoſe who have adhered to the Army and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in the laſt conſpiracy, be every one of them regiſter'd as liberators of their Country, and that they be the prime Gentlemen, and onely capable of places of power and truſt, and that their poſterity ſhall claime if of equall abilities, preheminence before others.</p>
            <p>That all theſe be put into a military poſture under a faithfull commander, and let none elſe have the uſe of Armes.</p>
            <p>That the Armies of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> be inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the number of the Liberators of the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> and regiſtred accordingly.</p>
            <p>That this body of the Militia of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> chooſe a proportion'd number of deputies at their Muſters, who may elect out of their number ſome perſons who are to make up the ſelect Senate, or Conſervators of the Liberty of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this Senate be for life, onely that there be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate number to be inquiſitors into the Senate.</p>
            <p>That this Senate be choſen out of the ſeverall parties called Independents, Anabaptiſts, Fift-Monarchy-men and Papiſts.</p>
            <p>That Papiſts, Epiſcopall men and Presbyterians be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
            <p>That the forces now in being continue for ever, as guards to the Parliament, Council of State, and ſelect Senate.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:40427:27"/>
            <p>This is the Chief part of Sir <hi>Henry Vanes</hi> Modell, by which the Nation may ſee the maſſacre which was intended to be made of their ancient Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. And indeed as one writes of this <hi>Pſeudo-Lyeur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, he was the fitteſt man to advance any intereſt to the ruine of Government, who can but ſooth him with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reit that he is pleaſed with his Chimeras;</hi> ſuch an one both <hi>Cromwell</hi> and <hi>Lambert</hi> found him, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made him ſubſervient to their deſignes.</p>
            <p>But to come to the matter, <hi>Lambert</hi> having finiſhed his work in the North, in his march back to <hi>London</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to ſet his deſign on foot; and herein he imitates the Ivie, which being not able to ſupport it ſelf, mounts up by the Oake, and at length kills it; ſo he makes uſe of <hi>Fleetwood</hi> as a ſtirrop for his ambition to climbe up withall, meaning to pull the ſtaires down when he was gotten up, as <hi>Oliver</hi> before had ſhown him the way. To this purpoſe the Souldiers by his inſtigation ſend up a paper to <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> to be by him or Col. <hi>Cobbet</hi> preſented to the Juncto, under the name of <hi>the humble Repreſentation of the forces under the command of the Lord Lambert in the late Northern expedition;</hi> The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of which Paper was, that <hi>Fleetwood</hi> might be made Captain Generall of all the forces in <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> &amp; that <hi>Lambert, Desborow,</hi> and <hi>Monke,</hi> might likewiſe be made Generall Officers; and that Sir <hi>George Booth,</hi> and the reſt of his complices, might be brought to ſpeedy tryall, &amp;c. <hi>Fleetwood</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Paper, calls a counſell of ſome officers to conſider of it, and not ſounding the depth of <hi>Lamberts</hi> deſigne, communicates it to Sir <hi>Arthur Haſelrig</hi> and Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> members of the houſe; <hi>Haſelrig</hi> being a perſon of a turbulent ſpirit, acquaints the Juncto with it, tels them there was ſome deſigne hatching by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40427:27"/>the Army, ſuſpects <hi>Lamberts</hi> ambition to make himſelf chief in the government of the Land, and raſhly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth to ſend him to the Tower.</p>
            <p>The Rump netled herewith, ſend to <hi>Fleetwood</hi> for the Paper, he gives them a Copy of it, but pretends the Original was in <hi>Cobbets</hi> hands, who being ſent for would not be at home when it ſhould be delivered; this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſes them more then before, therefore to let them know that ſervants ought not to preſcribe rules to their Lords and Maſters, they immediately Vote, that the making of more Generall officers was needleſſe, chargable, and dangerous to the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>The Army though angry at the Juncto's votes, were yet ſo wiſe as to diſſemble it, and in ſtead of breaking out into fury, in an humble Petition proteſt their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions <hi>to be ſtill true and faithfull to them, what ever theirs and the enemies of the publike good might ſuggeſt againſt them; deſiring them not to believe that they had any intentions to diſſolve their power, or to the ſetting up of a ſingle Perſon, which they had ſo ſolemnly and freely declared againſt,</hi> concluding with ſeverall Propoſitions, pretended for the Nations good, and reiterated pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of their fidelity.</p>
            <p>Thus did they ſtrive to out-vie one another in diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, yet durſt not truſt each others fidelity; the Army conſcious of having wronged their maſters, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in ſo high a degree, their guilty conſciences fed ever on a fearfull diſtruſt of revenge. The Juncto on the other ſide had to their coſt ſeen by former experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the danger of making a Generall over their Armies, who ſhould have full power to give Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to their officers, and place and diſplace whom he pleaſed; they knew that from ſuch a preferment there was but one ſtep to a ſingle Perſon, and ſo by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40427:28"/>ſequence they ſhould be bereaved of their authority. Thus did the Cocks of both factions peck at one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and both of them wanting true worth in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, would make a Ladder of miſchief to climbe up to promotion.</p>
            <p>Yet the Juncto receives their Petition with a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hearty thanks, but gave no credit to what they ſaid, well knowing that whatever Oaths or Proteſtations the Army made, if once they oppoſed their intereſt, they were utterly void; therefore to ſecure themſelves, they ſeek to draw to their adherence what part of the Army they could, and thought they had aſſured to themſelves two Regiments of Horſe, and one of Foot; which with their Congregationall Brigade, the Trained Bands of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Militia of the ſeveral Counties, they hope they ſhall be able to deal with the Army.</p>
            <p>But by the treachery of <hi>Vane</hi> and ſome other falſe Brethren, their whole deſignes are betraid to the Army, who now think they have a juſt occaſion to diſſolve them, and which might likewiſe afford a fit plea to the people.</p>
            <p>Yet the Juncto thinking themſelves ſecure, doubt not but to fruſtrate their intentions, and make void the Commiſſions of <hi>Fleetwood, Lambert,</hi> and ſeven other ring-leading officers, ordering a Committee for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Army, and Vote it High Treaſon to raiſe any money but by Act of Parliament, &amp;c. But the Army in ſtead of quitting their power to the Juncto, reſolve that the Juncto ſhall quit theirs to them, and once more from ſervants intend to turn their Maſters.</p>
            <p>And now the game begins to work, the Rump ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what force they can about the Houſe; a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Foot, and four Troops of Horſe appear, who
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40427:28"/>are appointed to convenient places adjoyning to it, three Troops are ſent unto the City to crave their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but are denied, onely in <hi>Southwark</hi> they make ſome appearance.</p>
            <p>The Army on the other ſide are as quick in their preparations, and aſſemble what force they can about <hi>Whitehall;</hi> they likewiſe ſend to the City, but in vain, it reſolving to ſtand Neuter, having great cauſe to wiſh the deſtruction of both; and that they might not want wherewithall to doe it, the Tower of <hi>London</hi> ſupplies them both with Ammunition, and now had the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers been true to each ſide, there might have been ſome bloudy noſes amongſt them, but what <hi>Lucan</hi> ſaid of old was true of them, <hi>Nulla fides pietaſque, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Nor Faith nor Conſcience common ſouldiers have.</q>
            <p>And firſt the Rumps own Life-guard deſert them, upon ſight of a piſtoll preſented to their Captains breaſt by <hi>Lambert,</hi> and joyning with their enemies, force back their Speaker, that old Fox <hi>William Lenthall,</hi> who like a ſpunge hath ſuck'd up much of the Common-wealths treaſure, but may we hope in time be ſqueezed out again. The Congregationall Brigade (or the truſt that is in Sectaries) revolt likewiſe from them, and joyn with the Army.</p>
            <p>The ſpeaker <hi>Lenthall</hi> coming to the Houſe, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the oppoſition of the Souldiers, commands them as their Generall to return to their obedience to the Parliament, as he then call'd it, and to acknowledge him their ſupreme Commander; but <hi>Lambert</hi> riding among them, though rather like a Hagler then a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and awing them with his preſence, they return'd him no anſwer, but what he might underſtand by the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40427:29"/>Language of Brickbatts. Which oppoſition though he like not well, yet he preſſed to have gon forward; till <hi>Lambert</hi> coming up to his coach, whiſper'd him ſuch a word in his ear, that he was glad to wheel about and retire back to his own Houſe. So that the Rump, by ſuch affronts as theſe, taught the weakneſſe of their force, and the unwillingneſs of their ſouldiers to fight, were forc'd to pull down their proud Stomacks, though utterly averſe at firſt from hearkning to any Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to ſurrender their power into <hi>Lamberts</hi> hands, though to palliate the compulſive cauſe of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion; the Council of State ſeem'd to interpoſe as mediators, and both ſides were ſaid to withdraw to their quarters upon their command. But their partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſoon appear'd, the cauſe going clearly on <hi>Lamberts</hi> ſide, ſo that the poor Rumpers were quite ſhut out of dores for that bout.</p>
            <p>Thus thoſe men who had but ſome few months before ſolemnly proteſted their deep ſorrow for their wicked Apoſtacy and back-ſliding from the Good Old cauſe (as they called it,) and deviation from the way of God, (which without doubt they never intended to walk in) in the year 1653. when they interrupted the Rump, which were ſo grand Aſſertors of the peoples liberties, had taken ſuch paines, and acted ſuch glorious things (as they ſaid) for the (good but indeed inglorious for the bad) of the Nation; thoſe men who had with ſuch ſeeming hearty (but indeed feigned) expreſſions, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their repentance for their former diſturbance, and their now Reſolutions to be ſtedfaſt to them, thus ſoon forgot both th' one and th' other; and in ſo ſmall a time relapſed into what they then acknowledged for an error.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Officers who had aſſiſted the Rump are by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40427:29"/>the Army ſuſpended from their Commands; they like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by their Declaration diſanull all thoſe Votes which were diſpleaſing to them; thus did they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all Government which correſponded not with their will and intereſt.</p>
            <p>And now both Rump and Army put forth their Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, accuſing each other of a great deal of knavery, (of which they were both ſufficiently ſtored;) but as it often happens, <hi>when Thieves fall out true men come by their own,</hi> ſo by their appeaching one another, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to the world the grand cheats and abuſes they had put upon the Nation, which made the people to deteſt their horrid villanies and tyranny, and to wiſh the reſtoring of the rightfull Heir, of whom ſince his miraculous eſcape from <hi>Worceſter,</hi> we will in the next place undertake to diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty</hi> after his arrival in <hi>France,</hi> lived there for ſome while a retired life, during which time hap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that notable debate betwixt the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> and Cardinall <hi>Mazarine;</hi> the occaſion whereof was the Cardinalls great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower, and abuſe thereof, not only miſerably oppreſſing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> people, but alſo depriving the Princes of the Bloud of their Right; whereupon they charge him with ſeverall miſcarriages of State, to which the Cardinall makes a defenſive anſwer. The King alſo by the inſtigation of the Queen his Mother, (du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whoſe Regency <hi>Mazarine</hi> arrived to that height) enclines to his ſide, alledging <hi>That he had approved himſelf both a faithfull ſervant, and an able Miniſter of State.</hi> But the Princes were ſo exaſperated againſt him, that nothing but his baniſhment will ſerve their turn, which finding the King averſe unto, they reſolve to accompliſh their deſires by force, and to ſtrengthen their faction, deſire aſſiſtance of the Duke of <hi>Larraign,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:40427:30"/>then in ſervice of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> with ten thouſand men.</p>
            <p>Theſe differences arriving to ſuch a height, cauſed <hi>His Sacred Majeſty</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to uſe his utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to cement the breach, and bring them again to a reconciliation; but all his undertakings proved fruitleſs, and in ſtead of producing a pacification, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted an unjuſt odium upon himſelf, both the Princes and the Cardinall ſurmizing he counſelled the King againſt them.</p>
            <p>This falſe aſperſion coming to the ears of the vulgar, who were great adorers of the Princes, as thoſe whom they imagined ſtood for their Liberties, ſo incenſed them againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Princes, as to the threatning violence againſt their perſons; whereupon <hi>His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty</hi> (knowing the madneſs of popular commotions) to avoid their fury, retires himſelf for a while to Saint <hi>Germanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Cardinalls malice was more then the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, though he hid it under a politick veil, (as the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt waters carrie the ſmootheſt brow,) which he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward found opportunity to expreſſe, perſwading the King of <hi>France</hi> to make a peace with <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and moſt unworthily to diſſert his royal kinſman.</p>
            <p>But what is affinity or former courteſies in competiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with ſelf intereſt? the thrice valiant Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> who under the Marſhall of <hi>Turine</hi> had performed ſuch eminent ſervices againſt the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> as hath made his name deſervedly famous, yet was by them ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully expelled, with a Complemental Apology for his departure. This Magnaminous Prince who at eighteen years of age had done Acts anſwerable to the ancient Hero's, whoſe valour and prudence were in high eſteem with the moſt Renowned Princes throughout all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40427:30"/>nowithſtanding his many Remarkable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, yet was by this his near kinſman who ſtyleth himſelf <hi>The moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> moſt unchriſtianly deſerted, to ingratiate himſelf with an uſurping Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</p>
            <p>The moſt illuſtrious Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> who had a long time been detained by the Juncto in the <hi>Ile of Wight,</hi> and was at laſt per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itted by them to go to his Siſter the Princeſs Royal in <hi>Holland;</hi> being now like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe come thither for ſuccour and relief, was alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of <hi>France.</hi> This pious Prince whom neither the perſwaſions of great men, temptations of Riches and Honor, nor the ſevere commands of his own Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of never ſeeing her face again, could alter nor move from the Proteſtant profeſſion, could find no Harbor there in his diſtreſſe; <hi>Cromwells</hi> intereſt out weighing Majeſty, valour, piety, and conſanguinity.</p>
            <p>Theſe afflicted Princes being thus unworthily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken by the <hi>French</hi> King, <hi>His Sacred Majeſty</hi> took his journey into <hi>Germany,</hi> where the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> had long been Ambaſſador for him to ſollicite aid and aſſiſtance. The Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> followed him not long after, (accompanied with his Royal Siſter the Princeſſe of <hi>Orange,</hi>) whom they found at <hi>Collen.</hi> Having ſtaid there a while, theſe three Princes, together with the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Norwich,</hi> the Lord <hi>Newburg,</hi> and ſeverall Ladies and perſons of quality went in progreſſe to the Faire at <hi>Franckford,</hi> being complemented in all Princes Countries thorough which they paſſed, by their chief Miniſters of State, and ſaluted with their great guns from their Towns and Caſtles.</p>
            <p>During <hi>His Majeſties</hi> aboad at <hi>Frankford, Chriſtina</hi> Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> (who had ſome time before volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily reſigned her kingdome into the hands of <hi>Carolus
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40427:31"/>Guſtavus</hi> her kinſman,) was paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng that way in her intended journey to <hi>Italy:</hi> of which <hi>His Majesty</hi> having notice, (there being ſome ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pathy in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, onely with this diſtinction, the one a voluntary exile, the other forced from his kingdome by tyranny;) he with the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and a gallant Traine, gave her an interview at a Village called <hi>Conningſtein,</hi> not farre from <hi>Franckford;</hi> where betwixt theſe two Potentates paſſed many Ceremonious Complements, each thinking themſelves obliged to the other for ſo grand a favour.</p>
            <p>After ſome ſhort ſtay at <hi>Franckford, His Majeſty</hi> returned again to <hi>Colen,</hi> being by the way moſt ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly entertained by the Elector of <hi>Mentz:</hi> During his ſtay at <hi>Colen</hi> was found out the Treaſon of one Captain <hi>Manning,</hi> who under pretence of waiting on <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> diſcovered all his deſignes and councels to <hi>Cromwell;</hi> This unhappy wretch confeſſed his ſalla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from the Protector was a hundred pound a month: by which one may gueſſe the vaſt profuſion of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſpent upon theſe Villaines. His Treachery being diſcovered, he was by <hi>His Majeſties</hi> command ſent to a ſtrong Caſtle adjacent to <hi>Colen,</hi> there to be ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t cloſe priſoner. But his perfidiouſneſs was ſo highly reſented at Court, that one of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> ſervants (though contrary to order) piſtol'd him as he was lighting out of the Coach at the Caſtle-gate, which though it came far ſhort of his deſert, yet was not ſo well done, in ſending the Devill his due before his time, and wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hangman of his labour.</p>
            <p>Not long after upon the Breach betwixt <hi>Cromwell</hi> and the King of <hi>Spain, Don John de Auſtria,</hi> Governour Royal of the Low-countries for his Catholike Majeſty, ſent the Count <hi>de Fuenſaldagne</hi> his Ambaſſadour to our
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40427:31"/>King, ſolemnly inviting him into <hi>Flanders,</hi> aſſuring him in the name of His Royal Maſter all poſſible ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and aſſiſtance; which invitation <hi>His Majeſty</hi> kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepted, and leaving <hi>Colen</hi> came to <hi>Bruges,</hi> the place appointed for his reception, where for the moſt part he remained till ſuch time he was treated by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> for his return, finding the <hi>Spaniard</hi> of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Nature, and far more conſtant then the fickle <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hither not long after came his Brother the Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> who in regard of the great command which he had in the <hi>French</hi> Army, had ſtaid there till the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the League with <hi>Cromwell,</hi> but then was warned to depart with all his retinue (conſiſting of a gallant number of young <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen, bred up under his valour and conduct,) having but a ſhort time reſpited for their ſtay. (<hi>Cromwells</hi> hatred to the Royal family never ceaſing time nor place for their perſecution,) during which time he was viſited by the Duke of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dena</hi> then in <hi>France,</hi> and other <hi>French</hi> Grandees, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Marſhall of <hi>Turine,</hi> who bore an Honourable reſpect towards him, and was very ſorrowfull for his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſement.</p>
            <p>In his way he touched at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> where he was mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificently entertained by <hi>Don John,</hi> to whom he freely proffer'd his ſervice in the warrs, which was with a great deal of thanks accepted: and long wanted he not occaſion for his valour, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> forces (according to the Articles concluded on betwixt them) beleaguering <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> which being a place of great importance, (an inlet into <hi>Flanders</hi> by ſea,) cate was taken how to raiſe the ſiege: to which purpoſe <hi>Don John</hi> levies what forces he could either by his own or <hi>His Majeſties</hi> influence, which joyning with thoſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40427:32"/>noble Spirits under the thrice valiant Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> make up a conſiderable Army. Himſelf in perſon, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Dukes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them toward the Beſiegers; who having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of their approach, left ſuch forces in the Leagure as might ſecure them from a ſalley, and with the reſt drew up towards <hi>Don John;</hi> The <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> (notwithſtanding thoſe they had left in the Trenches) were more numerous then the <hi>Spaniards</hi> both in Horſe and Foot; whereupon adding confidence to their number, with undaunted reſolution drew up a forlorne hope of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Infantry, and deſperately charged the <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niſh</hi> Foot, and being ſeconded with <hi>Lockharts</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, after a hot diſpute gave them a totall rout, in this conflict L. C. <hi>Fenwick</hi> loſt his life. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cavalry ſeeing their Foot overthrown, fly with them for company, nor could by any perſwaſions be induced to ſtand; whereupon the <hi>French</hi> Horſe who all that while ſtood ſtill, with a full Carreir purſue their flying enemies. But the Duke of <hi>Yorkes</hi> Regiment not uſed to ſhew their backs to an enemy, gave them a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate charge and made them to ſtand, whileſt their flying Friends ſaved their lives: But after a noble and gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant reſiſtance, over-powered by numbers they were overthrown, very few of them eſcaping, amongſt which were the Dukes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> though the firſt was not heard of till three days after, whereupon ſome have conjectured that he was taken by the <hi>French</hi> forces, but by <hi>Turine</hi> after at a fit opportunity nobly releaſt.</p>
            <p>But to return again to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> affairs from whence we have made a long digreſſion. Great was the joy of the people at the <hi>exit</hi> of the Rump, not only rejoycing inwardly, but breaking out into open laughter
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40427:32"/>for joy: but <hi>nullum commodum ſine incommodo,</hi> there is no pleaſure without a diſpleaſure. No ſooner had the Rump left riding us, but up gets the <hi>Committee of ſafety</hi> into the ſadle, conſiſting of theſe perſons following.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charles Fleetwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Lambert.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gen. <hi>Desborough.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Steel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Whitlock.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Hen. Vane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>L. Gen. <hi>Ludlow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>C. Sydenham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>M. <hi>Saloway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>L. <hi>Strickland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Berry.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>L. <hi>Lawrence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>James Harrington.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Wariſton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>L. Major <hi>Ireton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Tichburn.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Hen. Brandrith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Robert Thompſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Hewſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Clerk.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Lilburn.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Bennet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Cornelius Holland.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Such a pack of fools and knaves, that had <hi>Lambert</hi> ſtudied ſeven years he could hardly have found ſuch another. Wherefore this government was far more the ſcorne and deriſion of the people then the former, who now begin to ſee the difference betwixt being rul'd by a gentle Prince, and many Ruſticks. The moſt remarkable thing that happened during their ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, was the death of that grand Regicide Preſident <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> (all their doughty acts beſides for the good of the Nation ſcarcely affording matter enough for <hi>Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> to make a penny Pamphlet of,) <hi>October</hi> 31. 1659. he made his <hi>exit,</hi> cheating thereby the Hangman of his due; But that there might be ſome ſhew of ſorrow made at his funerall, the Gallows (as related to him) was arrayed in mourning. And <hi>Needham</hi> writes his Elegy, when 'twould make a man ſmile to ſee the ſoft
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40427:33"/>and tender-hearted Villain weeping (like <hi>Niobe</hi> till he turn'd ſtone) over his Tombe: To ſee him cry with one eye and laugh with the other, (as one that could fit himſelf to all humours if gainfull,) and yet the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giecomicall Rogue keep his countenance. The tears of ſuch a Saint (as one writes) falling like drops of <hi>Lambeth</hi> ale upon the tongue of <hi>Dives;</hi> but enough of this filthy ſubject, we will take our farwell of him, and leave him with his fellow creatures, <hi>Judas, Ravillack, Catesby</hi> and <hi>Noll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though the Devil was merry at his Company in Hell, <hi>England</hi> was ſtill troubled with his Companions on earth, <hi>The Committee of ſafety</hi> were now Lords Paramount, whileſt the City of <hi>London</hi> for want of Trade was become a Cage of Broken Merchants, and Tradeſmen being ready to periſh for want of buſineſs, and their families for want of bread, nor had the poor any other employment then to curſe the cauſers of their miſeries. Their Longanimous patience being now worne out with a tedious expectation of a change, but ſeeing no hopes of any period to their miſeries ſo long as this uſurped government laſted, they reſolved to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition the Common Counſell for their aſſiſtance to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the obtaining of a free Parliament, according to which Reſolution a Petition was <hi>drawn, ſubſcribed,</hi> end <hi>preſented;</hi> but by reaſon of ſome pretended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formality in the addreſſe, it was laid aſide. However they reſolve the re-enforcement of it, but the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> not willing to hear of any things of this Nature, ordered part of the Army under Col. <hi>Huſon</hi> to march into the City, and by violence to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it as he march'd in the boys hooted at him, reviling his publike appearance for ſuch whom he might now perceive how the people generally hated; he minds
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40427:33"/>them not, but goes on; and being come to the Old Exchange, draws up his Myrmidons, where the boys per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting as they began, the incenſed Colonel cauſes his men to ſhoot among them, ſo that two or three of them were kill'd, and among the reſt one of the Colonels own <hi>calling,</hi> a cobler, who was accidentally ſtanding in the Croud. The Kings party ſeeing theſe tumults, expected now that ſomething might be done, and therefore they walk the ſtreets in great numbers pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately armed, with a reſolution to fall on, when they ſaw the Citizens begin. But the Major, then in great favour with the tumult, part by promiſes and part by intreaty kept all things very quiet; for which he was afterwards undeſervedly blam'd by thoſe who were over-cholerickly loyall. Neither was <hi>Huſon</hi> idle, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching up and down the City with that inſolence and barbariſme which is not to be expreſs'd, for beſides thoſe kill'd at the Exchange by the Colonels direction, (for which he was afterwards indicted and convicted at the <hi>Old-baily,</hi>) his ſouldiers took the Liberty in other places to maime ſome, and murder others; others to ſeize and carry away priſoners.</p>
            <p>But this was nothing to what they intended, the City muſt be burnt too, to make it a compleate ſacrifice of their indignation; to which purpoſe a prodigious quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of fire-balls were laid in at <hi>Pauls,</hi> and <hi>Greſham Colledge,</hi> which two places they had made Guards of, converting the houſe of prayer to a Den of Thieves. Thus was the City deſign'd for fire, ſword, and pillage, had not God by a timely period prevented their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.</p>
            <p>Thus while theſe mens miſcarriages doe inveſt <hi>His Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>esty</hi> with the love of his people, he lives retiredly at <hi>Bruges,</hi> expecting either what his loyall ſubjects
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40427:34"/>might, or what the ſucceſſe might be of that treaty which was then in agitation between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain. His Majesty</hi> having ſome hopes to believe that thoſe two Crowns united might joyn to his relief. In order to this treaty the two grand favorites of both Crowns being met upon the frontiers, <hi>His Majeſty</hi> was alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited thither by <hi>Don Lewis de Haro. His Majeſty</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this invitation at <hi>Dieppe</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> whither he had withdrawn himſelf to attend the ſucceſſe of Sir <hi>George Booths</hi> buſineſſe, his friends in <hi>England</hi> having given no ſmall encouragement to his hopes: But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ill ſucceſs of affairs in <hi>England,</hi> he haſts to the Frontiers; being come to <hi>Roan</hi> he takes poſt, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pani'd with the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond</hi> and the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> and being at length arrived near the end of their journey, he ſends to give <hi>Don Lewis</hi> notice of his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, who preſently with a noble traine came forth to meet him. When they came near, <hi>Don Lewis</hi> alighted from his horſe, and kneeling down, though in a place by reaſon of the dirt ſomewhat inconvenient for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he clapt his hands about <hi>His Majesties</hi> knees, and with a great deal of humility and affection kiſſed them. From this place <hi>Don Lewis</hi> accompanied <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to the place provided for his accommodation, riding bare-headed before him; where he was all the while of his ſtay nobly and ſumptuouſly entertained. Many propoſitions are made by <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to <hi>Don Lewis,</hi> as to the giving him aid and aſſiſtance for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining of his right, to all which <hi>Don Lewis</hi> returns civill and pleaſing anſwers, behaving himſelf with that reſpect to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> as if he had been his Maſter himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty</hi> having ſpent ſome time here returns to <hi>Paris</hi> where he ſtaid with his Mother ſome few days,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40427:34"/>and ſo returns to his retirement at <hi>Bruſſels:</hi> what the ſucceſſe of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> private and perſonall negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, we make no queſtion that time would have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered not a little to his advantage, had not his long drooping affaires received new life from an unexpected alteration of the ſcene.</p>
            <p>For as his enemies were buſy in their endeavours for the deſtruction of the Nation, ſo was Generall <hi>Monke</hi> the Governour of <hi>Scotland</hi> as ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udious how to ſave it. The peoples eyes were all fixed upon him, as their <hi>Moſes</hi> to deliver them from this iron yoke of Egyptian bondage. He having received intelligence of the Armies proceedings, weighing the miſeries attending ſuch Anarchicall confuſions, reſolves with himſelf by the divine aſſiſtance to put a period to theſe unhappy diſtractions, by ſetling the government on its right Baſis or Foundation. To this purpoſe having firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his diſſent from their proceedings, he ſecures divers ſtrong holds of that Nation, as alſo thoſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of his own that concurred not with him in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions.</p>
            <p>Having done this he ſends a letter to the Officers of the Army at <hi>London,</hi> importing ſomething of diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in himſelf, and ſome Officers of the Army in <hi>Scotland</hi> in reference to the things newly done in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lang.</hi> The Council of Officers having received this Alarum had a nocturnal conſultation, the reſult whereof was, that the regiments ſhould forthwith march North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and that <hi>Lambert</hi> ſhould goe to command them; but knowing too well the perſon with whom they had to deal, or whether it were that the ſouldiers would not fight one with another, <hi>Lambert</hi> and the reſt thought it their wiſeſt courſe to ſee whether they could undermine him, by the pretence of a treaty and a few fair p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalls.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40427:35"/>Hereupon <hi>Whaley,</hi> and <hi>Goffe,</hi> and <hi>Carill,</hi> and <hi>Backer,</hi> are ſent away to remonſtrate to <hi>Monck</hi> the State of Affaires in <hi>England,</hi> and thereupon to mediate with him under the fair pretence of avoiding the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of more blood. The Officers alſo wrote unto him and his Officers, to expoſtulate with him touching a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a brotherly Union. <hi>Morgan</hi> alſo takes a journey out of <hi>Yorkeſhire</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to ſee if he could bring the Generall to a Compoſure. But during theſe overtures, the thoughts of action were not at all laid aſide, wherefore <hi>Lambert</hi> follows his commanders, beginning his journey on the third of <hi>November,</hi> and quartering at <hi>Ware</hi> that night. Generall <hi>Monk</hi> alſo begins to look about him, He removes thoſe Officers which he had ſecured in <hi>Tintallon Caſtle</hi> unto the <hi>Croſs Hand,</hi> draws his forces together, ſecures <hi>Barwick,</hi> and ſends Major knight with a Party of 500. Horſe into <hi>England</hi> as far as <hi>Morpeth,</hi> as it is ſuppoſed to ſee what parties there were in that Country to joyn with them, which is the rather conjectured, becauſe they retreated ſo ſuddainly without making any further attempt, not was it ſafe for them to ſtay there, in regard that <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> more numerous forces were gathering together about <hi>New-caſtle.</hi> However to amuſe his adverſaries he ſends three Commiſſioners to <hi>London,</hi> viz. <hi>Col. Clobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Col. Weekes,</hi> and <hi>Major Knight,</hi> to treate with the ſame number of perſons on their ſide; They arrive, enter into a treaty, and too haſtily conclude upon theſe particulars following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the title of</hi> Charles Stuart <hi>be renounced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the three nations ſhall be governed by a free State and not by a ſingle perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That a learned and godly Ministry be maintained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Univerſities be reformed and countenanced.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:40427:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Officers and Souldiers be indempnified for what is paſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the armies retire and be dispos'd of into their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective quarters, moſt advantageouſly againſt the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> Whitlock, Vane, Ludlow, Saleway, Berry, <hi>be choſen for</hi> England, <hi>That</hi> Saint John, Wareſton, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington, Scot, <hi>and</hi> Thomſon, <hi>together with the Generalle three commanders be choſen for</hi> Scotland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> Steel, Barrow <hi>and</hi> Dobſon, <hi>be elected for</hi> Ireland, <hi>to give their aſſiſtance in determining the qualifications of ſuch perſons, as are to be members of ſucceeding Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That two field officers of the regiments in the three Nations, and ten on the behalf of the ſea officers ſhall meet on the ſixt of</hi> December <hi>as a generall councill, to adviſe touching the model of civil government that ſhould be then ready to be preſented to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were the chief heads of the agreement ſigned by the Commiſſioners on both ſides, &amp; ſent immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly away likewiſe unto <hi>Scotland</hi> for the Generalls con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. But Generall <hi>Monck</hi> inſtead of conſenting, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons a Convention to meet at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and ſends away a letter to the City, yet ſo contrived that both the character and the ſpeech ſeem'd ſuſpicious; which was delivered by Col. <hi>Markham,</hi> and Col. <hi>Askin,</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Long Parliament, not ſeeing the depth of the deſigne. To the Convention he propoſes three things,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That having received a call from God to march into</hi> England <hi>for reſetling the Parliament, they would during his abſence which would not be long, preſerve the peace of the Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That if any troubles ſhould ariſe they would aſſiſt him in the ſuppreſſing thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:40427:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That they would raiſe him ſome money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which the convention anſwer'd, that for the raiſing of money, they were ready to doe it.</p>
            <p>As to the other two demands, they reply'd that they were in no condition to perform his deſires, being that they wanted armes; However that they would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it. Preparations therefore for warre ſtill goe on, and the Horſe after ſome endeavours, wherein Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Generall <hi>Morgan</hi> was very active, were perſwaded to ſign the Engagement, which was offer'd to them by Generall <hi>Monck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some weeks had paſs'd when Generall <hi>Monck</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it now neceſſary to return ſome kind of anſwer to what his Commanders at <hi>London</hi> required from him, as to his conſent to thoſe articles which they had among themſelves agreed upon, wrote a letter to <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> bearing date from <hi>Edinburgh Novemb.</hi> 14. wherein he ſignified, that he was very glad to find his Lordſhip and the Officers of the Army of ſo complying a ſpirit, and ſo tender of the publick peace; but becauſe he was deſirous that the agreement ſhould be full and firme, and becauſe he did conceive that ſome things did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine untreated of and unagreed upon, that therefore 'twas the reſolution of himſelf and the reſt of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers there, to adde two more to thoſe that were already commiſſionated, to treate with the ſame number of ſuch as ſhould be appointed by his Lordſhip for the putting a finall end to this unhappy buſineſs; and that the place if his Lordſhip would permit ſhould be at <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> which being granted Generall <hi>Monck</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged the occaſion of delaying them ſo prudently, that while they were eager to entrap him, they never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the advantages which the other gain'd upon themſelves. While they are debating at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:40427:36"/>the Committee of Safety and the Council of Officers have many debates at home. They labour much to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the City, <hi>Whitlock</hi> to his praiſe be it ſpoken, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Fleetwood</hi> and <hi>Desborough</hi> being very induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to that purpoſe; but the Citizens having with much ſtrugling choſen an honeſt and reſolute Common-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, at length diſown'd them, and deſire, though it were a ſound moſt ungratefull to the men at <hi>Wallingford-houſe,</hi> that they may have a Free-parliament, which animoſity of theirs was much augmented by <hi>Huſons</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence and the murders which he committed, in the midſt of their City on the 5. of <hi>December.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing they ſo much endeavour'd was to bring forth the form of government, of which they had ſo long been in travel, and at length they conclude upon ſeven unalterable principles or fundamentalls as they name them, which were,</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, That no kingſhip ſhould be exerciſed in the nations.</item>
               <item>Second, That they will have no ſingle perſon to be chief Magiſtrate.</item>
               <item>Third, That an army be continued and maintained, and conducted ſo as to ſecure the peace of the Nations, and not be disbanded, nor the conduct altered but by conſent of the <hi>Conſervators.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fourth, That no impoſition be upon the Conſciences of them that fear God.</item>
               <item>Fifth, That there be no Houſe of Peers.</item>
               <item>Sixth, That the Legiſlative and Executive powers be diſtinct and not in the ſame hands.</item>
               <item>Seventh, That both the aſſemblies of the Parliament ſhall be elected by the people of this Common-wealth duly qualified.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But neither this piece of confuſion, nor <hi>Huſons</hi> regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40427:37"/>could appeaſe the City; ſo that by meer neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſtrained, the Council of Officers moſt graciouſly condeſcend to the calling of a Parliament, and the Committee of Safety order the iſſuing out of wri s ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, thinking to ſtop the breach which they had ſo over-haſtily made.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rump</hi> ſeeing theſe confuſions, were not idle for themſelves; They knew that of the two, Generall <hi>Monck</hi> enclin'd to their ſide then <hi>Lamberts,</hi> and that in <hi>Lamberts</hi> army they had alſo many friends, if they could but ſhew themſelves. The firſt Alarum which the Committee of Safety &amp; the Officers received was from <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> where <hi>Harſlerig, Walton,</hi> and <hi>Morley</hi> had made ſure of the Garriſon, and ſo dealt with Vicead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall <hi>Lawſon,</hi> who gave the ſecond Alarum, which rung like a knell in the then more amazed ears of theſe people; for he ſent them a declaration in his own and the name of ſeverall of the ſea-commanders, inſiſting upon ſeverall reaſons why they conceiv'd it neceſſary that the long Parliament ſhould ſit again. Hereupon <hi>Vane, Saloway,</hi> and <hi>Salmon,</hi> were ſent down to conferre with him, but <hi>Scot</hi> being there with two bolſters, one for each elbow; kept him ſo ſteady, that 'twas impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to hale him on one ſide. So that at length he poſitively declares for the Long-Parliament, the Souldiers alſo which were ſent to block up <hi>Portſmouth</hi> ſubmit to <hi>Harſlerig</hi> and <hi>Morley,</hi> declaring poſitively for the Rumps re-ſitting. <hi>Desboroughs</hi> regiment, which was by the Committee of Safety ſent for, to ſtrengthen their party, being come as far as Saint <hi>Albans,</hi> when they heard how things went, make a halt, and pauſe upon't. Hereupon <hi>Harſlerig</hi> with what forces he had marches for the City, and thoſe regiments which were about the town, being rendevouz'd by <hi>Okey</hi> and <hi>Alured,</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:40427:37"/>declare their reſolutions to live and dye with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; which being done, the Speaker <hi>Lenthall</hi> takes charge of the Tower, and delivers it to the Care of Col. <hi>Fitch.</hi> The Rump being now abſolute maſters of the field, give the conduct of the Army to <hi>Popham, Thomſon, Scot, Okey,</hi> Sir <hi>Ant. Aſhley Cooper, Alured,</hi> and <hi>Markhnm,</hi> and the cuſtody of the Tower to Sir <hi>Ant. Aſhley Cooper, Weever, Scot,</hi> and <hi>Barners.</hi> They alſo order <hi>Lamberts</hi> forces to repair to their quarters, and ſend Letters of thanks and acknowledgment to Generall <hi>Monck</hi> for his fidelity and good ſervice. <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> alſo ſubmits, and <hi>Lockhart</hi> courts them in a Letter from <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> but at length comes the welcome news of the ſubmiſſion of <hi>Lamberts</hi> forces, who ſeeing their Generall either ſo baffled or diſappointed, forſake him, and he thereupon ſends a letter of ſubmiſſion to the Parliament. Generall <hi>Monck</hi> alſo humbly congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulates the recovery of their power; Theſe fair gales blowing ſo briskly in their poop, they think they have the world in a ſtring, and therefore having ſpoke their friends fair, they begin to think of talking with their enemies. In order to which they ordaine an act for the publick ſale of Sir <hi>George Boothes</hi> Eſtate; They alſo diſcharge Sir <hi>Harry Vane</hi> from being a member of the Houſe, and order <hi>Lambert, Disborough, Aſhfield, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Kelſey, Packer, Cobbet,</hi> and <hi>Creed,</hi> to repair to their moſt remote habitations from <hi>London</hi> during their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; but finding them to ſtay in town, give order to the Council of State to ſecure them. Generall <hi>Monck</hi> they deſire to come as ſpeedily as he can to <hi>London,</hi> for elſe they ſaw he was reſolved to come without bidding, whereupon he advances into <hi>England,</hi> and at <hi>Morpeth</hi> the ſword-bearer of the City meets him, with a letter from the Lord Major and Common Council, whom
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40427:38"/>he ſpeedily return'd with an anſwer. The Parliament for all their complements being not well ſatisfy'd in the intentions of Generall <hi>Monck,</hi> ſend <hi>Scot</hi> and <hi>Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> under pretence of congratulating with him for the good ſucceſs God had given to his endeavours, to prie into his actions, and to make diſcovery of his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. And to curry favour with the Nation in generall, they put forth a Declaration, wherein they promiſe to this effect, firſt, they declare their reſolutions to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect what they had begun, <hi>for ſetling the government of theſe Nations, and the people thereof in the way of a Common-wealth and free State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all proceedings touching the Lives, Liberties, and Eſtates of the free people of this Common-wealth ſhould be according to the laws of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they would make effectual proviſion for counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing an honeſt godly miniſtry, and that impropriations and augmentations ſhould be continued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they would uphold all the Schooles and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities in the land, and continue their privileges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they would apply themſelves with all speed to ſuch Counſels and means as ſhould be found moſt proper for the ſpeedy increaſing of trade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly, as to the preſent burthens, that they were very ſenſible thereof, and that it was one of their greateſt cares to give the people eaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the people were now grown too wiſe to believe thoſe who had ſo oft before deluded them, &amp; now ſeeing them fall to their old tyrannies afreſh, under pretence of reſtoring them their long enthralled liberties, begin to rouſe up themſelves, and to ſhew their generall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred towards them. To Generall <hi>Monck</hi> therefore as a perſon whom they ſaw to be of a free and ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſpirit, they reſolve to make their applications,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40427:38"/>laying before him the infidelity, treachery, and tyranny of the Rump, beſeeching him to aſſert their libertie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and promiſing him to ſtick by him in the maintenance of their freedome. The <hi>Devonſhire</hi> men, as being his own Countrimen, began; the ſubſtance of whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe, and the Generalls anſwer we ſhall inſert, being indeed the full ſcope of what all demanded, and of the anſwer which all received. The ſubſtance of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe was this; <hi>That they found their Countrymen groaning under high oppreſſions, and a defect of trade: that though there was an alteration in the State affaires by the reaſſembling of the Long Parliament; yet that they found themſelves but in part redreſs'd, and that therefore the chief expedient would be to recall thoſe members that were ſecluded in</hi> 48. <hi>that they may fill up the vacant places, and not be oblig'd to oaths before their ſitting: for which things they ſhould defend him againſt all oppoſers with life and fortunes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this the Generall anſwers, <hi>That the government was monarchicall before the warre, that ſince there have been ſeverall intereſts, that theſe intereſts are interwoven by marriages and purchaſes, and all engag'd againſt the King as to Civils, and therefore that no government can be good that doth not rationally comprehend the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the ſaid interests. That Monarchy cannot be admitted becauſe its ſupport was taken away; and beſides that it is excluſive of all the Civil and Spirituall intereſts now in being: which premiſes being granted, to admit of the ſecluded members, as being monarchicall, and ſuch as would aboliſh the laws made ſince their ſecluſion, would engage the Nation in a new warre upon the account of ſelf-preſervation; that therefore he thought 'twas better to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the preſent Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such doubtfull anſwers as this, as they pleas'd the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40427:39"/>Rump, ſo they did not diſſatisfy the other party, but gave cauſe to both parties to think well of him.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Northampton</hi> he receiv'd another addreſs from the hands of Sir <hi>John Norrice,</hi> to whom he replies that he was but a ſervant of the Parliaments, with whom he ought not to interpoſe in matters of Higheſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment.</p>
            <p>On the 28. of <hi>January</hi> at Night the Generall arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at <hi>Saint Albanes,</hi> where he had ſeverall addreſſes made to him from <hi>Norfolke, Suffolke, Buckingham,</hi> and <hi>Leiceſter;</hi> being come thither he ſends to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to ſend their forces out of town, and quarter them according to the liſts which he had ſent them; which they readily order'd the Commanders of the army to ſee performed accordingly.</p>
            <p>Generall <hi>Monck</hi> being now not far from <hi>London,</hi> thoſe forces quartered in the City were ordered to march from thence, to make Room for his Excellencies Souldiers: but they having learned of their Maſters to be Rebellious, refuſed to goe; and having caſt off their Officers, a conſiderable party of them engarriſoned themſelves at <hi>Somerſet-houſe.</hi> That night alſo the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices drew themſelves into a party in the City, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending (no doubt) to have joyned with the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Red-coates, which had they done, they might have given a ſhrewd Alarum to the Rump; but before their joyning they were diſſipated by a part of the Army-horſe. The Mutiners upon a falſe Alarum were got out of the Town, and having their mouths ſtopt with a little pay, were commanded away, leaving the Town quiet, and in condition to entertain honeſter Gueſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>February</hi> 3. His Excellency marched in the head of his Army to his Quarters at <hi>White-hall;</hi> On the 6. of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40427:39"/>the ſame Month he was by <hi>Scot</hi> and <hi>Robinſon,</hi> Squires of the Rump, conducted to that <hi>Image of Authority,</hi> aſſembled in the Houſe where the Parliament uſually ſits; where he was by their pretended Speaker com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemented with a fawning ſpeech, candied over with Scripture-phraſes to make it the more plauſible. To which His Excellency returned a more pertinent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, informing them of the ſeverall applications, and numerous ſubſcriptions he received from moſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in his March from <hi>Scotland;</hi> the chiefeſt Heads of their deſires being for <hi>a free and full Parliament, a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell-Miniſtry, incouragement of Learning and Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, admittance of the Members ſecluded before</hi> 1648. <hi>and that they would determine their ſitting,</hi> &amp;c. But theſe were matters they loved not to hear of, much leſſe reſolved to practiſe; yet ſeeing the peoples ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs was ſuch, and that it was in a manner the agreement of the whole Nation, they at laſt moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly condeſcended to promiſe a full Repreſentative, but no ſecluded Members to be admitted, nor in effect any other then Phanatiques.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſupreme Trifle</hi> was now come to a forced put, monies muſt be raiſed to pay the Souldier, and the pride of the ſtubborn Citizens taken down that would not let the Rump to ride them, or <hi>the Good Old Cauſe</hi> would be totally ruined; in order to both, out comes a Tax of 100000 l.<hi>per menſem;</hi> this being debated in Common-council, they agreed in the Negative, which ſo incenſed the <hi>Back-ſide,</hi> that they adjudged the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front intollerable; and immediately poured out their indignation upon the City in theſe following Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:40427:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thurſday February</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>The Houſe received a report from the Council of State, of ſome Reſolutions taken by the Council, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That the Parliament doth approve of what the Council of State hath done in Ordering, that the Commiſſioners for Government of the Army, do appoint forces to be and continue in the City of <hi>London,</hi> for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the peace thereof, &amp; of the Common-wealth, &amp; for reducing of the City to the obedience of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That the Parliament doth approve of what the Council of State have done, in ordering that the Commiſſioners for the Army doe take order that the poſts and chaines in the City of <hi>London</hi> be taken away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That the Gates of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Portcullices there be forthwith deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That the Parliament doth approve of what the Council of State, and Commiſſioners of the Army have done, in ſeizing and apprehending of Mr. <hi>Vincent,</hi> Merchant in <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Brown,</hi> Grocer in <hi>Wood-ſtreet, Daniel Spencer</hi> in <hi>Friday-ſtreet, Laurence Brompfield</hi> in <hi>Tower-ſtreet,</hi> Major <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bludworth,</hi> and <hi>Richard Ford,</hi> in <hi>Seething<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane,</hi> Major <hi>Cox</hi> at the <hi>Swan</hi> in <hi>Dowgate,</hi> Mr <hi>Penning</hi> in <hi>Fanchurch-ſtreet,</hi> and Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Jackſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſolved,</hi> That the preſent Common-council of the City of <hi>London,</hi> Elected for this year, be diſcontinued, and be and are hereby declared to be Null and Void, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the Lord Mayor of <hi>London</hi> have notice hereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ordered,</hi> That it be referred to a Committee to bring in a Bill for the Choice of another Common-council, with ſuch Qualifications as the Parliament ſhall think fit, with order to meet at eight of the Clock in the Speakers Chamber to morrow morning.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:40427:40"/>
            <p>Theſe Reſolves they ſend to the Generall to put in execution, intending with this ſtone to kill two Birds, not onely to bring the Citizens in ſubjection, and to make them pay in their money, but alſo to create a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred betwixt them and the Generall by this odious em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, of whoſe uniting they had more then an ordinary jealouſy. However his Excellency in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Commands, marches into the City with his whole Army, ſeiſes on divers of their Common-council, and ſends them to the Tower, digs up their Poſts, and breaks down their Gates, and all done with ſuch a ſeeming compliance to the Rump, that the ſtupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Citizens having now fear added to their ſlavery, durſt hardly murmur, but with ſighs and nods bid adieu to their liberty.</p>
            <p>Whileſt His Excellency was thus buſied in the City, the Rump were as buſy as Bees at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> for not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the General had ſo lately preſerved them, yet they moſt ungratefully ſought his ruine;</p>
            <p>Firſt they enter into a ſecret combination with the Sectaries, who upon their inſtigation preſent unto them <hi>à repreſentation and addreſſe,</hi> wherein was ſo little of divinity, that there was hardly any morality; however with much formality it was brought them by <hi>Barebone</hi> and others of the ſame gang: but this inſtead of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good did hurt, for the people now plainly deſcrying the ruinous tenents of theſe people, were rather the more reſolved againſt them, then terrified to ſee the Rump mounting up a faction againſt them.</p>
            <p>And then alſo ſeeking to caſt <hi>Monck</hi> to who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo lately they were ſo ocurteous, out of power, they paſſed a Bill for the Army to be governed by five Commiſſioners, viz. Generall <hi>George Monck,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> Col. <hi>Herbert Morley,</hi> Colonel <hi>Valentine</hi> and <hi>Walton,</hi> Colonel
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40427:41"/>
               <hi>Mathew Allured,</hi> and that the <hi>Quorum</hi> of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners be three. Had they brought this to paſſe, they might have had hopes to have held the peoples noſes ſtill to the Grindſtone; But His Excellency abhorring their perfidiouſneſs, and ſeeing their deſigne was to fix themſelves in a perpetual Counſell, all their qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with which they kept ſuch a ſtirre, tending onely to bring in ſuch as had been <hi>the Kings Tryers, Exciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Sequeſtrators, Cloſe-Committee-men, Major Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, Buyers and Sellers of the Church and Crown Lands,</hi> &amp;c. in brief, ſuch as lived upon the ruines of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and feared they ſhould goe naked, ſhould every Bird claim again his feather; ſo that the peoples Repreſentatives muſt repreſent them in all their tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, elſe they were not to be admitted States-men.</p>
            <p>Hereupon Generall <hi>Monck</hi> having on <hi>Friday Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> 11. perform'd the Votes of the Houſe for brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king down the Gates, and pulling up the Poſts, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come back to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> upon adviſe with his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, thought it fit to return again to the City on <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday</hi> Morning with his whole force; but before he went, ſends a letter to the Parliament ſigned by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his Officers, wherein he ſignified his deſires to the Parliament for the ſpeedy filling up the Houſe, and for putting a period to their ſitting. In the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon he drew up his forces in <hi>Finsbury,</hi> and repairing after dinner to <hi>Guildhall,</hi> he had a conference with the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, which being ended, the concluſion thereof was ſuch as caus'd all the Bells in the City to ring, and all the ſtreets to blaze with Bonfires: Such a ſudden change, Hiſtory cannot tell us of its parallel; wiſe men grew mad upon it, and mad men ſober; The Cryes, the Bonfires, and the ſume of Roſted Rumps did quite take down the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40427:41"/>Legiſlative Stomach; Both men, women, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Old and Young, Rich and Poor, all ſung forth the deſtruction of the Long called Parliament; the whole City was as it were on fire with Bonfires for joy; And now thoſe who formerly threatned the fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the City, were burnt at every door, for all the people cryed out, <hi>let us burn the Rump, let us roſt the Rump;</hi> yea ſuch an <hi>odium</hi> had they contracted to themſelves, that they roſted Carrion before the door of the Houſe where they uſually ſat, no leſſe then thirty eight Bonfires were made between <hi>Fleet-conduit</hi> and <hi>Temple-barre:</hi> To be ſhort, there was ſcarce ſo much as one Alley in the whole City wherein there were not many Bonfires. Next day being <hi>Sunday,</hi> all the Churches ecchoed forth praiſes and thanks to God, private devotion not being wanting: nor was this joy confined onely within the Walls of the City, but ſince a publique miſcheif was removed, a publique rejoycing over-ſpread the whole Kingdome, and all the people with one accord, ſhouted, clapped hands, and poured out joyfull thanks for this great deliverance. So the wearied Hare is delighted, and cheareth her ſelf, when ſhe hath ſhook off the Bloody Hounds, and ſo a Flock of Sheep are at reſt and eaſe, when the Ravenous Wolves have newly left them.</p>
            <p>Yet was not all this enough to put the Rump out of Countenance, they met again as formally as ever, and acted with a Confidence that might excuſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-peoples Jealouſy over the Generall. Their grand deſign now was to fruſtrate the hopes of a Free-Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no ſtone was left unturned in order hereunto; The Bolder and more ingenuous ſort of honeſt men were gathered up by flying Troops that they had every where diſperſed to hinder a Conjunction, threatning
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40427:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>Baniſhment and ſequeſtration to the whole party of declarers. Nor did they want their ſpecious pretences to inſinuate with the vulgar, <hi>The Houſe ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately fill'd, the form of the Writ was already pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, the Qualifications agreed upon, and</hi> in fine <hi>they would inſtantly proceed to a ſettlement of Church and State,</hi> and was not this enough? what would they have more? The Common-wealth-men they were a Birding too, telling their pretty tales of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Venice, O the Gallantry of thoſe ancient Romans that baniſhed</hi> Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin <hi>out of</hi> Rome! In the mean time the Preſſes are at work, by Libells againſt the King, wherein he was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently abus'd, particularly by a feigned letter from <hi>Bruſſels</hi> by Arguments of intereſt, and by falſe intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to corrupt and deceive the people. Yet would not all doe, the Country were too ſenſible of the groſſe Abuſes and Cheates they had put upon the Nation.</p>
            <p>The Generall willing they ſhould be overcome as well by Argument as Force, eaſily yields to a propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that both ſides might meet and ſpeak what they could for themſelves. The Rump choſe for themſelves St. <hi>John, Haſlerig,</hi> Col. <hi>Morley,</hi> Col. <hi>Thomſon,</hi> Sir <hi>Ant. Aſh. Cooper,</hi> Mr. <hi>Weever,</hi> Col. <hi>White,</hi> Col. <hi>Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Raleigh,</hi> Col. <hi>Fielder,</hi> on the part of the ſecluded members came, Col. <hi>Popham,</hi> Sir <hi>Will. Lewis,</hi> Sir <hi>John Holland,</hi> Sir <hi>Gil. Gerrard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Knightley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Anneſtey,</hi> Mr. <hi>Crew,</hi> Mr. <hi>Trevor,</hi> Col. <hi>Harley,</hi> Col. <hi>Norton,</hi> Sir <hi>John Temple,</hi> Col. <hi>Brich.</hi> Theſe met at Alderman <hi>Wales</hi> Houſe, then the Generalls quarters, where they had a long conference together before him; but when the Generall came to weigh the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on both ſides, he found thoſe of the Rump much too light for the other partes. The Generall being now ſatisfied in the Juſtice of the Secluded mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40427:42"/>cauſe, quits his head-quarters in the City, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to <hi>White-hall, February</hi> 21. where met him in his Lodging moſt of the ſecluded Members in town, to whom he ſpake to this purpoſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gentlemen,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You are not I hope ignorant what care and endeavours have been us'd and means aſſayd for healing the breaches of our diviſions among our ſelves, and that in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto diverſe conferences have been procured between you, yet having a fuller ſatisfaction from thoſe Gentlemen that were ſecluded then formerly, I was bold to put you all to the trouble of this meeting, that I might open my ſelf to ye all with more freedome then formerly. But leſt I might be miſapprehended or miſtaken, as of late it befell me, I have committed to writing the heads of what I intended to diſcourſe to ye, and deſire it may be openly read.</p>
            </q>
            <p>After which a Paper was read to the Members by the Generalls Secretary to this effect:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That by what he had heard the ſettlement of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion lay in their hands, and that he was aſſured they would become makers up of its wofull breaches, in purſuit where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he would think nothing too dear. That he would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe nothing on them, but took leave to mind them, that the old foundations were ſo broken, that in the eye of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they could not be reſtor'd but upon the ruine of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. That the intereſt of</hi> London <hi>lay in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the only Government capable of making her the bank for the trade of Chriſtendome, that he thought a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate not rigid Presbyterian government, moſt acceptable to the Churches ſettlement; therefore he exhorted them to ſettle the conduct of the Army, and maintenance for the forces by ſea and land, to ſummon a New Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40427:43"/>and make a legal diſſolution of this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This read, the Members took leave, and repaired to the Houſe, which they found open for them with all freedome, above four ſcore appearing at the firſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; They were no ſooner entred but fell inſtantly upon the Nulling of thoſe ſpurious orders which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to their firſt ſecluſion in <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1648. proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thence, to the Enlarging and Confirming of the Generalls Commiſſion: and the diſabling of the Rumps Commiſſioners for the Government of the Army, the diſcharging of priſoners illegally commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the appointment of a new Convention <hi>April</hi> 25. 1660. The Militia's they placed in good hands, and empowred a Council of State to govern in the next intervall; which being done, and proviſion made for a new Election, <hi>March</hi> the 16. they diſſolved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Thus by the great bleſſing of God was the deſign of the Rump happily prevented, who intended to have held the people at gaze in expectation of a further ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, till divers Troopes (which they had ordered to that purpoſe) ſhould have ſeiſed all the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſons of the Kingdome; Nay, they were ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent as to tempt the Generall himſelf into a compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with them, but his Noble ſoul was too Generous to be wrought upon, to proſtitute his Honour, his Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and all, to preſerve a violent and reſtleſs faction. Nor were they wanting in other ſhameleſs villanies, <hi>falſifying the Liſts of the Militia, ſolliciting Petitions from the City for their Continuance, jugling the Army-Officers into a Tumult, Employing their inſtruments to deſtroy the Generall, Mutinying the Army and the City, and finally engaging a great part of the Souldiery to remonſtrate againſt the reſt of the Nation,</hi> ſo deſirous
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40427:43"/>they were to have perpetuated their tyranny, though all their endeavours proved too little to prevent their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding the fruitleſſeneſs of their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, their reſtleſs ſpirits were never quiet, having their Agitators very buſy in the Army, though the Council of State put forth a Proclamation againſt them; theſe curſed fire-brands, more fatall to <hi>England</hi> then <hi>Paris</hi> was to <hi>Ilium,</hi> having with their <hi>Machiavilian</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine poyſoned a conſiderable party of the Souldiers, to Head their faction, <hi>Lambert</hi> (by what means I know not,) makes an eſcape out of the Tower, to which place not long before he had been committed, for refuſing to ſign an Engagement of living peaceably; hereupon the Generall placed four companies of his own Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Tower, and the Council of State iſſued forth a Proclamation againſt him and his complices, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring all perſons whatſoever to be aſſiſtant to the ſuppreſſion of them, and that whoſoever ſhould bring him in ſhould for his reward receive a hundred pounds; the Citizens repaired their Poſts and Chaines, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their Guards, and (in ſhort) the whole Nation was as vigilant as poſſible to diſappoint the grand Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy of the Phanaticks.</p>
            <p>At laſt the Hue and Cry overtook the Thief; <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> is heard of with a party near <hi>Daventry,</hi> conſiſting of four Troops of Horſe, viz. Colonel <hi>Alureds,</hi> and Major <hi>Nelthrops,</hi> (which two Gentlemen were then in <hi>London,</hi> and not in the leaſt acquainted with their Troops defection,) Captain <hi>Haſlerigs,</hi> and Cap. <hi>Clares,</hi> beſides ſeverall Anabaptiſts, Quakers, and other Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Colonel <hi>Ingoldsby</hi> having notice where he was, reſolves to give him a viſit; in his way his forlorn hope meeting with Captain <hi>Haſlerig</hi> took him priſoner, but
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40427:44"/>upon giving his parol, and a promiſe to ſend his Troop to them, he was diſmiſſed; which according to his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement not long after came in, led by the Cornet and Quartermaſter.</p>
            <p>The Enemy ſeeing himſelf too weak in Armes, ſeeks to gain by Art, and deſires a parley, thinking thereby to increaſe their party; which they (being armed againſt the temptations of the Fiend) are not unwilling to admit of, the main buſineſs they drove at, was under pretence of ſecurity to all intereſts, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade a re-admiſſion of the Lord <hi>Richard</hi> to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectorſhip; which was well anſwered by a ſtout Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, telling them their onely end in that was to ſet up one again whom they themſelves had already learn'd to pull down; that they were under command, and knew it their duty not to diſpute; but to ſubmit to what or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders they received from their ſuperiours, which they likewiſe wiſhed them to doe. The diſpute being end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they prepare for action, but Col. <hi>Alureds</hi> Troop deſerting them, <hi>Lambert</hi> ſeeing himſelf forſaken, ſeeks to fly: but providence had ſo ordered it, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he was mounted on a Barbery, which might have haſtned him in his flight, yet being on ploughed land his Horſe was of little advantage to him; And now he who before had gained the name of ſtout and valiant in many battles, when he ſaw Col. <hi>Ingoldsby</hi> ride up to him and demand him priſoner, was preſently taken without drawing his ſword, and driven to that pittyfull ſhift to cry out, <hi>Pray my Lord let me Eſcape, Pray my Lord let me Eſcape.</hi> There were taken with him Colonel <hi>Cobbet,</hi> Major <hi>Creed,</hi> Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Young,</hi> Captain <hi>Timothy Clare,</hi> Captain <hi>Gregory,</hi> and Captain <hi>Spinage,</hi> and ſome other private ſouldiers, Colonel <hi>Okey,</hi> Colonel <hi>Axtel,</hi> and Captain <hi>Cleer,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40427:44"/>Okeys</hi> ſon in law eſcaped, though purſued four miles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> the 24. (the day before the Parliament ſitting) they were brought up priſoners to the Council, who after examination, committed <hi>Lambert, Cobbet,</hi> and <hi>Creed,</hi> cloſe priſoners to the Tower. The ſame day the Militia forces of the City Trained Bands and Auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, according to an Order of the Council, marched into <hi>Hide Park,</hi> the Mayor in his Coller of S's, with the Mace, Sword, and Cap of Maintenance, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen in Scarlet, and the Commiſſioners of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia in handſome equipage going before them to a place erected for their entertainment. Each Col. had his Tent, and their Regiments very full, ſeverall of the Nobility and Gentry of great quality going as Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers; in Alderman <hi>Robinſons</hi> Regiment were 250. in the reſt very many; The Regiments were all ſo gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantly accountered, as did ſufficiently ſpeak both the riches and ſtrength of the City, there being little viſible difference betwixt the Trained Bands and Auxiliaries, but onely in their age. This certainly was an happy Omen of our future ſettlement, that the day before the ſitting of the Parliament, there ſhould not onely appear ſo gallant a Body of able Citizens to defend them, but the Chief of that faction that endeavoured the diſturbance of the Nation ſhould be delivered into their hands, and the reſt of his Accomplices timely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and diſperſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 25. both Houſes of Parliament met at Saint <hi>Margarets Church</hi> in <hi>Westminſter,</hi> where Doctor <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> preached before them, taking his Text out of <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. The Sermon ended they repaired to their Houſes; The Lords made choice of the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> for their Speaker, the Houſe of Commons of Sir <hi>Harbotle Grimſtone.</hi> This was a great joy to the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40427:45"/>whole Nation, to ſee our Grand Council reſtored again to their former priveledges, a large ſtep to our ancient freedome; yet not comparable to what the firſt of <hi>May</hi> produced, when both Houſes of Parliament and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Monck</hi> received each of them a Letter from his moſt Sacred Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, with a gracious Declaration to all his Loving Subjects, brought by Sir <hi>John Greenvil,</hi> ſince made Earl of <hi>Bath.</hi> His Letters ſpeake his piety, and unwearied care for his Subjects proſperity; deſiring rather to prepare and improve the affections of his Subjects at home for his reſtauration, then to procure aſſiſtance from abroad (though then propounded to him) to invade either of his kingdomes. Our intended brevity will not permit us to give you the exact draught of his Letters, though deſerving to be Regiſtred in Letters of Gold; take a view of his gracious expreſſions of piety, goodneſs, and love to the Nation, in this his following Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="declaration">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHARLES</hi> R.</head>
                  <p>CHARLES by the Grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. To all our Loving Subjects, of what degree or quality ſoever, greeting. If the generall diſtraction and confuſion which is ſpread over the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome doth not awaken all men to a deſire and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thoſe wounds which have ſo many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther been kept bleeding may be bound up, all we can ſay will be to no purpoſe: However after this long ſilence, We have thought it Our duty to declare how much We deſire to contribute thereunto; And that as We can never give over the hope in good time to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the poſſeſſion of that Right which God and Nature
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40427:45"/>hath made our due: ſo we doe make it our daily ſuit to the Divine Providence, that he will in compaſſion to Us, and Our Subjects, after ſo long miſery and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering remit and put Us into a quiet and peaceable poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of that Our right, with as little blood and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to Our people as is poſſible: Nor doe we deſire more to enjoy what is Ours, then that all Our Subjects may enjoy what by Law is theirs, by a full and entire Adminiſtration of Juſtice throughout the Land, and by extending Our mercy where it is wanted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
                  <p>And to the end that the fear of puniſhment may not engage any Conſcious to themſelves of what is paſſed, to a perſeverance in guilt for the future, by oppoſing the quiet and happineſſe of their Country in the reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration both of King, Peers and People, to their Juſt, Ancient, and Fundamentall Rights: We do by theſe preſents declare, That We doe grant a free and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall pardon, which We are ready upon demand to paſſe under Our Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> to all Our Subjects of what degree or quality ſoever, who within fourty days after the publiſhing hereof ſhall lay hold upon this Our grace and favour, and ſhall by any publick Act declare their doing ſo; And that they return to the Loyalty and Obedience of good Subjects, (excepting onely ſuch perſons as ſhall hereafter be excepted by Parliament.) Thoſe only excepted, let all Our Loving Subjects, how faulty ſoever, relie upon the word of a King, ſolemnly given by this preſent Declaration, That no Crime whatſoever committed againſt Us, or Our Royall Father before the Publication of this, ſhall ever riſe in Judgment, or be brought in Queſtion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of them, to the leaſt endamagement of them, either in their Lives, Liberties, or Eſtates, or
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40427:46"/>(as far forth as lies in Our power) ſo much as to the prejudice of their Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>utations, by any Reproach or term of diſtinction from the reſt of Our beſt Subjects. We Deſiring and Ordaining that hence forward all Notes of Diſcord, ſeparation and difference of parties be utterly aboliſhed among all Our Subjects; whom We invite and conjure to a perfect Union among themſelves under Our Protection, for the Re-ſettlement of Our Juſt Rights and theirs, in a free Parliament; By which, upon the word of a King We will be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe the paſſion and uncharitableneſs of the times have produced ſeverall opinions in Religion, by which men are engaged in parties and animoſities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt each other, which when they ſhall hereafter unite in a freedome of Converſation, will be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſed, or better underſtood: We doe Declare a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to tender Conſciences; and that no man ſhall be diſquieted or called in queſtion for differences of opinion in matter of Religion, which do not diſturbe the Peace of the Kingdome: And that We ſhall be ready to conſent to ſuch an Act of Parliament, as upon Mature Deliberation ſhall be offered to Us for the full granting that Indulgence.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe in the continued diſtractions of ſo many years, and ſo many and great Revolutions, many Grants and Purchaſes of Eſtates have been made to, and by, many Officers, Souldiers and others who are now poſſeſſed of the ſame, and who may be liable to Actions at Law u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on ſeverall Titles: We are likewiſe willing, that all ſuch differences, and all things relating to ſuch Grants, Sales, and Purchaſes, ſhall be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Parliament; which can beſt provide for the juſt ſatisfaction of all men who are concerned.</p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:40427:46"/>
                  <p>And We do further declare, that We will be ready to conſent to any Act or Acts of Parliament to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes aforeſaid, and for the full ſatisfaction of all Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears due to the Officers and Souldiers of the Army un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of Generall <hi>Monck;</hi> and that they ſhall be received into Our ſervice upon as good Pay and Condions as they now injoy.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given under Our ſign Manual, and privy Sgnet, At Our Court at</hi> Breda, <date>
                           <hi>this</hi> 4/14 <hi>day of</hi> April 1660. <hi>In the twelfth year of Our Reign.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Never was Letter from abſent Lover received with more unfeigned affection then theſe, never was meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage entertain'd with a more generall conſent, nor did the Houſe ever more truely appear the peoples full Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives then at this preſent. The Letters being read with that accuſtomed Ceremony and Reverence due to Majeſty, produced theſe Reſolves, <hi>Nemine contradicente.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reſolved by the Houſe of Lords, That they doe own and declare, that according to the Ancient and Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Laws of this Kingdome; the Government is and ought to be by King, Lords and Commons.</p>
            <p>Reſolved, that a Committee of eight Lords, do joyn with a Committee of the Houſe of Commons, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of an anſwer to His Majeſties Gracious Letter and Declaration.</p>
            <p>Reſolved by the Houſe of Commons, That a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee be appointed to prepare an anſwer to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Letter, expreſſing the great and joyfull ſence of this Houſe of His gracious offers, and their Humble and Hearty Thanks to His Majeſty for the ſame; and with profeſſions of their Loyalty and Duty to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40427:47"/>and that this Houſe will give a ſpeedy anſwer to His Majeſties gracious Propoſalls.</p>
            <p>Reſolved, that the ſumme of 50000 l. be preſented to His Majeſty from this Houſe.</p>
            <p>Ordered, that the Letter from His Majeſty to the Houſe and His Declcration, be entred at large in the Journall Book, as alſo that to the Generall, to be kept amongſt the Records of this Houſe for His Honour.</p>
            <p>This compliance of the Parliament with His Sacred Majeſty, ſurcharged the Citizens hearts with joy, thoſe beams of Majeſty which enliven Trading, having been long abſent from the City, the preſence of the Prince being one principall cauſe of a Cities greatneſs: The Bells and Bonfires made outward expreſſion of thoſe indelible Characters of Loyalty written in their hearts; the great guns from the Tower thundred forth <hi>Vive le Roys,</hi> whilſt each County in <hi>England</hi> ſtrived to out-vie one another in expreſſions of Loyalty.</p>
            <p>The Souldiery who had hitherto made Clubs trump, reſolve now to enthrone the King of Hearts in their affection, expreſſing their Loyalty to <hi>His Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,</hi> in this following addreſſe preſented to his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency the Lord Generall <hi>Monck.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="address">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Although we cannot doubt of your Excellencies confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in our affections, and our faithfulneſs to your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and that diſcipline which by your good and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent conduct hath been exerciſed over us, whereby we are inſtructed to an entire obedience to your Excellency, and that Authority which the Lord ſhall place over us, which we hope we have manifeſted in our laſt actings under your Excellency againſt all perſons whatſoever, in any ways diſturbing the peace and ſettlement of the Nation, although ſome of thom have been our Brethren, former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40427:47"/>engaged in the ſame cauſe with us, as alſo in our laſt Remonstrance and addreſſe to your Excellency, wherein as it becomes us in daty, we have ſolemnly declar'd to acquieſce in what the Lord ſhall bring forth from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations of this preſent</hi> Parliament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yet in regard your Excellency hath been pleaſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate a Letter and a Leclaration from the</hi> Kings Majeſty, <hi>full of Gracious expreſſions, we cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the matter of it gives a great meaſure of quiet to our minds, and more then ordinary expectations of the enjoyment of much tranquility and happineſs under</hi> His Majeſties <hi>government.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The free and generall Indemnity offered by</hi> His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, <hi>with a liberty to tender Conſciences, ſatisfaction of Arrears, and his readineſs to conſent to a confirmation of Sales, and other Grants and Purchaſes of Eſtates, to all perſons now in poſſeſſion of the ſame, is that of which as we cannot doubt of the reall performance, being left by</hi> His Majeſty <hi>to the</hi> Parliaments <hi>determination, ſo we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believe it is the moſt probable way to bring the Nations to their deſired ſettlement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And we hope to evince to</hi> His Majeſty, <hi>and all the world, that we and all thoſe that have been engaged in the</hi> Parliaments <hi>cauſe, are</hi> His Majeſties <hi>beſt and moſt reall Subjects; and that your Excellency and the Armies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Command, have comply'd with the obligations for which they were firſt raiſed; for the preſervation of the true</hi> Proteſtant Religion, <hi>the Honour and Dignity of the</hi> King, <hi>the priviledges of</hi> Parliament, <hi>the liberty and property of the</hi> Subject, <hi>and the fundamentall Laws of the</hi> Land.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Greenvile</hi> who brought <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters had the thanks of both Houſes given him for the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40427:48"/>ſame, and 500 l. given him as a teſtimony of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to him; the Speaker of the Houſe of Commons delivering himſelf in theſe pathericall expreſſions.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="commendation">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir <hi>John Greenvile,</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I need not tell you with what gratefull and thankfull hearts the Commons now aſſembled in Parliament have received <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Gracious Letter, <hi>Res ipſa loquitur:</hi> you your ſelf have been <hi>Auricularis &amp; ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laris testis de rei verita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e,</hi> Our Bells and our Bonfires have already begun the Proclamation of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> goodneſſe, and of our joys. We have told the people, that our King, the glory of <hi>England,</hi> is coming home again, and they have reſounded it back again in our ears, that they are ready, and their hearts are open to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him; both Parliament and people have cryed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oud in their prayers to the King of Kings, <hi>Long live King</hi> CHARLES <hi>the ſecond.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am likewiſe to tell you, that the Houſe doth not think fit that you ſhould return to our Royall Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, without ſome Teſtimony of their reſpects to your ſelf; They have therefore ordered and appointed that 500 l. ſhall be delivered unto you, to buy a Jewell, as a Badge of that Honour which is due to a perſon whom the King hath Honoured to be the meſſenger of ſo Gracious a Meſſage: and I am commanded in the name of the Houſe to return you their very hearty thanks.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And as at land, ſuch was the affections of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; where Generall <hi>Mountague</hi> having received two Letters, the one from <hi>His Ma eſty,</hi> the other from the moſt Illuſtrious Duke of <hi>Yorke;</hi> as alſo thoſe others ſent to the Houſe of Commons and his Excellency, together with <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Gracious Declaration; he
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40427:48"/>immediately cauſed a great gun to be ſhot off, the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſummons to call his Officers together; who coming aboard, he communicated <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Letters unto them, which being read, with anunamimous conſent they declared themſelves for <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> profeſſing their exact Loyalty, to live and die in his defence: de<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ring the Generalls of the Fleet humbly to preſent the lame to <hi>His Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But no ſooner did the under Sea-men hear thereof, but their over-joy'd hearts burſt forth into loud accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of joy; this news was more welcome to them, then had they taken the wealth of the <hi>Weſt Indies</hi> for prize: And now to expreſſe their Loyalty, the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall himſelf fired a great Gun, crying <hi>God bleſſe His Majeſty.</hi> Then might you ſee the Fleet in her pride, with Pendants looſe, Guns roaring, Caps flying, and loud <hi>Vive le Roys</hi> ecchoed from one ſhips Company to another, which were anſwered with the great Guns from <hi>Deal</hi> and <hi>Sandwich</hi> Caſtles. The Noble Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gave two pipes of Canary to the Commanders and Gentlemen in his ſhip.</p>
            <p>And as at ſea, ſo in <hi>Ireland</hi> was ſeen the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance; for the Convention there, hearing what was done in <hi>England,</hi> ſend a Declaration hither, wherein they firſt expreſſe their diſclaime of the <hi>ſinfull and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary force put upon the Houſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 1648. and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as alſo the ſaid perſons did preſume to erect a high Court of Juſtice, and by an ugly and execrable ſentence condemn the King to death; they do declare their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the fact, and proteſt againſt thoſe inhuman, unparallell'd, and barba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous actions, as being the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and higheſt aſſaſſination that ever prot hane or ſacred Hiſtory ever recorded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the 8. 1660. <hi>His Majeſty</hi> was ſolemnly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40427:49"/>by the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds and Commons, the Lord Mayor, &amp;c. in the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with an univerſall teſtification of Loyalty from all degrees of people; The manner whereof being ſo remarkable, (each <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſon in his proper Sphear contending to out-vy each other in expreſſions of obedience to <hi>His Sacred Majeſty</hi>) take as followeth.</p>
            <p>Between one and two of the Clock, the Lords met in the Painted Chamber, where they continued till they were placed in order, the Earl of <hi>Manchester</hi> Speaker firſt, then the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Oxford,</hi> &amp;c. Thus they walked all along with the Heralds before them, through the Court of <hi>Requeſts,</hi> and <hi>Weſtminster-Hall,</hi> to the Pallace, where they ſtaid befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the Hall gate, whither alſo preſently after came the Houſe of Commons: Being placed in order, both Lords and Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mons ſtood bare, whileſt Mr. <hi>Biſh</hi> dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Mr. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ley</hi> king at Armes, with a loud voice Proclaimed <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="proclamation">
               <body>
                  <head>The Proclamation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Although it can no may be doubted, but that</hi> His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties <hi>Right and Title to His Crown and King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omes, is and was e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ery way compleated by the death of his moſt Royall father of glorious memory, without the Ceremony or ſolemnity of a</hi> Proclamation: <hi>yet ſince Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in ſuch caſes have been always uſed, to the end that all good ſubjects might upon this occaſion testify their duty and reſpect; And ſince the armed violence, and other the Calamities of many years laſt paſt, have hitherto depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us of any ſuch opportunity, whereby we might expreſs our Loyalty and allegiance to</hi> His Majeſty. <hi>We therefore the</hi> Lords <hi>and</hi> Commons <hi>now aſſembled in</hi> Parliament, <hi>together with the</hi> Lord Mayor, Aldermen, <hi>and</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40427:49"/>
                     <hi>of the City of</hi> London, <hi>and other freemen of this kingdome now preſent, do according to our Duty and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, heartily, joyfully, and unaminouſly, acknowledge and proclaime, That immediately upon the deceaſe of our late Soveraign Lord King</hi> Charles, <hi>the Imperial Crown of the Realme of</hi> England, <hi>and of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Dominions, and Rights belonging to the ſame, did by inherent Birth right, and lawfull undoubted ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, deſcend and come to His moſt Excellent</hi> Majeſty Charles <hi>the ſecond; as being lineally, juſtly, and lawfully, next Heir of the</hi> Bloud Royal <hi>of this Realme; and that by the goodneſs and providence of Almighty God, He is of</hi> England, Scotland, France, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>the moſt potent, mighty, and undoubted</hi> King: <hi>And thereunto we most Humbly and Faithfully do ſubmit and obliege our ſelves, our Heires and Poſterity for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>God ſave the King.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Proclamation being ended, the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons took their Coaches, proceeding to the further ſolemnity of proclaiming <hi>His Sacred Majeſty</hi> as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. Firſt the Head Bayliffe of <hi>Westminſter,</hi> and his Servants riding with White ſtaves to prepare the way, then followed a gallant Troop of Officers of the Army and other Gentlemen with Trumpets before them, then the Life-guard very ſtately mounted, and richly clothed, after them a Claſs of ſix Trumpets and three Heralds, then a Herald between the Serjeant to the Commons and the Mace of the Council, next Mr. <hi>Ryley</hi> king at Armes, in his rich coat of the Kings Armes, between Serjeant <hi>Norfolk</hi> and Serjeant <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> after whom came the Uſher of the Black Rod and Mr. <hi>Biſh</hi> together. Theſe uſhering the way, in the next place came the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> Speaker to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40427:50"/>the Houſe of Lords in his Coach and ſix Horſes, then the Speaker of the Houſe of Commons in his, then his Excellency the Lord Generall in his, after which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed both Houſes of Lords and Commons in their Coaches, and laſt of all a Troop of Horſe. In this manner they came to <hi>White-hall,</hi> where they Proclaim'd <hi>His Majeſty</hi> a ſecond time, and then in like order proceeded: Being come to <hi>Arundell-Houſe,</hi> they made a ſtand, where Mr. <hi>Ryley</hi> king at Armes taking one of the Heralds and ſix Trumpets with him, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced forward toward <hi>Temple-Bar;</hi> which (according t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> agreement) being ſhut, he came to the gate, knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd demanded entrance; being asked who it was that knocked, he replyed, that if my Lord Mayor would come to the gate he would deliver his Meſſage to him, who accordingly coming, the Trumpets ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, after which ſilence being made, it was demanded of the king of Armes, <hi>Who he was, and what was his meſſage;</hi> to which he anſwered, <hi>We are the Heralds at Armes, Appointed and Commanded by the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, to demand entrance into the famous City of</hi> London, <hi>to proclaime</hi> Charles <hi>the ſecond, King of</hi> England, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and we expect your speedy anſwer to this demand;</hi> to this they anſwered, <hi>Sir, if it pleaſe you to have a little pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience we ſhall speedily give you an anſwer to your meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</hi> After ſome little conference between the Lord Mayor and Aldermen, the Gates were opened, and the king at Armes entred, with Trumpets ſounding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and was joyfully received by the Lord Mayor in his Crimſon Velvet Gown and Hood, the Aldermen and Sheriffs in Scarlet, and the Officers of the Militia gallantly accoutred on Horſe-back.</p>
            <p>Both ſides of the ſtreets were guarded by the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40427:50"/>forces of <hi>London</hi> from <hi>Temple-Bar</hi> to the <hi>Old Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> and ſtood all with their ſwords drawn, as alſo the Officers, and ſeverall ſpectators in windows. The City Horſe fell in next the Life-guard, then the Lord Mayor and Aldermen, after whom the Herald and the reſt as formerly. When they came to <hi>Chancery-lane end</hi> they proclaimed <hi>His Majeſty</hi> a third time, where at the word <hi>Charles the ſecond</hi> in the Proclamation, the king at Armes lifting himſelf up with more then ordinary cheerfulneſs, and expreſſing it with a very au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible voice, the people preſently took it, and on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don carried it to the <hi>Old Exchange,</hi> which was pu ſued with ſuch ſhouts, that is was near a quarter of an hour before ſilence could be made to read the reſt of the Proclamation. After this they went to <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> where <hi>His Majeſty</hi> was proclaimed a fourth time, the ſhouts of the people then being ſo great, that though <hi>Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells</hi> were then ringing, yet could not the ſound of them be heard. Thence they went to the <hi>Old Exchange,</hi> where <hi>His Majeſty</hi> was again proclaimed with the loud ſhouts and acclamations of the people, and ſo the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity ended. But to recount the numberleſs num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Bonfires, the ringing of Bells, ſhooting off Guns, and the joyfull expreſſions of the people that attended this gallant and well ordered proceſſion, would wear a pen of ſteel to the ſtumps, and tire the hand of the moſt unwearied writer.</p>
            <p>But this joy was not confined within the walls of the City; the whole Kingdome participating of the benefit, ſo did they alſo ſhare in the triumph: Our Chronicles make mention (even to admiration) of the ſolemnities at the Coronation of <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, but no Hiſtory can ſhew a preſident of ſuch tranſcendent joy as was at the proclaiming of <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40427:51"/>Take a view of their ſolemnities at <hi>Sherborn</hi> in <hi>Dorſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> by which you may give a gueſſe at the reſt.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Munday May</hi> 14. the Kings Majeſty (after ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne prayers, praiſes, and a ſeaſonable premonition at the Church by Mr. <hi>Bampfield</hi> to prevent exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancie,) was with high expreſſions of joy proclaimed by Mr. <hi>Birſtal,</hi> Maſter of the kings School there, to whom Sir <hi>John Strangways</hi> High Steward of <hi>Sherborn-Caſtle</hi> did read the Proclamation, himſelf not being able by reaſon of his age, to utter it with ſo loud and audible voice as was requiſite. The performance was attended by divers perſons of quality, viz. Mr. <hi>George Digby,</hi> ſecond Son to the Earl of <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> Eſquire <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Eſquire <hi>Rogers,</hi> one of Judge <hi>Mallets</hi> ſons, and many other Eſquires and Gentlemen, who brought with them as many Horſe and Foot well armed, as to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Town Forces made up between five and ſix thouſand. Beſides the melody of divers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts of Loud Muſick, there were the Martiall Noiſes of many Drums and Trumpets, innumerable Volleys of ſhot, the continuall ringing of Bells, and loud accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of many Thouſands of Men, Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, had that thwack'd the ſtreets ſo full, that thouſands of people, as well in Armes as others, were conſtrained to ſtay in the fields for want of room to receive them. The very Earth did ſeem to quake, and the Aire to tremble at the mighty rending ſhouts that were at that irerated. On the top of the Tower of the Ancient Cathedrall were four large white flags with red croſſes in them, diſplayed on high poles: The Conduit that day and the next ran with Claret, beſides many Hogs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads of March-bear, and large Baskets of white loaves ſet out in the ſtreet for the Poor. In the cloſe of the day, ſome of the witty wags of the Town, did very
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40427:51"/>formally repreſent an High Court of Juſtice at the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions Bench, whither by a formidable guard was brought a grim Judge or Lord Preſident, in a Bloud-red Robe, and a tire for his Head of the ſame Hue; who being gravely ſet down in the Chair of Judicature, with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry aſſeſlours, the Cryer in the Name of the Supreme Keeper of the Liberties of <hi>England</hi> did command ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. After the appointing of an Attorney Generall, a Solliciter Generall, and other Officers for the due conſtituting of ſo High a Court, and the empanneling of a Jury, <hi>John Bradſhaw</hi> and <hi>Oliver Caomwell,</hi> whoſe Effigies were artificially prepared and brought thither by a Guard of Souldiers, were indicted of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and murthering of the King, commanded to hold up their bloudy-hands, which for the purpoſe were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmeared with bloud: They were asked, Whether they did own the Authority of the Court? which being ſilent, the whole multitude preſent cryed out, <hi>Juſtice my Lord, Juſtice, on theſe bloody Traytors and Murtherers.</hi> They were asked again, whether they owned the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Court? and upon refuſall, ſentence was paſſed upon them, to be dragg'd to the place of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, to be there hang'd upon two Gibbets forty foot high, on both ſides the States Armes, which had lately been erected by Captain <hi>Chaſee,</hi> one of <hi>Lamberts</hi> Champions: which ſentence was accordingly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The Honeſt Officers that dragg'd them to Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the lower part of the Town to the upper, had many a blow with Fiſts, Swords, Halberts, and Pikes, which were aimed at the execrable Malefactors. As they hung upon the Gibbets, they were ſo hack'd and hew'd, ſo gored and ſhot through, that in a ſhort time little remained beſides <hi>Cromwells</hi> Buffe-coat and Bloudy ſcarfe, that was worth the burning; yet
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40427:52"/>would nor the people be ſatisfied till they had made a fire between the Gibbets, and burnt all they could get of their garbage or garments; and at laſt tore down the States Armes to help make up their funerall pile. At night beſides the multitude of Bonfires, there were three huge piles of faggots fired on the brows of three of the Higheſt Hills about a mile diſtant from the Town, which were viſible over all the Marſhes of <hi>Sommerſet-ſhire,</hi> in part of <hi>Wales,</hi> and the greateſt part of <hi>Black-moor.</hi> This extraordinary joy of the people of this Town might perhaps proceed from the native Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of the place, which having enjoyed formerly the reſidence of many a King and Biſhop, and the felicities that attend thoſe Governments in Church and State, did cauſe them to be even tranſported with joy at the reſtitution of the one, and fair hopes of reſtauration of the other to theſe ſo long harraſed Kingdomes and Churches.</p>
            <p>And now the Parliament and City (like the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> when <hi>David</hi> was forced from <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> by <hi>Abſalon,</hi>) ſtrive who ſhall be forwardeſt to bring the King home. The Parliament ordered 50000l. to be preſented to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> as alſo 10000l. to the Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and 5000l. to the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> as a teſtimony of their reſpects to the Royal Family. the City of <hi>London</hi> likewiſe ordered a preſent of 10000l. to be ſent to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> who is deſired to make a ſpeedy return to the exerciſe of His kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and theſe Honourable perſons from the Lords, Commons, and City, ordered to attend him in his journey.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:40427:52"/>
            <p>For the Houſe of Lords.
<list>
                  <item>The Earl of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Earl of <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Brook.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Earl of <hi>Warwick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Viſcount Hereford.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Berkley.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> and Dr. <hi>Charleton</hi> their Phyſician.</p>
            <p>For the Houſe of Commons.
<list>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Fairfax.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Bruce.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Faulkland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>C stleton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Herbert.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Mandevil.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Horatio Townſend.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Anth. Aſhley-Cooper.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>George Booth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Denzil Hollis</hi> Eſq;</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Holland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Henry Cholmley.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> and Mr. <hi>Bowles</hi> their Phyſician.</p>
            <p>For the City of <hi>London.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Sir <hi>James Bunce</hi> Baronet</item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Langham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Reynardſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Brown.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Nicholas Criſpe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Tomſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Frederick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Adams.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Recorder <hi>Wilde.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Robinſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Bateman.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Alderman <hi>Wale.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Theophilus Biddolph.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard Ford.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Will. Vincent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tho. Bludworth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Will. Bateman.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>J. Lewes</hi> Eſq;</item>
                  <item>M. <hi>Chamberlain.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Col. <hi>Bromfield.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And now ſince we were come again under a Regall Government, the States Armes were ordered to be taken down in all places, and the Kings Armes ſet up in their room; the Standerts, Flags, and Jacks, Colours
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40427:53"/>for the Fleet, to be uſed as before 1648. their carved and painted works altered, &amp;c. The Statue of His late Royal Majeſty, that was formerly taken down at the Chappell in Guild-hall yard, was ſet up again. Thus was all endeavours uſed to obliterate as much as could be the very memory of our State-juglers, who promiſing to bring us into a fools Paradiſe of liberty, brought us into a reall bondage and ſlavery.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding the great hopes of a happy ſettlement, the knipperdoling Fifth-Monarchy-men, and others of that looſe principled gang, would needs have another firke to re-erect their Babell; their deſign was (having prepared ſaddles and armes,) to have ſtole the Horſes and Mares at graſſe about the Town; and having mounted their Proſelites, intended with them to perform wonders; but their Conſpiracy was rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before it was ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, giving to thoſe that were Loyall this advantage thereby, <hi>before the Stead was ſtole to ſhut the ſtable door.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I paſs any further, having diſcovered a Cheat, give me leave to have it pillory'd. The Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed of the ſum of ſeven thouſand, nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, ſeventy eight pounds, eight ſhillings nine pence, heretofore paid into the recei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the Exchequer, of the moneys collected for the relief of the Poor Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in <hi>Piedmont</hi> and <hi>Poland;</hi> but by the <hi>Quondam</hi> States-men converted to another uſe, they deteſting and abhorring the diverſion of the ſaid money, from the charitable uſes to which it was originally intended. Ordered the ſaid ſum to be paid out of ſuch monies as ſhould come into the ſaid receipt upon the moity of the Exciſe, at the rate of 2000 l. by the month, till the whole were ſatisfied, unto Alderman <hi>Viner,</hi> and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Pack</hi> Treaſurers for the ſaid monies; by this we
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40427:53"/>may ſee the large Conſcience of our pretended zealots; whoſe inſatiable Covetouſneſs extended ſo far as even to the robbing of the ſpittle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> the twelfth, ſeveral goods which were kept at a Fruiterers Houſe in <hi>Thames-ſtreet</hi> were ſeized on, they being found to have belonged formerly to <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While <hi>His Majeſty</hi> reſides at <hi>Breda</hi> with the Dukes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> the miniſters of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France</hi> congratulate him: The King of <hi>Spain</hi> preſents him very largely; The States Generall alſo deſire au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> and being admitted, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to the <hi>Hague,</hi> and preſent him with 6000l. Ster. and in further teſtimony of their kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſtfrieſland</hi> order ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Commanders, <hi>as ſoon as any publick addreſſe ſhould be made to the King, to ſignifie their ſerious and ſincere affections to</hi> His Majeſty <hi>and to His Family, and their deſires to ſettle a firme and everlaſting alliance with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About this time the Army in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſend an Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble addreſſe to the Generall, ſhewing, <hi>That as they were amazed at the former changes and revolutions, ſo they could not but with joy now obſerve light breaking out of darkneſs, and order out of confuſion. That whereas the Parliament had manifeſted their joyfull ſenſe of</hi> His Majeſties <hi>gracious offers, they did alſo teſtify their joy and contentment therein, and were reſolv'd to obſerve the commands of his Excellency, deſiring him to improve this reall and cordiall engagement of theirs, both with</hi> His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty <hi>and the two Houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to the Commiſſioners ſent to attend <hi>His Majeſty;</hi> they having a proſperous wind, and ſmooth ſea, <hi>(Eolus)</hi> in ſhort time arrived at the <hi>Hague,</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:40427:54"/>whither ſoon after came <hi>His Sacred Majeſty,</hi> the Dukes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> with the Princeſſe Royall, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Regiment of her Horſe, being Royally enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained all the way from <hi>Breda,</hi> at the charge of the States Generall; The next day the Commiſſioners had audience, the Earl of <hi>Oxford</hi> delivered the meſſage from the Houſe of Lords, <hi>Denzill Hollis</hi> from the Commons, and the Recorder of <hi>London</hi> from the City. <hi>His Majeſty</hi> conferred the Honour of knighthood on all the Citizens ſent as Commiſſioners, with the Lord <hi>Gerards</hi> ſword. The Miniſters of <hi>London</hi> had ſome conference with him, who received much ſatisfaction in his Religious diſcourſe. The States Generall during <hi>His Majeſties</hi> ſtay there (which by reaſon of croſſe winds was the longer) entertained him with a Coſtly Banquet and Royall preſents, among the reſt they gave him the gold plate wherein the firſt Courſe at one of their feaſts had been ſerv'd up, valu'd at 60000 l. and table-linnen to the value of 1000 l. alſo a bed worth 7000 l. and 600000. gilders; and as a further addition to the ſatisfaction of <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> they preſented to his Nephew the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> a full confirmation of all Honours and profits his Father enjoyed. At laſt the weather growing calme he went aboard, where ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his leave of the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Princeſs Royall, and Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> (who accompanied him into the ſhip) they ſet ſail for <hi>England, His Majeſty</hi> in the Royal <hi>Charles</hi> (formerly the <hi>Naſeby,</hi>) the Duke of <hi>Yorke</hi> in the <hi>London,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> in the <hi>James,</hi> before called the <hi>Swift-ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>The Gods did guide their ſail &amp; courſe, the winds were at command.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Dover</hi> was the happy place where firſt they came o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> land.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:40427:54"/>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> 25. they arrived at the Beech near the Peer of <hi>Dover,</hi> whither not above two Hours before, was come his Excellency the Lord Cenerall <hi>Monck,</hi> to congratulate <hi>His Majeſties</hi> happy arrivall. Now did all perſons put themſelves into a poſture for to obſerve the meeting of the beſt of Kings, and moſt deſerving of Subjects: The admirers of Majeſty were jealous on the Kings behalf of too low a condiſcention, and the lovers of duty on the other ſide of an oſtentation of merit; but ſuch an humble proſtration was made by his Excellency kneeling, and ſo fitting a Reception by <hi>His Majeſty</hi> kiſſing and embracing him, that all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were ſatisfied, and the Generall now taught by the ſight of his Soveraign to make perfect mixture of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaeſtion</hi> with <hi>Cracterus;</hi> ſo that what hath hitherto been done out of bounden duty to his Leige Lord, will here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be continued out of Loyall affection to his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Maſter. <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to demonſtrate the High eſteeme he had of his Excellency, put the George on him with his own hands, the Duke of <hi>Yorke</hi> and Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> put on the Garter, all theſe three Royall Princes joyning unanimouſly together to honour him, ſeverall other perſons alſo received the Honour of Knighthood, as Major Generall <hi>Maſſy,</hi> Alderman <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binſon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In his paſſage he was met by the Mayor and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Dover,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Redding</hi> the Miniſter, who, after a ſhort ſpeech, preſented <hi>His Majeſty</hi> with a large Bible with gold claſps. From thence <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> accompanied with a numerous Traine of Nobility and Gentry, went to <hi>Canterbury,</hi> where he was met by the Mayor, Aldermen, and Mr. Recorder <hi>Love,</hi> who after a Rhetorical ſpeech, with many expreſſions of Loyalty to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> preſented him with a gold Tanke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40427:55"/>and ſo conducted him to his Palace, where he remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till <hi>Munday May</hi> the 28. on which day he went to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and having ſomething refreſhed himſelf, he went to <hi>Chatham</hi> to ſee the <hi>Royall Soveraign,</hi> and the reſt of his Ships, (<hi>Englands Bulwarke</hi> againſt their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign enemies,) where having ſatisfied himſelf, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Commiſſioner <hi>Pell</hi> with his preſence at a Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, he returned to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and lodged at Col. <hi>Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> his Houſe; who preſented to <hi>His Majesty</hi> a very dutifull Addreſſe, ſigned by himſelf, and the Officers of his Regiment; which <hi>His Majeſty</hi> received very Graciouſly, and by many expreſſions to the Colonel, gave a teſtimony of his affection to him in particular, and to the reſt of the Army in generall. The Mayor and Corporation of the City preſented <hi>His Majeſty</hi> with a Baſon and Ewer of ſilver guilt of a good value, which was kindly accepted. <hi>May</hi> the 29. being <hi>His Majeſties</hi> birth-day, (a day to be had in everlaſting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, as well for his return to receive the Crown, as being born that day Heire to it) He took his Journey towards <hi>London,</hi> the Militia forces of <hi>Kent</hi> lineing the ways, and maidens ſtrowing herbs and flowers, and the ſeverall Towns hanging out white ſheets.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Dartford</hi> this following addreſſe was preſented to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> ſubſcribed by the ſeverall Regiments of Horſe under his Excellencies command, viz.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:40427:55"/>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="address">
               <body>
                  <head>To His moſt Excellent Majeſty, King <hi>Charles</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, our moſt Gracious Soveraign: the humble ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe of the Officers of the ſeverall Regiments of Horſe under the Command of his Excellency the Lord Generall <hi>Monck,</hi> as it was preſented by them.</head>
                  <p>With ſuch a joy as flowes from Reverence and Love, we humbly preſent our ſelves before Your Sacred Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty: Beſides our reflection on the Common good, which in this happy change relates to our particular, intends this joy, and renders it ſincere: for we can now pleaſe our ſelves in our ſelves, while we are really performing that duty for which we were first raiſed. And with all thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs we acknowledge that care <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> in Your late Letter and Declaration hath expreſſed of our neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary intent.</p>
                  <p>We bleſſe God to ſee that day, when the ſerenity of every mans Countenance diſcovers the tranquility of his mind, for this ſhews <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> to be the true ſoul of the people, ſince during Your abſence the whole Nation was caſt into ſuch diſtractions, as we have no pleaſure to remember; but had rather turn our thoughts and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full acknowledgments to the happy conduct of our <hi>Noble Generall,</hi> who hath thus far led us in our duty to Your <hi>Royal Perſon:</hi> yet as we cannot attribute too much to his merits, ſo neither can we deprive our ſelves of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Comfort which we find in the accompliſhment of his juſt deſign.</p>
                  <p>Therefore in plain and ſouldier-like (though humble) termes, we ſay, <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> hath made us and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion happy in Your return to this Your Native Kingdome; which doubtleſs will, nay we may ſay, hath produced a
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40427:56"/>ſettlement upon the foundation of our ancient Laws: By the due Execution of which, together with <hi>Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> pious inclinations, we truſt Libertiſme and Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wholly ſuppreſſed, the Proteſtant cauſe and true profeſſors of it encouraged, to the comfort of all Your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and good people.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> will now have Your great Council about You, who have already given proof of their Loyalty and Wiſdome, both to <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> and them. We profeſſe and declare, That as we have not been altogether uſeleſs in the Reſtoration as well of <hi>Your Sacred Majeſty</hi> to Your Crowns and Kingdomes, as Your people to their juſt Rights, ſo we ſhall in the future cheerfully ſacrifice our Lives, and whatſoever can be more dear to us, in the ſervice of <hi>Your Majeſty,</hi> againſt all oppoſitions whatſoever; and by a ready obedience to <hi>Your Majeſties</hi> commands, Expreſſe our ſelves,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Majeſties moſt Loyall Subjects and obedient Servants.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>At <hi>Black-Heath</hi> the Army was drawn up, to whom <hi>His Majeſty</hi> delivered himſelf in many gracious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of his favour and protection, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Souldiers with the loud acclamations of the Drum and Musket, diſplaying of Enſignes, and other Milita y rejoycings. From thence (the Army being placed according to his Excellenies order) <hi>His Majeſty</hi> marched towards <hi>London,</hi> ſeverall Bonfires being made all the way as he paſſed along, one more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable then the reſt for its bigneſs, wherein the St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes (Butter-print, <hi>alias</hi> their) Armes, were conſumed to aſhes.</p>
            <p>When <hi>His Majeſty</hi> came to St. <hi>Georges</hi> fields, the Lord M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yor and Aldermen were in a Tent ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40427:56"/>him; There the Lord Mayor delivered the King his ſword upon his knees, which <hi>His Majeſty</hi> return'd him. After a repaſt taken there, <hi>His Majeſty</hi> ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to <hi>White-hall</hi> in this manner. All the Streets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing richly hanged with Tapeſtry, and a lane made by the Militia forces to <hi>London-bridge,</hi> from <hi>London bridge</hi> to <hi>Temple-bar</hi> by the Trained-bands on one ſide, and the ſeverall Companies in their Liveries, and the Streamers of each Company of the other ſide by the Railes: from <hi>Temple-bar</hi> to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> by the Militia forces, Regiments of the Army, and ſeverall Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men formerly Officers of the Kings Army, led by Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> firſt marched a Troop of Gentlemen led by Major Generall <hi>Brown,</hi> brandiſhing their ſwords, in Cloath of ſilver doublets, in all about 300. beſides their ſervants. Then another Troop of about 200. in Velvet coates, the Foot-men and Liveries in purple. Then another Troop led by Sir <hi>John R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>binſon,</hi> with Buff-coats, Silver ſleeves, and Green ſcarves. After this, a Troop with blew Liveries and ſilver lace, colors red, fringed with ſilver, about 130. After that a Troop, 6. Trumpets, 7. Foot-men in ſea-green and ſilver, their colors pinck, fringed with ſilver. Then a Troop with gray and blew Liveries, ſilke and ſilver laces, 30. Foot-men, and 4. Trumpets, conſiſting of about 220. their colors sky, f inged with ſilver. Another of gray Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, 6. Trumpets, colors sky and ſilver, of about 105. Gentlemen. Another Troop of 70. Gentlemen, 5. Trumpets, colors sky and ſilver. Another Troop led by the Lord <hi>Cleveland,</hi> of about 300. Noblemen and Gentlemen, colors blew, fringed with gold. Then another Troop of about 100. having black colors fringed with gold. After them another Troop of about 300.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:40427:57"/>
            <p>After theſe came two Trumpets with <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Armes, the Sheriffs men in red cloakes and ſilver lace, with half pikes, 79. in number, then followed the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Companies of <hi>London,</hi> with their ſeveral Stream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, all in black velvet coats with gold chains, every Company having their footmen of their ſeveral Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſome red and white, ſome pink and white, ſome blew and yellow, &amp;c. Three Trumpets in Liveries richly laced, and cloth of ſilverſleeves went before the Company of the Mercers. After all theſe, came a kettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drum, 5. Trumpets, and 3. ſtreamers, having very rich red Liveries with ſilver lace. The number of the Citizens, were about 600. After theſe 12. miniſters, another kettle-drum, 4. Trumpets, then <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Life-guard, led by the Lord <hi>Gerard,</hi> another party led by Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerard,</hi> and Major <hi>Roſecarron,</hi> and the third diviſion by Colonel <hi>Pragurs;</hi> Then 3. Trumpets in rich coats and ſattin doublets. The City Marſhall with 8. footmen in French-green, trimed with crimſon and white, the City waites, the City Officers in order; Then Dr. <hi>Warmſtry,</hi> the two Sheriffs, and all the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen of <hi>London,</hi> in their ſcarlet gowns and rich trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, with footmen in Liveries, red coats laced with ſilver, and cloth of gold. The Heralds and Maces in their rich coats. The Lord Mayor bare, carrying the ſword, his Excellency and the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> bare: Then the glory of all <hi>His Sacred Majeſty</hi> rode between the Dukes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Glocester:</hi> afterwards followed a Troop bare with white colors, then the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls Life-guard; after which another company of Gentry, having sky colors, fringed with gold; after which 5. Regiments of the Army-Horſe led by Col. <hi>Knight,</hi> viz. His Excellencies Regiment, Col. <hi>Knights,</hi> Col. <hi>Cloberr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> Lord <hi>Fauconbergs,</hi> Lord <hi>Howards;</hi> Laſt of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:40427:57"/>all came two Troops of Nobility and Gentlemen, with red colors, fringed with gold. Never did <hi>Hiperion</hi> the worlds bright eye, behold a more gallant ſight of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentlemen then marched then, brandiſhing their ſwords all along. Soon after <hi>His Majeſty</hi> was paſsed, all the muſquetires that had lined the ſtreets gave many volleys of ſhot.</p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>His Majeſty</hi> conducted to his Royal Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace at <hi>White-hall,</hi> where after the Lord Mayor had taken his leave, <hi>His Majeſty</hi> went unto the Lords, to whom the Earl of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> their Speaker addreſſed himſelf in theſe words.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>That this day may prove happy to</hi> Your Majeſty, <hi>is the hope and Expectation, and the earneſt deſire of my Lords the Peeres, whoſe Commands are upon me to make this humble tender to</hi> Your Majeſty <hi>of their Loyall joy for</hi> Your Majeſties <hi>ſafe Return to Your Native Kingdome; and for this happy Reſtoration of</hi> Your Majeſty <hi>to Your Crown and Dignity, after ſo long, and ſo ſevere a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Your juſt Right and Title.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſhall not reflect upon</hi> Your Majeſties <hi>ſufferings, which have been Your peoples miſeries; yet I cannot omit to ſay, That as the Nation in generall, ſo the Peeres with a more perſonall and particular ſenſe have felt the ſtroke that cut the</hi> Gordian <hi>knot which faſtned</hi> Your Majeſty <hi>to Your kingdome, and Your kingdome to</hi> Your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For ſince thoſe ſtrange and various fluctuations and Diſcompoſures in Government, ſince thoſe horrid and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd Violations of all Order and Juſtice,</hi> Strangers have ruled over us, <hi>even with a Rod of Iron: But now with ſatisfaction of Heart, we own and ſee</hi> Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty <hi>our Native King, a ſon of the wiſe, a ſon of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40427:58"/>kings, whoſe hands hold forth a golden Scepter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Great King! <hi>Give me leave to speake the Confidence as well as the deſires of the Peers of</hi> England: <hi>Be you the powerfull defender of the true Proteſtant faith, the juſt aſſertor and maintainer of the Laws and Liberties of Your Subjects; ſo ſhall</hi> Judgement run down like a River, and Juſtice like a mighty ſtreame; <hi>and God, the God of Your Mercy, who hath ſo miraculouſly preſerved You, will eſtabliſh Your Throne in Righteouſneſs and in Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dread Soveraign! <hi>I offer no flattering Titles, but ſpeak the words of truth: you are the deſire of Three kingdomes, the ſtrength and the ſtay of the Tribes of the people, for the moderating of Extremities, the reconciling of Differences, the ſatisfying of all Intereſts, and for the Reſtoring of the collapſed Honour of theſe Nations. Their Eyes are toward</hi> Your Majeſty, <hi>their Tongues with loud Acclamations of Joy, speak the thoughts and Loyall intentions of their Hearts; their Hands are lift up to Heaven with Prayers and Praiſes: and what Oral Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph can equall this Your Pomp and Glory?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Long may</hi> Your Majeſty <hi>live and raign, a ſupport to Your Friends, a terror to Enemies, and Honour to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and an Example to Kings, of Piety, Juſtice, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Power; that this Prophetick Expreſſion may be verified in</hi> Your Majeſty, King CHARLES the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſhall be greater then ever was the greateſt of that name.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty</hi> having returned a gracious anſwer to the Lords, went from thence unto the Banqueting Houſe; where Sir <hi>Harbotle Grimſton</hi> Speaker to the Houſe of Commons, delivered himſelf in this ſpeech to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> the Members of that Houſe being there preſent.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40427:58"/>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſt gracious and dread Soveraign,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If all the Reaſon and Eloquence that is diſperſed in ſo many ſeverall heads and tongues as are in the whole world, were conveyed into my Braine, and united in my tongue, yet I ſhould want ſufficiency to diſcharge that great task I am now enjoyned.</p>
               <p>The reſtitution of <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> to the exerciſe of Your juſt and moſt indubitable Native Right of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, and the deliverance of Your people from bondage and ſlavery, hath been wrought out and brought to paſſe, by a miraculous way of Divine Providence, beyond and above the reach and comprehenſion of our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and therefore to be admired, impoſſible to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</p>
               <p>God hath been pleaſed to train <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> up in the School of affliction, where You have learned that excellent leſſon of patience ſo well, and improved it ſo much for the good of the people, that we have all juſt cauſe for ever to Bleſs God for it, and we doubt not but Your Name is Regiſtred in the Records of Heaven, to have a place in the higheſt from amongst thoſe glorious Martyrs, of whom it is reported that through faith in Chriſt, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in their ſufferings, they converted their very Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentors, and conquered thoſe Barbarous bloody Tyrants, under whom they then ſuffered, inſomuch as they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were many times inforced to confeſſe and cry out, <hi>Sat eſt, viciſti Galilaeus,</hi> they had their <hi>(viciſti)</hi> and that deſervedly, but <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> muſt have a treble <hi>(vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſti)</hi> for with the ſame weapon, Faith and Patience, You have overcome them, and conquered the Hearts and Affections of all Your People in three great Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Hearts and Affections of all that are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40427:59"/>the name of good Chriſtians, or reaſonable men.</p>
               <p>'Tis God and God alone to whom be the glory that hath made <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> ſo great a Conquerour, indeed Your Conqueſt is incomparable, no ſtory can inſtance the like, or furniſh us with an Example to parallel it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; 'Twas a uſe and cuſtome amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> when any of their Commanders had done eminent ſervices abroad, at their returns, to honour them with Triumphs, and riding through their ſtreets, there they received the praiſes and applauſes of the people, with this inſcription upon their Lawrell Crowns, <hi>(Vincenti dabitur.)</hi> But <hi>Your Majeſties</hi> victory is of another Nature, and as it differs much from theirs in the quality of it, ſo Your Triumph muſt differ as much from theirs in the manner of it: They conquered bodies, but <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered ſouls; they conquered for the honour and good of themſelves, but <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> hath conquered for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and good of Your people; they conquered with force, but <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> hath conquered with faith; they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered with power, and therefore God himſelf hath written with patience; and therefore God himſelf hath written Your Motto, and inſcribed it upon Your Royal Crown <hi>(Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienti dabitur.)</hi> Their triumphs were in narrow ſtreets, but <hi>Your Majeſties</hi> triumphs muſt be in large hearts; their triumph laſted but for a day, but <hi>Your Majeſties</hi> triumph muſt laſt for all Your days, and after that to triumph in Heaven to all Eternity.</p>
               <p>I have read of a Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> who was called <hi>Carolus Audax,</hi> the Hiſtorian tells us that his Father was called <hi>Carolus Bonus,</hi> an Obſervator hath this note upon it, That Goodneſs doth ever produce Boldneſs; Sir, you are the true Son of ſuch a good Father, and ſo long as You ſerve our good God, He who is goodneſs it ſelf, will give You B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldneſs; a Princely vertue, and the best foil <hi>Your
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40427:59"/>Majeſty</hi> can uſe to ſet out the true luſtre of all Your other moſt eminent and lovely Graces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſt Royall Soveraign!</hi> I have yet a few words more, and to doubt of Your patience, who is the mirror of patience, were to commit a crime unpardonable, and fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be excepted out of that Act of Oblivion, which <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> hath ſo graciouſly tendered unto Your people; therefore with an humble confidence I ſhall preſume to acquaint <hi>Your Majeſty,</hi> that I have it further in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to preſent You at this time with a <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> and humbly upon my bended knees to beg Your Royall aſſent thereunto. Sir, it hath already paſſed two great Houſes, Heaven and Earth, and I have <hi>Vox po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli,</hi> and <hi>Vox Dei,</hi> to warrant this bold demand. It is that <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> would be pleaſed to Remove Your Throne of State, and to ſet it up in the Hearts of Your poople, and as You are deſervedly the King of Hearts, there to receive from Your people a Crown of Hearts: Sir, this Crown hath three excellent and rare properties, 'tis a ſweet Crown, 'tis a faſt Crown, and 'tis a laſting Crown; 'tis a ſweet Crown, for 'tis perfumed with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the incenſe of prayers and praiſes; and 'tis a faſt Crown, for 'tis ſet upon Your Royall Head, by him who onely hath the power of Hearts, the King of Kings; and 'tis a lasting Crown, <hi>Your Majeſty</hi> can never wear it out, for the longer You wear this Crown, it will be the better for the wearing; and it is the hearty deſire and moſt earneſt prayers of all Your Loyall, Loving and Faithfull Subjects, that You may never change that Crown till You change it for a Crown of Eternall Glory in the Highest Heavens, And the Lord ſay Amen.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The ſolemnity of the day was concluded by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of Bonfires, by the flames whereof the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40427:60"/>Rumpers might ſee how deteſtable their tyranny was unto the people, for as if all the houſes had turned out their Chimnies into the ſtreets (the weather being very warme) there were almoſt as many fires in the ſtreets as houſes throughout <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> a very coſtly one was made, where the Effigies of <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> with the Common-wealths Armes, were ſet upon a high poſt, which having been expoſed there a while to publike view, with torches lighted, that every one might take better notice of them, were burnt together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Friday</hi> following <hi>His Majeſty</hi> went the private way to the Houſe of Lords, the Yeomen of the Guard making a lane, the Heralds at Armes in their rich coats, the maces, and the Lord Generall bare. When <hi>His Majeſty</hi> came to the Houſe, the Uſher of the Black-Rod went to the Houſe of Commons to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them that <hi>His Majeſty</hi> deſired them to meet him at the Houſe of Lords; when they were entered, <hi>His Majeſty</hi> made a ſhort ſpeech, and gave his Royall aſſent to three Acts, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, the Act for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Parliament, Second, for the Tax of 70000 l.<hi>per menſem,</hi> Third, for the continuance of Proceſs and Judiciall proceedings; after which the Lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour made a ſpeech more at large. The ſame day a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation was publiſhed againſt vicious, debauched, and profane perſons.</p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:40427:60"/>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty</hi> being thus reſtor'd the next thing moſt conſiderable was the ſettling of his Privy Council, a work which he was not long about, their Names being as follows.</p>
            <list>
               <item>The Duke of <hi>York.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lord Chancellor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>M. of <hi>Ormond.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord High Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain <hi>Leudſey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Barkſhire.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Southhampton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Viſcout <hi>Seymor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Say</hi> and <hi>Seal.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Wentworth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Ed. Nicholas.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Ant. Aſh. Cooper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Duke of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord Gen. <hi>Monck.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>M. <hi>Hertford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Mancheſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Northum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of St. <hi>Albons.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Earl of <hi>Leiceſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Culpeper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Roberts.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Will. Morris.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Anneſtey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Den. Hollis.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Clerks of the Council.</head>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Brown.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>George Lane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir. <hi>Ed. Walker.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Nicholas.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>While theſe things are done at <hi>White-hall,</hi> The Houſe proceed to the naming of theſe perſons which they reſolved ſhould be out of the Act for pardon, and agreed upon theſe ſeven,</p>
            <list>
               <item>Col. <hi>Harriſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Will. Say.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Jones.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tho. Scot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cor. Holland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Liſle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Berkstead.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To which they afterwards added <hi>Peters</hi> and <hi>Hulit,</hi> both
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40427:61"/>ſuſpected for the Kings Executioners, <hi>Cook, Dendy, Broughton, Phelpes, More.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the ſeventh of <hi>June</hi> a Proclamation was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in <hi>His Majeſties</hi> name, to reſummon all thoſe that ſate and gave judgment, in that horrid and deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able murther of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Father, to appear and render themſelves within 14. dayes after the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, to the Speakers of either Houſes, the Lord Mayor, or the reſpective Sheriffs, and that no perſon ſhould harbour them under miſpriſion of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; which being publiſhed, many preſuming on the charity and goodneſs of <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> did accordingly ſubmit themſelves to his mercy. Such were <hi>Hevening<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Penington, Adrian Scroop, Auſtin Garland,</hi> Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> Col. <hi>Downs,</hi> Col. <hi>Dixwell, Hen. Martin,</hi> Sir <hi>Hard. Waller.</hi> Mr. <hi>Meir,</hi> Col. <hi>Waite,</hi> Col. <hi>Temple, Tichborn, Fleetwood,</hi> Col. <hi>John Temple,</hi> and ſome few others.</p>
            <p>Nor could <hi>His Majeſty</hi> want employment; having enough to doe to receive all theſe addreſſes which were made to him from all the Shires and Towns of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which though they throng'd in ſo faſt, yet <hi>His Majeſty</hi> was ſtill ready to entertain them, with ſo much grace and favour, that he gave ſatisfaction to all.</p>
            <p>Nor was this joy confin'd within the limits of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> other Countries partaking thereof, and making themſelves concern'd in our great alterations, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly at <hi>Heidelburgh, Frankendale, Wormes,</hi> and <hi>Herld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bron,</hi> in all which places was a day of publick prayers and thanksgiving, for the reſtoration of <hi>His Sacred Majeſty</hi> of Great Brittain. The King of <hi>Portugall</hi> alſo when he heard the news thereof, preſently gave order that the ſame night all the great guns of the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:40427:61"/>Caſtle, and Forts of the Town and Harbour ſhould be fired; The whole City was adorn'd with lights, and in every window of the Kings Palace were ſet two great Torches of white wax, beſides Bonfires and Fireworks in the ſtreets; the King and Queen next morning with the Infanta and Nobility, went forth in ſolemn manner to the Church of St. <hi>Anthony's</hi> of the <hi>Capuchins,</hi> all the bells in the Town ringing the while. By which it was plainlyſeen with what reall joy and ſatisfaction the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Court and Nation receiv'd the welcome tydings of ſo happy a change.</p>
            <p>And now we are beyond ſea, it may not be from the purpoſe to relate ſomething of the great Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King of <hi>France</hi> and the Infanta of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which happened much about this time; eſpecially the King of <hi>France</hi> being a Prince ſo nearly related to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi> The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> being now after a tedious journey arrived at <hi>Fintarabia,</hi> the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Marriage being the ſame with the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of ordinary marriages but more pompous, were celebrated and performed by the Biſhop of <hi>Pamplona,</hi> with the aſſiſtance of the Patriarch of the Indies, in the Church of ſaid Town: Before the performance the Infanta kneel'd twice before the King her Father; firſt to ask him bleſſing, and ſecondly before ſhe gave her conſent to the Marriage. The Ceremony being ended, the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> gave her all the reſpect due to ſo great a Queen, giving her the right hand both in his going out of the Church, and as they rode together in the Coach; He likewiſe gave her his own lodgings and took hers, where though ſhe had not been ſeen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſhe then did ride in publick; within a day or two after the two Kings had an interview, where both Kings were uncovered, that the grandees of <hi>Spaine</hi> might
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:40427:62"/>not take an occaſion to be cover'd. Then the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> having deliver'd his daughter into the hands of the King of <hi>France,</hi> the Queen Mother took her away in her Coach, which done, the two Kings parted with all demonſtration of amity and affection. Afterwards the young Queen was preſented with ſeverall preſents from her Father, and <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Kings Brother and Cardinall, which were ſo rich, and ſo magnificent, that never were more Royall preſents ſeen.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Parliament to ſhew the value of that pardon, from the benefit of which they were excepting ſo many perſons, came to <hi>His Majeſty</hi> and in the name of themſelves, and the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> laid hold on <hi>His Majeſties</hi> gracious pardon mentioned in his Declaration from <hi>Breda;</hi> wherefore on <hi>Munday</hi> being the 25. of <hi>June, His Majeſty</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd a Proclamation in purſuance of his former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, declaring that <hi>His Majeſty</hi> did graciouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the addreſs of the Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <p>After this the Houſe proceed upon the Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity, and having reſolved that thoſe perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned ſhould be excepted from life, they agree upon 20. more, which, though yet excluded from death ſhould ſuffer all penalties and forfeitures excepting life; concerning which buſineſs after they had had many debates, they conclude at laſt upon theſe perſons following,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Lenthall.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Hen. Vane.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Sydenham.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Disborough.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ald. <hi>Ireton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Axtell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Keeble.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Capt. <hi>Blackwell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Major <hi>Creed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Charles Fleetwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alderman Pack.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:40427:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>Col. <hi>Pine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Col. <hi>Cobbet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Capt. <hi>Dean.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oliver</hi> St. <hi>John.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Will. Nye.</hi> Miniſters</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Goodwin.</hi> Miniſters</item>
            </list>
            <p>But as the King ſaw them quick in their juſtice, ſo he thought them too ſlow in their mercy; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having often preſs'd them to perfect the Act of Indempnity and nothing yet finiſh'd, he goes himſelf to the Houſe to haſten them, telling <hi>them with what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience he did expect that Act to be preſented to him for his aſſent, as the moſt reaſonable and ſolid foundation of peace and ſecurity; That he thought the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons too long about it, thanking God that he had the ſame intentions and reſolutions which he had at</hi> Breda; and then reading what he had then writ to them he added afterwards, <hi>that if they did not then joyn with him in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhing the fear which keeps the hearts of men awake, and apprehenſive of ſafety and ſecurity, they would keep him from performing his promiſe.</hi> He then thank'd them for their <hi>juſtice to thoſe who had been the immediate murderers of his Father,</hi> and aſſured them <hi>he never thought of excepting any other;</hi> and at length conjur'd them <hi>that ſetting all animoſities aſide to paſs that Act without further delay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty</hi> having thus put them in mind of their clemency, was not forgetfull himſelf of that gratitude which he thought due to thoſe who had ſerv'd him with a meritorious loyalty; and there caſting an eye of grace upon his Excellency the Lord Generall <hi>Monck</hi> for his faithfull ſervice, he was graciouſly pleas'd to create him <hi>Duke of Albemarly, Earl of Finington, Baron of Pothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge, Beaucham and Teyes, Captain Generall and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief of all</hi> His Majeſties <hi>forces both in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>Maſter of</hi> His Majeſties
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:40427:63"/>
               <hi>Horſe, Knight of the moſt noble order of the Garter, and one of</hi> His Majeſties <hi>moſt honourable privy Councill.</hi> Whereupon accompanied with the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and other perſonages of high quality, he took his leave of the Houſe of Commons, and went to take his place in the Houſe of Peers.</p>
            <p>Gen. <hi>Mountague</hi> alſo created Earl of <hi>Sandwich, Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Hinchimbrook</hi> Baron of St. <hi>Needs,</hi> Maſter of the <hi>Wardrobe,</hi> one of the Commanders of the treaſurie, and Knight of the Garter, not long after took his place in the Houſe of Peers.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Greenvile</hi> who adventur'd firſt to bring <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Letters over to the Houſes and the Lord Generall, <hi>His Majeſty</hi> was pleas'd to create Earl of <hi>Bath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was <hi>His Majesty</hi> unmindfull of Col. <hi>Carles,</hi> to whom with a ſmall alteration of his name, he gave a new coat of Armes, which will always be a ſignificant record of that ſervice wherein his Loyalty was ſo uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>Nor did the <hi>Penderils His Majeſties</hi> faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in his ſhelter at <hi>Boſcobel</hi> goe unrewarded, of one of whom named <hi>William,</hi> it is reported that being in the Park of St. <hi>James</hi>'s, and meeting <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> he run to the King and took him by the arme, with ſuch an unadviſed rudeneſs to kiſs his hand, as made <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> more ſeverely then ordinary demand who he was; but when he reply'd that he was that <hi>William that fed His Majeſty in the Oake, His Majesty</hi> was graciouſly pleas'd to give the Marq. of <hi>Ormond</hi> charge of him to ſee him well provided for; for ſomething before that in Reference to the ſetling of the Kings Houſhold, the Marqueſs was made Lord high Steward of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Houſhold. Other offices were alſo diſpos'd
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40427:63"/>of to others. The Earl <hi>Mancheſter</hi> was made Lord Chamberlain. The Earl of <hi>Barkſhire</hi> one of the Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, but the treaſurie was ſtill let to remain in the hands of Commanders.</p>
            <p>And as the King is now ordering of his houſhold, ſo is the Duke of <hi>Albemarly</hi> making alterations in the Army to <hi>His Majeſties</hi> beſt advantage, the commands of moſt of the Regiments both of Horſe and Foot being conferr'd upon the Nobilitie. Col. <hi>Smithſons</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is given to the Earl of <hi>Oxford,</hi> Col. <hi>Faggs</hi> to <hi>John Viſcount Mordant,</hi> Col. <hi>Purys</hi> to the Lord <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> Col. <hi>Twiſtletons</hi> to Sir <hi>Edward Maſſey,</hi> the Lord <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lkenbridge's</hi> to his Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Sir <hi>Ralph Knights</hi> Regiment to the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> Sir <hi>Ralph Knight</hi> Commanding as Lieut. Col. under him, Col. <hi>Streaters</hi> Regiment to the Lord <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> Col. <hi>Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons</hi>'s Regiment is Commanded by the Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi> the Lord <hi>Oſſory</hi> Commands another, and the Lord <hi>Widdrington</hi> another. Hereby it was provided by the army's being put into ſuch ſafe hands, that it ſhould no more be ſubject to the rebellious contrivances of agitators, or any others who ſhould ſeek to ſtir them up to rebellion or ſedition; nor was this all, for his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency not onely alter'd their commanders, but ſtrictly charg'd that every ſouldier ſhould take the oathes of ſupremacy and allegiance to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> and that none ſhould be new liſted, or paſs the muſters that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed it.</p>
            <p>The City about this time calling to mind the injury which the Rump had offered not onely to the perſon but the effigies of His late moſt Sacred Majeſty, which they had taken down from all the publick places in the City where it had been ſet up, cauſed another ſtatue to be ſet up in the place of that which
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:40427:64"/>was taken down from the Exchange with this Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Monarcharum Mag. Brit. Secundus</l>
               <l>Franciae &amp; Hiberniae Rex,</l>
               <l>Martyr, ad coelum miſſus</l>
               <l>Penultimo Jan. Anno Dom. <hi>1648.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>The Scepter in his right hand, A Church in his left, A Globe at his left foot, and on his Shield MAGNA CHARTA.</p>
            <p>As alſo another to be ſet up repreſenting the pourtraiture of His Sacred Majeſty that now is, with this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Monarcharum Mag. Brit. Tertius</l>
               <l>Franciae &amp; Hiberniae Rex,</l>
               <l>Aetat. ſuae Anno triceſimo, Regni duodecimo,</l>
               <l>Reſtorationis primo,</l>
               <l>Anno Dom. <hi>1660.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>The Scepter in his right hand In his left the Globe, and on his Shield AMNESTIA.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mis Majeſty</hi> alſo ſet forth a Proclamation for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calling all Commiſſions at ſea, granted by himſelf or his Royal Brother before the firſt of <hi>May</hi> laſt; willing and commanding every of them to forbear further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the ſaid Commiſſions, under ſuch penalties upon diſobedience as may be legally inflicted upon pirates, and likewiſe requiring all his Subjects employ'd in ſea affaires by any forraigne Prince to repaire home to <hi>His Majeſties</hi> ſervice.</p>
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:40427:64"/>
            <p>It was now time ſeeing <hi>His Majesty</hi> reſtor'd, to think of reſtoring him his revenues, but the Parliament ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them ſo waſted and imbezeled by the devaſtations of the times, are willing to ſupply that want by grant of that impoſition commonly called Tunnage and Pound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, which they prepare with all ſpeed, together with an Act for Pole-money and continuing the excize till the 20. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> to all which three Acts <hi>His Majeſty</hi> ſoon after coming to the Houſe gave his Royal aſſent and confirmation. Which as it was their own Act, ſo was <hi>His Majeſty</hi> willing that no other Act of theirs ſhould ſeem to proceed from force or violence upon them, and therefore at length to take away any ſuch ſuſpition, the guards were diſcharg'd from their atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the Houſes, who being now upon the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of their duty to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> and the honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervice of their Country were not thought to want any other ſecurity then the hearts and affections of the people, who think they muſt have an eſteem for them, who are ſo ready to ſerve their Soveraigne, from whom they receive ſuch benefits not only in health but in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>His Majeſty</hi> having ſince he came into <hi>England</hi> touch'd and heald above 2000. perſons.</p>
            <p>On the 13. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> ſeverall proclamations were procaim'd, one againſt fighting Duells, whereby <hi>His Majeſty</hi> ſtrictly commands all his Subjects, that they doe not by themſelves or any others, either by meſſage, word, writing, or otherwiſe, challenge or cauſe to be challenged, any perſon or perſons to ſight in Duell, nor to carry, accept or conceale any challenge, nor actually to ſight or be a ſecond to any therein.</p>
            <p>That the offenders ſhall not onely incur <hi>His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> diſpleaſure, but be incapable of any office or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment;</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:40427:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>That perſons that know and conceal ſuch challenges, ſhall be liable to the ſame penalties.</p>
            <p>In the concluſion <hi>His M jeſty</hi> doth deny and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid any interceſſion to be made for ſuch offenders, declaring that his pardon ſhall not extend to them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was for the diſcovery of goods con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, belonging either to his late Father, Queen, or himſelf.</p>
            <p>The third for calling in and ſuppreſſing of two books written by <hi>John Milton,</hi> the one intituled <hi>Joannis Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toni Angli defenſio pro populo Anglicano contra Claudes Anonymi alios Salmaſii defenſionem regiam;</hi> the other in Anſwer to a book intituled, <hi>The portraicture of His Sacred Majeſty in his ſolitudes and ſufferings,</hi> and alſo a third book written by <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> called the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor as <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> while he is doing juſtice and ſettling the government here, unmindfull of ſecuring <hi>Ireland,</hi> to which purpoſe His grace the Duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemarly</hi> is conſtituted Lord Lieutenant, <hi>His Majeſty</hi> thinking it no way prejudiciall to entruſt the ſecurity of one of his Kingdomes in thoſe hands, which have been the ſafety of all three.</p>
            <p>About the 21. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> was publiſh'd an Act for the continuance of the Exciſe till the 25. of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturday Auguſt</hi> 25. His Excellency to eaſe the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and charge of the Kingdome, did diſpatch expreſſe orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to the ſeverall Regiments of the Army, to take no more Officers or Souldiers into any place vacant by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eath or otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Upon the eight of <hi>Auguſt His Majeſty</hi> went to the Parliament. At his coming into the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, the Speaker made a ſpeech to <hi>His Majeſty,</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:40427:65"/>wherein he firſt took notice how great a bleſſing God had powr'd upon the nation in reſtoring <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to his Dominions, and lawfull inheritance.</p>
            <p>That the eminent vertues &amp; excellent qualifications which God had beſtowed upon <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> to make him every way ſit for government, did invite the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to give <hi>His Majeſty</hi> a cheerfull accompt of their proceedings.</p>
            <p>Then he reckon'd up thoſe bills that did already at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Royall Aſſent.</p>
            <p>The firſt was <hi>an Act for the confirmation of Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory proceedings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond was <hi>an Act to prevent the taking of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive uſury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third was <hi>an Act for a perpetuall Anniverſary thanksgiving to be obſerved and kept upon the twenty ninth of May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth was <hi>an Act for a ſpeedy proviſion of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to pay off and disband all the forces of this kingdome by ſea and land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt was <hi>an Act of free and generall pardon, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity and Oblivion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the concluſion of his ſpeech, they made known to <hi>His Majeſty that they had nothing more to ask or offer at that time, but that as ſoon as</hi> His Majeſties <hi>occaſions would permit them to adjourn and goe into their own Countries, where they ſhould make</hi> His Majeſties <hi>Subjects ſenſible of the Happineſs they had in having ſuch a King, to Rule and Govern over them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſty</hi> having given His Royal aſſent to all theſe Bills and paſs'd them, made a ſhort Speech to the <hi>Houſe, Wherein he told them that no man had more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiently long'd to have thoſe Bills paſs'd, then he had done to paſs them; as the foundation of much ſecurity and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:40427:66"/>happineſs to the Nation. That he did very willingly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all that was pardon'd in the Act of Indempnity. But for the time to come the ſame diſcretion and Conſcience, which had dispoſed Him to the Clemency which he then expreſs'd, which was most agreeable to his nature; would oblige him to all rigour and ſeverity, how contrary ſoever to His nature toward thoſe who ſhould not now acquieſce, but continue to manifeſt their ſedition and diſlike of the Government. That never any King valu'd more the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of His people then he did; nor did He know any way to make Himſelf ſure of His peoples affections, then by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſt and kind to all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He thank'd them for the Pole-Bill, not that it came into His Coffers; but for the other grand intent of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding the Army, and diſcharging the Navy which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things he <hi>earneſtly pray'd</hi> them to diſpatch. He hinted to them the uneſtabliſhment of His Revenue, yet told them that that was not the thing which did trouble him, and therefore bid them but <hi>take care of the publick, and for what was neceſſary for the good and quiet of the Kingdom, and take their own time for His own particular,</hi> which he was ſure they would provide for with as much affection and Franckneſs as he could deſire.</p>
            <p>The chief heads of the act of Oblivion were as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. <hi>That</hi> His Majeſty <hi>taking into conſideration the long and great Troubles, Diſcords, and Warrs which had been for many yeares in this Kingdom; and that for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon divers of His Subjects had incurr'd ſeverall penalties; and being piouſly dispos'd to put an end to all Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, which by reaſon of theſe late troubles might happen between His Subjects; and to the intent that no crime com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt</hi> His Majeſty <hi>or</hi> His Father <hi>may riſe in ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gment for the time to come againſt any of the offenders to endammage them either in their Lives, Liberties, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:40427:66"/>or Reputation by any reproach or term of diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and to bury too for the time to come all the ſeeds of diviſions, that they may be obliterated both in His own breaſt, and in the breast of every one of His Subjects: And for the fulfilling His Royal Word given in His Letters and Declaration ſent to the two</hi> Houſes <hi>of</hi> Parliament. His Majeſty <hi>with the advice and conſent of the</hi> Lords <hi>and</hi> Commons aſſembled <hi>in</hi> Parliament <hi>doth declare, that all ſorts of Treaſons, concealment of Treaſons, Murders, Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Offences, Crimes, Miſcarriages, Mispriſions, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, Counſelled, Executed or Committed ſince the firſt of</hi> January 1637. <hi>by any perſon before the fourth of</hi> June 1660. <hi>(except the perſons hereafter excepted by name) by vertue, or under colour of the Authority of the deceaſed King, or of</hi> His Majeſty <hi>now Raigning, or of the two</hi> Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>of</hi> Parliament, <hi>of any Convention calling it ſelf a</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>of any calling themſelves Keepers of the liberty of</hi> England, <hi>of any one calling himſelf Protector of the Re-publick of</hi> England, <hi>or Magiſtrate in chief, ſhall be pardon'd, acquitted, diſcharged, and be forever forgotten, and all the ſaid Perſons, their Heirs and Executors, are diſcharg'd from all paines of death and other Penalties, Accuſations, Convictions, judgments, &amp;c. which are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null'd by theſe preſents, and the ſaid Perſons are esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd in their poſſeſſions, inheritances and goods forfeited to</hi> His Majeſty <hi>for the ſaid offences. That no arrerages of Rents of any Lands or Tenements receiv'd, paid, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpos'd of, during the ſaid Troubles under the ſaid Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, or pretended Authorities; except thoſe of the Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of the Cuſtoms and Exciſe, and others afterwards excepted; be demanded back again. That the Act ſhall be as availeable to all in generall, as if it took notice of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans name and crime in particular: That thoſe who ſhall moleſt any perſon for any of the Offences already par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:40427:67"/>in the Act, ſhall be oblig'd to pay the Plaintiff treble dammages and the charges of the ſuit; and ſhall pay to</hi> His Majeſty 10. <hi>l.</hi> ſter. <hi>for every ſuch falſe actions, and all the proceedings upon ſuch ſuit ſhall be made null and void. That all Murders, Papacies, Sodomie, Rapes, Stealing and Marrying young women without conſent of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, marriage of two wives, or having two husbands, invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of spirits, conjurations, witchcrafts, enchantments, and charmes ſhall be excepted out of this preſent act; as alſo thoſe that are accountable for ſubſidie-mony, Cuſtoms, Taxes, Exciſe, Sequeſtrations, or for any of the rents of the</hi> King, Queen, Prince; <hi>or for the goods of the Church, or of Papiſts, Recuſants after the year</hi> 1642. <hi>yet ſhall not their Heires or Executors be charged at all, unleſs there be any ſummes of money yet remaining in their hands unpaid after the ſtating of the account. That no man ſhall be charg'd for money receiv'd by way of Salary, though under an illegall Authority. That the acquittances of the Exchequer ſhall be of force from the year</hi> 1642. <hi>That perjuries, ſubordinations of witneſſes, detentions of any of the</hi> Kings, Queens <hi>or</hi> Princes <hi>goods, excepting the Ships and Magazines ſhall be excepted out of this act of pardon, as alſo offences committed by</hi> Prieſts, Jeſuits, <hi>and</hi> Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries <hi>againſt the Statute of</hi> 27. Eliz. <hi>That the Act ſhall not extend to diſcharge any obligation not yet received. That all acts of hostility ſhall be pardon'd, and all names of diſtinction utterly aboliſh'd; upon the penalty of ten pound to every one that ſhall uſe them: That the perſons guilty of the Rebellion in</hi> Ireland <hi>ſhall be excepted, as alſo thoſe who have receiv'd any money upon the act for Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, of which they ſhall give an account: that thoſe who have been employ'd by</hi> His Majeſty, <hi>and have prov'd traitors and correſponded with His enemies ſhall be excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, being convicted in two yeares. That</hi> Sir Mich. Liveſey,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:40427:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>Mr. Walton, Harriſon, Whalley, Liſle, Say, Scroop, Okey, Huſon, Goff, Berkſtead, Holland, Ludlow, Tho: Chaloner, Carew, Jo: Jones, Corbet, Smith, Clement, Scot, Cawley, Love, Dixewell, Blagrave, Cooke, Broughton, Dendi, Hewlett, Peters, Hacker, and Axtell, Sir Hardreſſe Waller, Mr. Row, Garland, Harvey, Smith, Martin, Titchburn, G. Fleetwood, J. Temple, P. Temple, Waite, Mayne, Heveningham, Pennigton, Lilburn, Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington, Potter, Wogan, and Downs, <hi>and the two perſons that were diſguis'd upon the Scaffold, when the horrible Murder of His late Majeſty wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> committed, ſhall be wholly excluded from pardon; and in caſe any of them ſhall be attainted and convicted, that execution ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd in regard of the ſaid Sir</hi> Hardreſſe Waller, <hi>and the</hi> 18. <hi>nominated after him, till new orders from His Majeſty and the two Houſes of Parliament. That</hi> O. Cromwel, H. Ireton, J. Bradſhaw, and Tho: Pride, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, ſhall be alſo excluded from this pardon, and their goods and the Goods of Sir</hi> John Danvers, Tho: Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer, Sir Will. Conſtable, G. Norton, Sir John Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chier, deceaſed, and the goods of I. Eure, G. Purefoy, J. Blackeſton, R. Deane, F. Alleyne, P. Pelham, John Moor, J. Allured, H. Edwards, J. Venn, T. Andrews, A. Stapeley, T. Norton, J. Foy, and T. Hammon <hi>ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch ſequeſtrations as the Parliament ſhall order.</hi> That Mr. F. Laſtells <hi>ſhall pay a yeares Revenue of his Eſtate, and be incapable of bearing any publick Office; as alſo</hi> Sir John Hutchinſon. <hi>That</hi> Sir Gilbert Pickering, Mr. W. Lenthall, G. Burton, O. St. John, J. Ireton, W. Sydenham, J. Desbrough, J. Blackwell, C. Pack, R. Keeble, C. Fleetwood, J. Pine, R. Deane, R. Creed, P. Nye, J. Goodwin, J. Liſter, and R. Cobett <hi>ſhall be unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any publick Office, and they do except them, they ſhall loſe the benefit of this preſent act. That</hi> Lambert
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:40427:68"/>
               <hi>and</hi> Vane <hi>ſhall be wholly fore priz'd out of the ſaid act. That all perſons ſitting in illegall high Courts of Juſtice, and that gave ſentence againſt</hi> His Majeſty, <hi>ſhall be uncapable of bearing any publick Office, except</hi> Col. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>golsby and Col. Tomlinſon. <hi>That</hi> Sir Arthur Haſlerig <hi>ſhall not be excepted for life. That the Kings, Queens, and Biſhops Lands ſhall be reſtored.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some few dayes after the comming forth of this Act, <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> a moſt notorious incendiary, and of moſt miſchievous principles, was taken lurking in <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark.</hi> His apprehe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion is the more conſiderable in regard of his intimate acquaintance with <hi>Cromwells</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, who is thought employ'd him in the deteſtable butchery of His late Majeſty, or if not him, ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whoſe name and perſon he is able to diſcover.</p>
            <p>As to forraign affaires relating unto this Kingdom, there was not much which happen'd remarkable, onely the comming of Embaſſadors from ſeveral parts, as from <hi>Holland, Denmarke, France,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> who were ſent by their ſeveral Princes to congratulate the return of His Majeſty into <hi>England;</hi> though there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo pleaſing to the Merchant as the Peace like to be with <hi>Spaine,</hi> (in regard that the Protectors Warre with that Nation being ill-manag'd had prov'd very fatal to them) and therefore they were not a little joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to think they ſhould recover their former loſſes by a new Peace; which we muſt now believe cannot be long unconcluded, in regard that about the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this moneth, a ceſſation of Armes between both Kingdoms was publickly Proclaimed in <hi>London,</hi> to the great content of the whole Nation, who before theſe Warres were no ſmall gainers by their Peace with that Country.</p>
            <p>Thus have I given the Reader a brief draught of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:40427:68"/>the ſeries of our affaires, from the murder of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt to this preſent time, wherein may be ſeen how the Nation has been ridden theſe dozen years at ſwitch and ſpur in a Common-wealth ſaddle. I ſhall ſumme up all in a brief Character of His moſt Sacred Majeſty, though what I ſhall ſay herein will come as far ſhort of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Endowments as the Light of a Candle to that of the Sun.</p>
            <p>He is of ſtature ſomewhat tall, yet ſo exactly formed, that the moſt Curious Eye cannot find one Error in his ſhape; his face is rather grave then ſevere, which is very much ſoftned whenſoever he ſpeaks. His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion is ſomewhat dark, but much Enlightned by his Eyes which are quick and ſparkling; his hair which he hath in great plenty is of a ſhining black, not frizled but naturally curling into great Rings, that it is a very comely Ornament for his acquired Endowments; he underſtands Spaniſh and Italian, ſpeakes and writes French correctly: he is very well verſed in Ancient and Modern hiſtory, hath read divers choice pieces of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks, ſtudied ſome uſefull parts of the Mathematicks, as Fortification, and the Knowledge of the Globe, he is well skilled in Navigation: in b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ief, he is a true friend to Literature and to Learned men.</p>
            <p>During his expulſion he hath Travelled through and Lived in the Countries of three the moſt potent Princes in Chriſtendome, <hi>viz.</hi> The Emperours of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and ſo to the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Reſolution, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Prudence, &amp; the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Expedition.</p>
            <p>He is of a very ſolid judgment, not carried about with every wind of Counſel; ſo that it may be as truly ſaid of him as of his prodeceſſor <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, <hi>He that would corrupt his Council muſt firſt begin with the</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:40427:69"/>King, or as it is written of Noble <hi>Fabritius,</hi> that he could reſolve well, and having once reſolved, you might as ſoon have put the ſun out of his courſe as <hi>Fabritius</hi> from his reſolution, witneſs his ſtedfaſtneſs and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the Proteſtant Religion, notwithſtanding thoſe many ſpecious overtures made unto him by many ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till and plauſible arguments preſſed upon him to pervert him from it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
